In this demo, we're going to deploy a pod in our mini cube cluster.
As we discussed, a pod is the most basic and the smallest unit in Kubernetes.
So we will use the cube kernel command line utility to interact with the Kubernetes cluster.
Now, if you followed our demo earlier of deploying a cluster using mini cube, then you already have
the cube command line utility configured to work with the cluster.
We will run the command cube model, run Engine X, which is the name of the pod dash.
Dash image equals to engine X.
Now here is where we specify the docker image to be used.
While the pod name could be anything, the image name has to be the name of an image available at Docker
Hub or any other container registry.
You can additionally specify a tag for the image name or a different address to an image hosted on another
registry.
If the image is hosted in a place that's other than Docker Hub.
So once we run this command, we see a pod by the name and Genex has been created and you can check
the status using the cube Cardinal get Pods command.
Now here you can see the column name which is Engine X, The status is running and we see that there
is a ready column which shows the number of containers in a ready state.
We also see if the container has restarted since it was created.
And how long has the pod been running?
We can get more information related to the pod by running the cube cattle describe pod in Genex command,
and you'll notice that this provides a lot more information as compared to the get command.
So, for example, the name of the pod is in X.
It shows any labels that has been assigned to this pod.
So this was created by default when we ran the run command.
It shows when it was started, it shows the node that is that it is assigned to along with the IP address
of the node.
So in this case we just have a single node cluster set up using mini cube and the node name is Mini
Cube and that is the IP address of this worker node.
Secondly, it also shows the IP address of the port itself.
So in this case the pod is assigned an IP of one 72.16 .0.3.
We'll cover more about the IP addresses of the pod later in the networking section.
Now moving on, we can see that it displays information related to the container so we know that there
is a single container which uses the image engine X.
If there were multiple containers, we would list them here.
I'll explain about creating a pod with multiple containers in the upcoming lectures, but here we can
also see that the engine X image was pulled from Docker Hub.
And if you scroll all the way to the bottom, you'll see additional information called events.
And here you see the list of events that occurred since the pod was created.
It went through multiple stages before it started.
We can see that the pod was assigned to the mini cube node.
If there were multiple nodes, you would see which node the pod was assigned to here, and then it entered
the pulling phase where the engine X image was pulled down from Docker Hub successfully.
And then the container called Engine X was created and started.
Now there is one other command that we can use to check the status of the pod, and that is the same
command as before.
The cube car will get pod command but with the dash wide option.
And this provides additional information such as the node where the pod is running and the IP address
of the pod as well.
So this is the internal IP address of the pod itself.
So each pod gets an internal IP of its own within the within the Kubernetes cluster.
But more on that later.
That was a quick demonstration on how to run a pod in mini cube environment.
In the upcoming videos, we will see how to create a pod using a YAML definition file.