In this lecture, we will look at conditionals.
Let us start with a simple example.
I have two playbooks here that does the same thing.
Install engine X on a host, but as you know, different OS flavors.
Use different package managers, debian users, APT and redhat users.
Yum.
But these are two separate playbooks and you will have to use the right playbook for the respective
servers.
I want to create a single playbook that works for both of these operating systems for all hosts.
So based on the operating system flavor, my playbook must run the appropriate task.
And that's where a conditional statement comes in handy.
I could use the when conditional statement to specify a condition for each task.
Only if the condition is true, that task is run.
So what is a condition?
It could be any check that we perform, such as checking in if the OS family is debian or red hat ansible
underscore os and a score family is a built in variable that ansible populates with the flavor of operating
system.
Make sure to use double equals sign when checking equality in conditional statement.
You may use an ore operator to specify either of two conditions.
Use the Yum module to install package if the OS family is Red Hat or Susie or an and operator.
So it must satisfy both conditions.
In this case we use the apt module only if the OS family is Debian and the version is 16.04.
You may use conditionals in a loop as well.
Say, for example, instead of a single package, we have a list of packages that needs to be installed.
We have an array named packages that has to list.
Each item in the list has the name of the package to be installed as well as a property called required.
Install the packages only if the required property is set to true.
First, we specify the loop directive to execute the install task in a loop.
The name of the package to be installed is now item name and this will install all three packages specified.
To visualize this better.
If you kind of expand the loop, you will see that the loop is in fact three different tasks, one for
each package.
Each task has the variable on it called item, and the item has the respective package details.
So if I wanted to write a conditional for each of the item, I would say when item dot required equals
true.
And so back in my main playbook, that's what I would put in when item required equals true.
And that's how you use conditionals in loops.
Let's look at one final example.
To use conditionals with the output of a previous task, we have a requirement to develop a playbook
to check the status of a service and email if it's done.
So there are two tasks.
The first task checks the status of a service, and the second task sends an email.
We have learned previously that to record the output of one task, we could use the Registered directive.
So we say register the output to the result variable.
And then in the second task we use the when conditional on that result variable to say check if result
dot std out has down in it.
The find method looks for a string within a variable and returns its position.
If it's not found, it returns minus one.
So our condition would be if it's not minus one, meaning that the output does not contain the word
down.
Send an email.
Well, that's it for now.
Head over to the coding challenges and practice working with conditionals.