In this lecture, we will look at loops.
Let's look at this example where we are creating an Ansible playbook to create users and a system using
the user module.
The user module helps you create users on the target systems.
In this case, we are just creating one user.
But what if we have multiple users?
What if we have a lot of users to create?
Well, one way to do this would be to duplicate these lines as many times as required.
But that is not very elegant and as there is a lot of duplication.
A better way to do this would be to have a single task loop over all the users.
That's where we use loops.
Loop is a looping directive that executes the same task multiple number of times each time it runs.
It stores the value of each item in the loop in a variable named item.
So you can simply replace the user name in this case Joe with the item variable inside double braces
like this.
This makes your playbooks much more organized and with reduced repetition.
In this case, you are not repeating the lines of the user module or the state.
If you didn't get how the part about item works, let me visualize that for you.
So any time you come across a playbook probably written by someone else and the loop part is confusing,
I would recommend visualizing it like this for visualization purposes.
A loop would break down into multiple tasks within each task.
You have a variable defined which is by default named item, and it has the value of each item in the
list.
In this case, the loop breaks down into ten or more tasks that uses the same user module.
Each task has a variable item whose value is set to each item in the loop.
The first task has the value of items at Joe, the second with George, third Ravi, and so on it goes.
When the playbook is executed, this is how it will be run.
In this case, the loop is an array of string values.
Just the usernames.
But what if I want to specify the user ID as well?
That would mean each item in the loop would have to have two values the username and the user ID.
But how do you pass into values in an array instead of passing in an array of strings to the loop?
I would pass in an array of dictionaries.
Each dictionary will have two key value pairs.
The keys would be name and UID, and values would be name and IDs of each user.
If you do that, what would you specify inside the task?
You can no longer use just item because item is now not just a string.
So let's try to visualize that to find out what you can specify inside the command.
As before.
Let's break down the loop into multiple tasks.
We'll just look at the first four.
Each task uses the same module and parameters.
We still don't know what to specify for name or UID, and we can see that each task has a variable item
defined.
How does item look in this case as before?
Move each item in the loop under the item variable in the tasks.
We can now see that the item variable inside each task in the loop is a dictionary which has the name
and UID of each user.
So within each task to get the user name, I could do item name and to get user ID, I could do item
UID.
And that is what we will have in the task section back in our playbook.
So that's how loops work with an array of strings and array of dictionaries with array of dictionaries.
Remember that you could simply use item property name in the dictionary to get an item within each dictionary
in the list.
But I did all of that to show you how it works when the data in the array gets really complex, using
this kind of visualization technique of breaking the loop down might help you understand it a little
bit better.
Also note that an array of dictionary can also be represented like this in a JSON format.
The Loop directive we just saw are used to create simple loops that iterate over a lot of items.
There's another way to create loops in playbooks, and that is using the width underscore directives.
This playbook that we developed can also be written using the width underscore items directive like
this.
In fact, the loop directive is newly added in Ansible.
In the past we just had the width underscore items directive.
In this case, both playbooks yield the same results and there is no much difference between the two.
For a simple lubes like the ones we have been working on.
It is recommended to use the LUBE Directive itself.
However, in some of the older playbooks you might come across the with Items directive, so you should
understand what that means when you when you see that.
Now let's look at the advantage of the width directives with items.
Just iterates over a list of items.
We have other directives such as with files that iterate over multiple files with a URL that connects
to multiple URLs with MongoDB that connects to multiple MongoDB databases.
And these are just a few.
So are these all or are there more?
If so, how many are there?
It so happens that these are just a few among the many white directives available.
In fact, everything you see after the width underscore string is a lookup plugin.
So whatever lookup plugin you have or you create you can use with underscore with that.
So what are lookup plugins?
Well, just think of them as custom scripts that can do specific tasks like read files, connect to
a URL or connect to a database or connect to other systems like Kubernetes or OpenShift.
Well, more on that some other time.
For now, let's head over to coding exercises and practice working with loops.