In this lecture, we discuss about roles in Ansible.
Just like how you would assign roles to different people in the real world, making them doctors, engineers,
astronauts, policemen or chef.
In the Ansible world, you would assign roles to blank servers to make them a database server or a web
server or a Redis messaging server or a backup server.
Assigning a role in the real world means doing everything one needs to do to make someone, a doctor,
an engineer, like, for example, sending the person to a medical school, earning a medical degree,
completing a residency program, and finally obtaining a license to practice, or with an engineer,
it would be going to an engineering school, earning a bachelor's degree, gaining field experience,
or getting a postgraduate degree in the automation world.
Assigning a role means doing everything you need to do to make a server a database server, such as
installing the prerequisites required for MySQL, installing MySQL packages themselves, configuring
the MySQL servers and finally configuring database or users.
With a web server, it would be again installing the prerequisites for engine X, installing engine
X packages, configuring Engine X services and configuring the custom web pages.
By now we know how to get these tasks done using Ansible playbooks.
We have done this a lot.
Here's a simple playbook that that can do this.
But then if you can do this in a playbook, why do you need roles?
This set of tasks to install and perform basic configurations on a MySQL database is going to remain
mostly common.
Once a person develops this Ansible playbook, it can be shared with hundreds of thousands of others
trying to do the same thing.
Install my SQL instead of all of them rewriting this piece of code and you could package it into a role
and reuse it later.
Next time you could simply assign the role you created.
And in a playbook like this, be it a single server or hundreds of servers, that's all you need.
So that's the primary purpose of roles to make your work reusable, be it for other tasks or projects
within your organization or outside for others globally.
Roles also help in organising your code within Ansible.
Roles introduce a set of best practices that must be followed to organize all tasks into a task directory.
All variables used by these tasks in the Advanced Directory.
Any default values goes into the default directory.
All handlers go into the handlers directory and any templates used by the playbooks go into the templates
directory.
Roles also help in sharing your code with others in the Ansible community.
Ansible Galaxy is one such community where you can find thousands of roles for almost any task you can
think of.
Installing and configuring different web servers, different database servers, automation tools, monitoring
tools, packaging tools, security software, etc..
So before you start writing those playbooks, I highly recommend taking a look at this community first.
There must be a role created for that already by someone.
So how do you get started with roles?
It's easy.
As we discussed in the previous slide.
First, we create the directory structure required for a role, but you don't have to do that manually.
Ansible Galaxy has a neat tool that can create a skeleton for you.
Use the ansible galaxy init command to initialize and create a directory structure.
Remember this is to create your own role from scratch and then move all of your code into the task directory
into a file.
And that's it.
So how do you use your role within your playbook?
Say I have my playbook within a directory called My Playbook.
My playbook YAML file contains a simple play to install and configure my SQL on my DB server.
I would like to assign the role I created using the roles directive like this.
But if I were to do that, how does my playbook know where that role is?
I could have created that role anywhere on my system.
How can my playbook find that role?
There are different ways to do that.
I could create a directory called Roles within my Playbook folder and move the role I created under
it.
When the playbook runs, Ansible looks for a role named my SQL under the roles directory, and that's
one way of doing it.
Or you can move the roles to a common directory designated for roles on your system at Etsy Ansible
roles location.
That's the default location where Ansible searches for roles if it can be found in your playbooks directory.
Of course, that's defined in the Ansible configuration file as roles path, which you can modify if
required.
Once you have created your role and place it in your roles directory and used it in a playbook, you
may share it with the community by uploading it to Ansible Galaxy through a GitHub repository.
Now what if you don't want to use a roll from Galaxy?
Instead, you want to find an existing role and use it in your playbook to find roles.
You could search from the Ansible Galaxy UI or do it from the command line interface using the Ansible
Galaxy Search Command.
To use a role.
Run the Ansible Galaxy install command with the name of the role.
The role is extracted to the default roles directory at SC Ansible roles Location.
The roles can now be used in your playbook by specifying the same name like this as an array of strings
as role names.
Another way to specify roles as an array of dictionaries.
This will allow you to pass in additional options to the role, such as to execute the role by escalating
privileges, by specifying the become directory or to pass additional parameters like the MySQL SQL
underscore user underscore name option like this.
To summarize rules make it really easy to develop, reuse and share Ansible playbooks to configure a
single server with both database and web application on it.
Assign both roles to it to configure it separately on separate servers.
Create two plays in the playbook one for each server and assign the respective roles to them.
To view a list of roles currently installed or on the Ansible Galaxy List command to view the location
where roles would be installed.
Check the ansible configuration using the ansible config dump command.
The default role path is where the roles are installed.
While installing rolls.
You may use the dash p option to install it in the current directory under roles like this.
Well, that's it for this lecture.