Hey, everyone.
I'm Lydia, Hailey, and I'll be your instructor for this Gift for Beginners course on Code Cloud.
Throughout my career as a software developer, I've also mentored a lot of new and advanced developers
in order to help them improve and optimize their work.
And by writing technical blog posts in a more visual way, I try to make those overwhelming computer
science concepts seem less overwhelming.
And one of those topics is get through this course.
I want to show you that git is actually an amazing tool to work with and I want to make you a fearless
git developer.
In this course, you'll learn how to get up and running with gates, how to use it in your daily life,
and how it actually works under the hood.
We'll cover the possibilities of having a local and remote git repository and adding version control
to your project by using branches.
And of course we'll cover all the useful commands that you can use with these branches to make working
with get even more powerful besides some common gate commands.
We'll also cover how Git actually works under the hood in order to get a better understanding of what
we're actually doing.
After each section, you'll get to test your new information with the hands on labs in order to fully
grasp the new concepts you'll work as if you're working on a real project with real team members.
So you have to push code, pull code, resolve, merge conflicts, and will validate it in order to
make sure that you actually understood it correctly.
I am really excited to be teaching this interactive course on Git and I hope you are too.
So let's dive right in.