JIT has two repository types, local and remote.
The local repository is on your own machine, so you have direct access to it.
The remote repository is usually a centralized server and is entirely optional.
We can save the changes that we made locally on this remote server.
The remote repository is very useful when you want to have a backup of your data in case your computer
breaks or when you're working with a team.
Teammates can initialize their own local repository on their own computers and simply pull the data
from the remote repository in order to start working on your project.
When one of the team members has made some changes, they can push these changes to the remote repository
in order to keep your local and remote repository in sync.
You can then pool these changes from the remote repository into your local repository.
The local repository actually consists of three stages.
The working area are all your active changes.
Git doesn't know what to do with them yet.
It just knows that these files contain some updates.
The staging area contains new changes that will soon be committed.
And then there are the committed files.
Previously we looked at the use case of Git and we saw that people could add their change and save new
states of the project each time.
What we're actually looking at here are commits.
People can commit their changes in order to add version control to the project.
The files that should be included in the commit are first added to the staging area.
A commit gets created when a developer actually commits those files.