First, let's initialize a local git repository by going into our project folder and initializing git.
We can initialize git by typing git init.
In your terminal you can see that we initialize an empty git repository in a git folder.
When you execute the LZ a command in order to list all the contents of the folder, including hidden
folders such as the git folder, you can see that the git folder has been created.
Later on in the course, I'll talk more about what Kit actually does and the contents of the git folder.
But for now, it's just important to understand the flow of git.
Let's add a file to our project.
It's going to be a simple text file with a very basic sentence.
We've just made a new file and edit the text.
This is a beautiful story to it.
I'm proud of my creation and I want to make sure that I save the current state the project is in.
So I'm going to save that to my local git repository.
Now that we've added the text file, let's see if get saw that I made a change, although we haven't
done anything with it yet.
We initialized a git repository in this project so git knows all of our files and their changes.
You can see the status of git by executing the git status command.
Let's see step by step what this output actually means.
First on branch master.
We haven't covered branches yet.
However, Git allows you to work on your code and have multiple states of your code base.
Your default branch is the master branch as we haven't made any new branches yet.
We're still on the default master branch.
No commits yet.
Storing changes in our local git repository is called committing with every commit.
We save the current state of the repository and show the changes that we made to it.
We haven't done so yet.
So there are no commits yet, as Gib tells us.
Untracked files.
These are the files that get nose off.
However, we haven't told yet what to do with them.
We haven't told it yet that we want to add it to our local repository, for example.
So they're still untracked right now.
We haven't told yet what to do with the new story.
One txt file.
It might be that we don't want to add that story to our local repository at all.
However, I want to commit my change.
Before we can commit a file, we first have to put it in the staging area.
We can put it in the staging area with a good ad command.
You run the get ad command with the files that we want to add to the staging area.
In this case, I want to add the story OneNote text file to the staging area.
So I execute git add story OneNote txt.
Perfect.
Now it's time to commit our change.
A commit records the change of a repository compared to its previous state.
In this case, we didn't have any previous commits.
So the addition of the file story, one text is a change compared to its previous state.
In order to commit the files that are currently in the staging area, we run the Git Command AM command
with a useful message right after the RM is a flick from message.
When you make a commit, it's very good practice to summarize the change that you just made in a very
short sentence.
This way you can easily track down when you made certain changes and your teammates also know what you've
been doing.
In this case, I'm committing my first story, so I'm going to add the message.
Added First story.
We just created our very first commit.
The changes have been saved and we can reset our project to this exact state at any point in the future.