Hello and welcome to this demo.
This is an optional demo.
In most cases, you should be able to just go straight from the lecture to the labs.
But in case you need a bit more hand-holding and need to see things in action, then you may follow
this demo.
In this demo we will focus on the different stages.
A file can be in your working area.
So let's start by creating a new file named story.
One txt.
So I already have a git repository initialized in the story block directory and we're going to create
a new file named story one txt with some sample contents.
Now, when a file is created for the first time, it is always in the working area in the untracked
state.
If we feel that the story is ready to be committed, we can add the story to the staging area using
the Git ad command.
When you now run the git status command, we see that it is green and it is in a state named changes
to be committed.
That means it's in a staging state.
It's in the staging area and then we commit it using the git commit command.
Now before committing git needs to know who you are because all commits are recorded by the name of
an author.
So you must use the git config command with the username and user email properties to set the username
and email address of that user.
When you type git commit command without any options, git opens a text editor whichever is the default
text editor configured is usually the VI editor and here you provide a message, a commit message.
Every commit needs to have a meaningful message that tells exactly what that commit does.
Very briefly.
So we go to the insert mode and we type in a message added for story and then we save and quit the editor.
As soon as we quit, the changes are saved with the commit message we provided, which can be seen here.
It shows the commit message and the number of files that were added or changed and the name of the file
that was committed.
So what exactly is a comet?
A comet stores a copy of the file in its current state.
One file or a set of files that were committed.
So it saves a copy of the entire file or a set of files within the Git folder.
Our work is now safe even if the file gets corrupted or we made some changes to it that we were not
supposed to.
We can restore the saved or committed version of the file later.
So how exactly does it save and in what format does it save?
All of that?
We will discuss towards the end of this course in a lecture named Understanding Git.
For now, just know that with each commit get internally stored a copy of all the files that were committed.
Now if we run the Git status command, we see that the working area is clean.
The next time the file is modified, it moves into a modified state.
The previous version of file, which was committed is still as is in the previous commit history.
It is the current version of the file that's now in a modified state.
If this change was accidental, then we could restore the previous version of the file from the previous
commit by running the Git restore command as it is shown here.
So when you do that, the current version of the file is updated with the contents of the file from
the previous commit.
Now, since there are no changes between the current and the previous commit, now the working area
is now clean again.
Now let's say we knowingly updated the file and then we are ready to commit the changes again.
And this time we follow the same process of staging the file using the Git ad command and then committing
it using the git commit command.
However, this time we will use the option git commit WM to pass in the commit message.
This way we can avoid going into the text editor and then typing in the message and then coming out
of the text editor.
Right.
So we will save with the message updated first story and now git creates a new commit and stores a new
copy of the current version of the story in that comment.
The previous version we committed earlier and the current version of the file lives in gets commit history
forever, allowing us to go back in time to any previous date or commit and look at the story at that
time.
Now let's say we modify story one text like last time, but we also added a new story story to text.
If we check the status now we see that story to txt is an untracked state as as expected and story one
is in a modified state.
If we wish to, we could stage and commit them together.
So running the git ad dot command will stage both of these files at once and then running the git commit
command will commit both of these files in git.
So our new commit now has a copy of both the files we committed.
In large projects, a single commit may have many, many such files and get what store a copy of all
the files changed on that comet.
Now, that's okay.
If all the changes were made as part of the same requirement.
So, for example, if multiple files were changed as part of a bug fix or feature ad operation, then
this is completely okay.
In this example, if both of these stories say we're part of a single series of story and say we are
adding a character to the story who should also be part of the second story, then those are a related
change, right?
So they should be part of the same comment.
However, say these stories were completely independent so they are not related and these should be
separate commits.
So let's go back to the previous date where story two was added and story one was updated.
And in this case we have two files in our working area.
We don't have to commit them together.
That's why we have the staging area to allow us to stage them separately and commit them.
Remember, only files in the staging area are committed, so we could first just stage story one text
alone and then commit it with a message updated for story.
And then we could stage story two and then commit that separately as story to text.
So why is it important to commit separate changes separately?
One of the best practice to be followed while committing is to make each commit atomic meaning.
Each commit should be to solve a single problem or implement a specific feature or improvement.
Each commit should have a single set of change.
Now, it doesn't mean a single file.
It could be multiple files, but it should be solving a single set of change.
In this example, we can see that Sarah added a front page and Max fixed buttons in navigation and page
added a subtitle.
These are good because all of their commits do one thing.
However, take a look at this example.
This is a bad example because each commit has multiple sets of changes made.
Sarah added the front page and also fixed the bug.
But what bug?
Does it have anything to do with the front page?
Max fixed buttons in the navigation bar and also added a subtitle.
The buttons in the navigation bar and the subtitle have nothing to do with each other, so they shouldn't
be part of the same commit page.
Fixed a few bugs and made minor improvements.
What bugs and what improvements?
And Max made two commits to solve the same bug.
That's a bad practice too.
A commit was made to update the JavaScript file to fix a button bug and another comment was made to
update the CSS file to fix the same bug.
They're both related to the same issue and so they should have been part of a single commit.
So why is it important to follow this best practice and to be atomic?
One advantage is that it maintains a clean history for the project and one that makes sense.
While working with a large team.
You'll have thousands of developers and hundreds of frequent commits and you can read the commit history
and figure out exactly what that commit was for.
Another advantage is that Git being a version control system allows you to go back in time and revert
a particular commit.
For instance, say we realized that the subtitle added by page resulted in a new bug on the website
and we can easily revert that commit alone and restore the state of the website.
And how to do that?
We'll discuss that in one of the upcoming lectures.
But for now I just know that that is a possibility with Git.
However, in the other example, if we tried to revert the commit that added the subtitle, we would
also be reverting the fixes applied on the button in the navigation bar.
But we do not want to revert those changes.
We only want to revert the change on the subtitle.
So it's always recommended to keep your commits atomic and name your commits with a message that tells
exactly what that commit does.
Now let's say we add a new line, a line for two story one.
And as expected, it's now in a modified state.
And then we stage that using the git add command and we can see that it is now staged for commit.
Now, before committing, let's say we make another change to the file.
Say we accidentally overrode the contents of the file.
Now, if you check the status now we see that story.
One is staged and also modified.
So why is that?
Why is the same file in two different stages?
Well, when you stage a file in Git, it caches the state of file when it was staged.
Meaning even before we commit a file where we know an entire copy of the file is saved, as soon as
a file is staged, a copy of the file is preserved or cached as well.
So as soon as you stage a file, you're safe.
In this case, I can restore the state of the file when it was staged using the Git restore option.
So now we have restored the file to the state that it was in when we last staged it.
Let's look at another example.
Say in the current state, we have story one in the staging area and we update story two now.
Story two is now in a modified state while story one is staged.
So let's say we want to stage and commit the changes to story two first before we actually commit story
one.
So we basically need to move story one out of the staging area and then move story two into the staging
area.
So how do we do that?
Now we can remove a file from the staging area using the command given here, which is git restored
dash dash staged option.
So we run the gate, restore story one the command with the staged option.
So now both story one and story two are in a modified state.
We took story one out of the staging area and then we will now move story two to the staging area and
then commit it by running the Git ad command and the Git command command.
Now let's look at another use case.
Let's say we add a personal file called notes txt, where we decide to store our ideas.
Now, this file is now in an untracked state as it's a new file.
Now, while staging the modified story one txt file, we accidentally add the node's file as well because
we ran the git add dot command.
Now if you check the status, we see that both these files are staged and if we do a commit now, both
of these files would be committed.
However, we don't want notes to be part of the git repository.
It's a personal file that we're going to use to store our ideas.
So we can remove a tracked file by running the git arm command.
Now you must specify a file name.
In our case, it is not txt and you also must specify one of the options either cached or false.
Now, specifying the cached option will retain the file in our directory and the force option will delete
the file permanently.
In this case, I have written down some ideas for the story in my node's file, so I don't want to delete
it.
I want to keep the file even if it is removed from the gits tracking.
So I will use the cached option while removing the file from git.
Now, if you see now we're back to the previous date where the file is still in our directory.
And when we run the Git status command, we see that it's in an untracked state.
So this is good, but it's not very good because there are chances that we might accidentally check
in this file with Kit and as we just did before.
So to instruct, get to permanently ignore this file, we use a dot git ignore file.
We add the name of the file to a new file called dot git ignore.
And now in the git status command we do not see the noticed file anymore.
However, we do see the dot git ignore file because that is also a file that git sees as a new file.
So it is a recommended practice to save the git ignore file itself in git so that when you share the
repository with others, the team can add commonly ignored files to this file such as the cache directories,
log directories, build temporary build files, etc..
Right.
So.
Well, that's it for now.
Head over to the labs and practice this by yourself.