Hello and welcome to this lecture on setting up Kubernetes.
In this lecture, we will look at the various options available in building a Kubernetes cluster.
So there are a lot of ways to set up Kubernetes.
We can set it up ourselves locally on our laptops or virtual machines using solutions like mini cube
or micro rockets.
These are solutions for developers or those who want to just play around and learn Kubernetes.
The cube admin tool is used to bootstrap and manage production grade Kubernetes clusters.
There are also hosted solutions available for setting up Kubernetes in a cloud environment such as GCP,
AWS, Azure or IBM Cloud and many others.
We also have a demo on provisioning a Kubernetes cluster on GCP, and of course, these are just a few
among the many options available to deploy a Kubernetes cluster.
So you may really follow any of these approaches to set up a Kubernetes cluster.
But to go through this course, you don't really need to set one up.
As part of this course, we give you a real Kubernetes cluster that you can access right in your browser
with the click of a button without having to set anything up.
And we have guided challenges and fun hands on lab exercises that will get you familiar with Kubernetes
in no time.
In this section of the course.
We will just start with one of these options.
The remaining examples are in the appendix section at the end of this course.
So we will start with the mini cube option, which is the easiest way to get started with Kubernetes
on a local system.
If Mini Cube is not of interest to you and you just want to rely on the online labs, then now would
be a good time to skip this lecture.
So before we head into the demo, it's good to understand how it works.
Earlier, we talked about the different components of Kubernetes that make up a master and worker node,
such as the API server, the key value store controllers and scheduler on the master and the Kubernetes
and container runtime on the worker nodes.
It will take a lot of time and effort to set up and install all of these various components on different
systems individually by ourselves.
Mini cube bundles, all of these different components into a single image, providing us a Pre-configured
single node Kubernetes cluster so we can get started in a matter of minutes.
The whole bundle is packaged into an ISO image and is available online for download.
Now.
You don't have to do that yourself.
Mini Cube provides an executable command line utility that will automatically download the ISO and deploy
it in a virtualization platform such as Oracle, VirtualBox or VMware Fusion.
So you must have a hypervisor installed on your system for Windows.
You could use VirtualBox or Hyper-V and for Linux you could use VirtualBox or KVM.
And finally, to interact with the Kubernetes cluster, you must have the Cube cuttle Kubernetes command
line tool also installed on your machine.
So you need three things to get this working.
You must have a hypervisor installed, the cube cut, utility installed and mini cube executable installed
on your system.
So we will now get into a demo.
But before that, let me quickly walk you through the hands on labs.
As I mentioned, we have hands on labs that will follow.
So once you've finished the demo, you'll see there's a quiz, and after that there's the hands on labs
and named those hands on labs.
So when you're on that lecture, you'll see a link that will take you directly to the labs hosted at
Code Cloud.
So when you go to the link, when you click on the link, it'll open up the labs and so you can quickly
read through what's here.
It's basically an introduction that says so you can just click start scenario and wait for the lab to
open up.
Okay, so you'll have a terminal and access to a real Kubernetes cluster here on the left.
And you have the quiz portal here on the right.
You can click on this this double arrow to go full screen.
That that way it's more visible.
And then you just have to go through and answer these questions.
So basically, here you have the quiz portal.
Here you have the question, read the question and try to identify the answer.
In this case, it's asking how many nodes are part of the cluster?
So by now you should know the command to get the total number of nodes.
Going to run the kip Cuddle cat nodes command.
And I see there are two.
So the answer is two.
So if you're not sure what the command is, click on the hint button and here you'll get the command.
Sometimes we give you the command or some kind of hint on how to identify that.
So here you click two and that that's successful.
And here you can see the time left for this lab and the total number of questions.
Some of these labs, we still we start with really basic and easy labs and we want to get you familiarized
with the environment.
And later on we'll have more complex labs which which will give you more experience.
And of course, in our advanced courses for the certified administrator and certified application developer
courses, we have a lot of these kind of labs and mock exams and that will help you prepare for the
exam.
So thank you very much.
And we will now head over to the demo where we'll see how to set up a cluster or quickly with mini Cube.