In this demo, we're going to install a basic Kubernetes cluster using the mini cube utility as part
of this beginner's course.
To keep things simple and easy, we will stick to Mini Cube as our lab solution.
We explore additional options of provisioning equipment in this cluster using the cube admin tool.
In this course.
As for this course, we just want to stick to the very basics and all the basic operations can be performed
on a mini cube cluster.
So we will start at the Kubernetes i o page within this website, click on the documentation section
and navigate to tasks and install tools section.
Now, before installing mini Cube, we must install the Cube CODDLE utility.
It may be called Cube Control or Cube Cuttle or Cube CTL.
Whatever you prefer, you might hear me mix it up at time, so bear with me on that.
So the cube command line tool is what we will use to manage our Kubernetes resources and our cluster
after it is set up using mini cube.
Installing the cube kernel utility before installing Mini Cube will allow Mini Cube to configure the
cube puddle utility to work with the cluster when it provisions it.
So the cube utility can work with multiple clusters, local or remote clusters at the same time, and
there's a small configuration for it.
And mini Cube will automatically take care of that when it starts when it provisions a Kubernetes cluster.
But that is if you already have the cube utility installed.
So that's important.
Now, our goal is to set up a cluster on our local machine.
I'm on Linux or Ubuntu system, but the same procedure will also work on Windows or Mac operating systems
as well.
All the demos and tools that we have throughout this course will work on all operating systems Linux,
Windows or Mac.
You just need to follow the respective installation procedure for your OS.
And to start with, I'm going to install the cube kernel utility on my Linux system and we're going
to go ahead with the latest version.
So just copy and paste the command provided here for downloading the cube kernel binary.
The binary has now been downloaded.
The next step is to make this command executable.
So I'm going to use the command mode plus X to make it executable.
And finally, we're going to move this to a location within the path user local bin.
Okay, so this way I'll be able to run this command from anywhere within my system.
So let's run the version command and you can see that it has installed the 1.18 version.
Now, what we just saw was one way of installing cube candle utility.
There are other ways to do it.
You can install it using a package manager's depending upon the type of distribution, the OS distribution
that you are on and the documentation associated with these are available here.
So if you scroll down you will see that there are instructions for installation on Mac OS and there
should be one for Windows as well.
So make sure that you use the appropriate link and set up model based on the documentation provided.
Now that we have completed the installation of Cube model utility, we can proceed with the installation
of Mini Cube.
Now the first thing that we have to check and this goes for all operating systems Linux, Windows or
Mac, is to make sure that virtualization is enabled for your laptop or desktop wherever you're setting
up this lab.
So one of the easy ways to make sure that virtualization is enabled on Linux is to grep for the VMAX
or the some keyword under the proc CPU info file.
So that's what I'm going to do now.
So as long as this command shows an output such as the switches listed here, virtualization has been
enabled and you don't have to enable it specifically from the bios.
If it's not enabled, then you have to check your laptop's BIOS settings.
So you have to restart your laptop, go into the bios, and there should be an option to enable virtualization
and you have to do that.
You might have to check your laptop's manual in order to know how that's done or just check online with
your laptop model and search how to enable virtualization on your laptop.
And again, make sure that you check the documentation here for the respective operating system that
you are on.
For each of these, there are specific commands that can be used to run a test to see whether virtualization
has been enabled.
So next we are going to install Mini Cube and again, we will go ahead with the option for Linux.
And the first prerequisite is to install Cube Cuttle, which we have already done.
The next one is to install a hypervisor.
So for Linux we can either use KVM or VirtualBox.
We will go with VirtualBox as that is our preferred virtualization solution.
You can also run mini cube without a hypervisor and directly on your host using docker.
So if you already have Docker installed, you could leverage that and have mini Cube provisioned Kubernetes
cluster using a Docker container.
However, note that as you can see here in the documentation page, there is a warning that says it
can result in security or data loss issues.
So we will just stick with a virtual machine based approach for now, I just prefer VirtualBox because
it can in case you mess up something on your system and you need to restart, it's easy to get rid of
the VM and restart again.
It won't really mess up your laptop and you can take snapshots before you make a major change and then
you can restore that snapshot in case that changed.
Doesn't really well work well for you.
Now, VirtualBox is supported on all variety of operating systems, including Linux, Windows and OSX.
So I'm going to open this in a new window and it takes me to the download section.
And here I'm going to select Linux distribution and the one that is most appropriate for my system.
You may choose one that is appropriate for yours.
So wait for it to complete the download and then we will install VirtualBox.
It has downloaded the Debian package, so I'm just going to install it directly.
Wait for the installation to complete.
And while it installs, let's go back to the documentation section.
So now the installation has been completed and I'm just going to close this and I'm going to launch
a virtual box.
So as you can see here, this is what the VirtualBox interface looks like and you will have a similar
interface for Windows or Mac with minor differences, but that should not matter.
So right now we don't have any virtual machines running.
So when we provision a cluster using mini cube, it will automatically create a virtual machine as required.
So apart from just installing VirtualBox, you don't really have to do anything directly with it.
Now let's proceed with the installation.
So the next step is to install the mini cube utility.
Again, there are different ways to do this.
Either use the package manager and install it as a package or we can do it using a direct download approach.
So we're going to download the latest version and just like we did with the cube control utility, I'm
going to call the package and then install it on my machine.
So I'm just going to copy the whole thing.
And this will download the mini cube binaries and assign an execute bit so that we can run it as a command.
And once that has been done, let us add Mini Cube to our path.
The user local bin directory has already been created so we don't have to do that first step.
We will run this command.
To install mini cube at the location slash user slash local slash bin.
Next, we will provision a Kubernetes cluster using the mini cube utility.
So we're going to run the mini cube start command, but we also have to specify the driver name to be
used with this command.
Now, Mini Cube can work with different virtualization tools, and that's where you must specify what
driver to use.
In our case, we use VirtualBox.
So let's open this link and make sure that you we are using the correct driver name.
So the name of a VirtualBox driver is VirtualBox.
So we'll make use of that name.
So I'm going to copy and paste this command until the driver name.
And then I'm just going to copy the driver name from this page and paste it here.
We will now execute the command.
When it starts, you'll notice that it follows a process.
So it is, in fact downloading the ISO image for mini Cube.
And then this is the image that will be used to provision a VM on VirtualBox.
We now see that it's downloading Kubernetes version one point 18.3 and any other required binaries.
Now let me switch to the VirtualBox UI and we will see that a virtual machine by the name Mini Cube
has been created and it is in a running state.
And you can see that the VM uses two CPUs and two GB of RAM.
So let's wait for this setup to complete.
Okay, So now this has been installed and the utility is now configured to use the Kubernetes cluster
provisioned using mini cube.
So let's head back to the documentation page.
And the next thing that we are going to do is run the mini Cube Status Command to ensure that everything
has been set up correctly.
So I'm going to clear the screen here and then run the mini cube status command.
We can see that the mini cube control plane, cube, black API server and cube config are all in a running
and configured state, so that's good.
If you run into issues with the installation any time, feel free to run this command and check the
status.
So our cluster is now set up.
We will deploy some applications on the cluster and make sure it's working as expected.
Now we will get into talking about the different concepts on deploying an application in the upcoming
lectures.
Right now we just want to make sure that the cluster we set up is working as expected, so we will simply
follow the tutorial given in this page, although it may not make total sense now, but I assure you
that we will get to that in a bit.
So click on this link under what's next.
And here we have some examples that could be used to test our setup.
In the new page, you can skip the first step of starting a mini cube cluster.
So we have already done that.
So the next thing that we need to check is if Cube commands are working.
So I'm going to run the cube control, get Nodes Command and you can see that it is a single node cluster
and the node name is Mini Cube and it is in a ready state and it was spun up about 8 seconds ago and
it's running the latest release of Kubernetes, which is 1.18 as of this recording.
So next, let us try to create some deployments using this cluster.
So here we have an example on this page.
I'm going to run Cube Cuttle, Create Deployment Command to create the deployment.
Once that is done, we will run the cattle, get deployments command and you can see that the Halo mini
cube deployment has been running for 22 seconds.
Next, we will expose this deployment as a service.
And for that, make use of this command here.
And CubeSat will expose deployment.
Hello, Mini Cube command.
Now, don't worry about the command for now.
We'll talk about this in much detail later in this course.
For now, we will just copy and paste.
Okay.
And then we will skip to step five where we will get the URL of the ex post service.
So by running this command.
Copy the URL and paste it into a browser on your laptop.
And it should list the details about the application like this.
Okay, so that's not the most exciting application, but this is proof that your setup is working and
that's all we need for now.
Now follow the remaining instructions to clean up your system, delete the services, and delete the
deployment.
Now the deployment will be in a terminating state for a few seconds.
And after it's done, the application will no longer be accessible on the web page.
Well, that's it for now.
And I will see you in the next lecture.