Hello and welcome to the Ansible for the absolute beginners course.
My name is Chad Manabat and I will be your instructor for this course.
I'm a DevOps trainer at Code Cloud Dotcom.
The true hands on learn by doing platform have been working in the industry as a consultant for over
13 years and have helped hundreds of thousands of students learn technology in a fun and interactive
way.
In this course you will learn Ansible through a series of lectures that use animation and fun illustrations
that simplify complex concepts.
We have demos that will show you how to install and get started with Ansible, and most importantly,
we have hands on exercises that you can access right in your browser.
At the end of the course you will work on a real world project of deploying the Code Cloud e Commerce
application using simple playbooks.
Let's now look at the objectives of this course.
Since this is for the absolute beginners, we go all the way from scratch, covering everything you
need to know to get started.
You don't need any prior coding or scripting experience.
We will get started with understanding what Ansible is and what it can do.
We will go through how to set up Ansible in your environment using a simple virtual machine deployed
using VirtualBox.
Then we will get started with an introduction to YAML, which is the language of Ansible.
All ansible playbooks are written in YAML.
One of the common challenges that beginners face in Ansible is understanding how to work with YAML.
But don't worry, we've got your back.
We have a number of coding exercises that will get you all set with YAML in no time.
We will then head over to Ansible inventory files, playbooks and various concepts such as variables,
conditionals, loops and roles.
Again, all of these concepts are accompanied by hands on exercises that give you enough practice to
be confident in automating with Ansible.
As with all of our other courses, we have hands on exercises that you can access right in your browser.
The browser gives you a quiz portal with a set of questions and an editor to answer the question.
Develop YAML files and playbooks to solve the quiz.
If you run into issues, you may view the hands or the solution section for the answer or reach us through
our Q&A section.
So let's get started.
I'm ready when you are.