The virtual machine is now powered off.
Will now right click on it and select clone.
And in the new Virtual Machine page, I'm going to give it a name.
So the first clone is going to be the Ansible master, so I'm going to name it as Ansible controller
and make sure that you check the reset Mac address option because I need a new MAC address for all my
virtual machines.
In the next page, I'm going to make sure I select a linked clone.
A linked clone will basically is space saving.
It does not consume the entire it does not clone the entire virtual machine, so it does not consume
that much space.
I'm now going to click on Clone to create a clone of of the virtual machine.
So I now have the Ansible controller and I'm going to create another clone for the Ansible target.
For the first Ansible target, I will name it as Ansible Target one.
I'll make sure I check the initialize Mac address option and I will select the linked clone.
So now I have a template, I have a master, I have a ansible controller and an ansible target.
I will now power up the Ansible controller and the ansible target.
Once they are powered on, I will log into it using the OS box's password.
I will open a terminal and run the config command to find out the IP address.
Now, the reason I find out the IP address and establish an SSH connection is that it is.
I find it very easy to work with these virtual machines over an SSH session rather than through this
terminal window.
That way I can easily copy and paste commands.
Okay.
I will now establish an SSH session to my ansible master.
The IP address is 1821681.113.
The username is always boxes.
This time I will name the session as Ansible dash controller.
Okay, so I'm logged in.
I will also establish a session.
To my target machine.
Which is at 192 168 1.114.
And I will name the session as.
Ansible target one.
Okay, so I now have a session to the controller and the target.
The next step is to rename the host.
As you can see, both my controller and Target are named as OS boxes.
I'd like to name the controller as controller and the target as target.
So the first step is to modify the slash ETSI slash hostname file.
If you look inside the file, it is currently always boxes, so I'm going to remove that and replace
it with the name that I want, which is Ansible controller.
Now going to save that.
And the other place to modify is the ETSI host's file.
So I'm going to edit the four slash ATC slash host file.
And I'll get rid of whatever is already there and replace it with the.
Name that I wanted.
Wanted to have.
I believe the local host part as it is.
And I can now restart my system.
I will repeat the same steps for the target one system.
Okay.
I will now restart my system.
I will now establish connectivity to my systems again.
And as you can see, the name is applied.
I can now see it as Ansible dash controller.
So the next step is to install Ansible on the Ansible controller.
If you go to the Ansible documentation site and look at the installation guide, you will see instructions
for installing Ansible on various operating systems.
If you look at the instructions under CentOS, you can see that it's as simple as running the command
install Ansible.
So I'm just going to copy that.
And execute that on my CentOS system and provide the confirmation to install the packages.
Okay.
Once completed, you can run the Ansible dash dash version command to confirm that Ansible is installed
and to confirm the version of the Ansible installed on the system.
So that concludes the Ansible installation part.
Then we will now perform a simple test to check the connectivity between Ansible and the target machine.
To check connectivity.
I will first run, try to SSH to the target server.
So the target server is at one 92.1 68 1.114.
So we'll try and ssh into it.
And as you can see, it first asked me to confirm the key fingerprint I'm going to hit.
Yes.
And I will provide the password for the target host and I'm logged in.
I will now exit out of the system.
Now to test the connectivity through Ansible, I'm going to create a test project.
I'll create a folder called Test Project.
Inside that folder I will create an inventory file.
The inventory file will have one entry for the target host, which is target one.
I will specify the IP address using the Ansible host attribute.
And the IP address is one 92.1.
68.1 .114.
And then I will specify the password used to connect to the target server which is ansible underscore,
ssh, underscore pass and OS boxes.
Dot org.
Okay, now I have my inventory file with the IP of my target server and the password.
I can now run the check by running the Ansible command.
That's Ansible and the name of my host, which is Target one.
And I will specify a module called Ping, which is used to run the paint test and my inventory file
with a dash ai parameter inventory txt.
When I hit enter, it will perform a pink test through Ansible and make sure that it can establish a
successful connectivity to my target machine.
In this case, it says its success and it comes back with a pong message.
And so that confirms that my Ansible controller can successfully communicate or connect to the target
machine.
Now we're going to duplicate what we did with Target one.
We'll create another clone called Target two.
Make sure we re initialize the MAC address and select linked clone as the option for clone type.
And then we will power on the target to machine.
Once it's powered on, we will log in to it.
Open a terminal and find the IP address of it.
In this case, it is one 92.1.
68.1 .115.
We will now establish a SSH connection to the system.
From my associates terminal.
And I will name the session as Ansible Target two.
I will now edit the hostname to target to.
We will shut it down and wait for it to come back up.
While we wait for it to come back up, we'll modify the inventory file to update it with information
about the target to system.
We'll add a new line for target to the ansible host would be one 92.1 68 1.115 and the password will
be the same.
I can now confirm that the target to system is back up.
I can now log in to it and confirm that the name is set to target two.
I will now try to do a pink test through Ansible for my target two server.
I will first test target one and it looks good.
I will now try a test for target two.
And as you can see, it's failed.
But we followed the same steps for both the servers.
We created the servers from the same clone.
We followed the same steps to set to identify IP address and set hostname.
It has failed for target two, but it's passed for target one.
If you read the error message, you can see that it's got something to do with the SSH login and in
the key it says please add this host fingerprint to your known host file.
But did we do that for the first host?
If you go back to the earlier session and look at it, you will see that we did a manual ssh from the
ansible controller system to the target one system.
And when we did that, we actually accepted the key fingerprint by confirming when we when we did the
SSH.
And so that added the key of target of the target server to the known host list on the Ansible controller
machine.
We didn't actually do that for the Target two server, so that is the reason the Ansible ping test failed.
Now there are two ways to fix that.
One is we do a manual ssh from the ansible controller machine to the target machine and then hit yes
when it asks us for the confirmation or two.
There is a way to disable this particular host key checking using the ansible configuration file, which
is not the recommended way.
However, we'll still take a look at it.
If you go to the ansible configuration file at ETSI, ansible, ansible, dot cfg and search for host
key in that file.
You'll find that there's an entry that says host key checking and by default it is enabled to disable
it.
You must uncomment that line and so set host key checking to false.
I've now done that and save the file.
And if I do a ping test now, I can see that it returns with a pong.
Now, this is not a recommended way in a production environment.
In a production environment, using passwords to establish connectivity between systems is not recommended.
So there's a better way to do that, and that is using SSH keys.
Thank you.
And that is all for this demo.