Until now, we have seen quite a few TerraForm commands in action, such as the TerraForm in IT Plan
and Apply.
Let us now take a look at some more commands available in TerraForm.
The first command we will take a look at is the TerraForm Validate Command.
Once we write our configuration file, it's not necessary to run TerraForm Plan or apply to check if
the syntax used is correct.
Instead, we can make use of the TerraForm validate command like this.
And if everything is correct with the file, we should see a successful validation message like this.
If there's an error in the configuration file, the validate command will show you the line in the file
that is causing the error with the hints to fix it.
In this example, we have used an incorrect argument for the local file resource.
It should be file permission and not file permissions.
The next command that we are going to see is the TerraForm Fmt or the TerraForm Format Command.
This command scans the configuration files in the current working directory and formats the code into
a canonical format.
This is a useful command to improve the readability of the TerraForm configuration file.
When we run this command, the files that are changed in the configuration directory is displayed on
the screen.
The TerraForm Show Command prints out the current state of the infrastructure as seen by TerraForm.
In this example, we have already created the local file resource.
And when we run the show command, it displays the current state of the resource, including all the
attributes created by TerraForm for that resource, such as the file, name, file and directory permissions,
content and ID of the resource.
Additionally, we can make use of the dash JSON flag to print the contents in JSON format.
To see a list of all providers used in the configuration directory.
Use the TerraForm Providers Command.
You can also make use of the mirror sub command to copy provide the plugins needed for the current configuration
to another directory like this.
This command will mirror the provider configuration in a new path.
Slash root slash terraform slash new underscore local underscore file.
We saw how to use TerraForm output variables in one of the previous lectures.
If you want to print all output variables in the configuration directory, use the command terraform
output.
You can also print the value of a specific variable by appending the name of the variable to the end
of the output command.
Like this.
The TerraForm Refresh Command is used to sync TerraForm with the real world infrastructure.
For example, if there are any changes made to a resource created by TerraForm outside its control,
such as a manual update, the TerraForm Refresh Command will pick it up and update the state file.
This reconciliation is useful to determine what action to take during the next apply.
This command will not modify any infrastructure resource, but it will modify the state file.
As we saw earlier, TerraForm Refresh is also run automatically by commands such as TerraForm Plan and
TerraForm Apply.
And this was done prior to terraform generating an execution plan.
This can, however, be bypassed by using the dash refresh is equal to false option with the commands.
The data from Graph Command is used to create a visual representation of the dependencies in a TerraForm
configuration or an execution plan.
In this example, the local file in our main file has a dependency on the random pet resource.
This command can be run as soon as you have the configuration file ready, even before you have initialized
the configuration directory with terraform in it.
Upon running data from Graph Command, you should see an output like this.
This text generated is hard to comprehend as it is, but it is a graph generated in a format called
DOT.
To make more sense of this graph.
We can pass it through a graph visualization software such as graph vis.
And we can install it in ubuntu using apt like this.
Once installed, we can pass the output of the form graph to the dot command which we installed using
the graph first package and generate a graphic like this.
We can now open this file via a browser and it should show a dependency graph like this.
The root is the configuration directory where the configuration for this graph is located.
We can see that there are two resources the local file called PET and the random pet resource called
My Pet that makes use of the local and the random provider respectively.
And finally, we can see that the local file called PAT depends on the random pat resource called my
pat.
As we have used a reference expression in the local file resource that points to the ID of the random
That's it for this lecture.
Now, let's head over to the hands on labs and explore working with the TerraForm commands that we learned
in this lecture.