In this section, we will learn about the difference between mutable and immutable infrastructure.
In one of the previous lectures, we saw that Venter from updates a resource such as updating the permissions
of a local file.
It first destroys it and then recreates it with the new permission.
So why does TerraForm do that?
To understand this, let us make use of a simple example.
Consider an application server running engine X with division of 1.17.
When a new version of Engine X is released, we upgrade the software running on this web server first
from 1.17 to 1.18, and eventually when a new version 1.19 is released.
We upgraded the same way from 1.18 to 1.19.
This can be done using a number of different ways.
One simple approach is to download the desired version of Engine X and then use it to manually upgrade
the software on the web server during a maintenance window.
Of course, we can also make use of tools such as ad hoc scripts or configuration management tools such
as Ansible to achieve this.
For high availability.
Instead of relying on one web server, we can have a pool of these web servers all running the same
software and code.
We would have to use the same software upgrade lifecycle for each of these servers using the same approach
that we used for the first web server.
This type of update is known as in place update.
And this is because the underlying infrastructure remains the same, but the software and the configuration
on these servers are changed as part of the update.
And this here is an example of a mutable infrastructure.
Updating software on a system can be a complex task, and in almost all cases there are bound to be
a set of dependencies that have to be met before an upgrade can be carried out successfully.
Let us assume that Web server one and two have every dependency met while we try to upgrade the version
from 1.18 to 1.19.
And as a result, these two servers are upgraded without any issues.
Web server three, on the other hand, does not.
The upgrade fields on Web server three because it has a few dependencies that are not met and as a result
it remains at version 1.18.
The failure in upgrade could be because of a number of reasons, such as network issues impacting the
connectivity to the software repository file system, full or different version of operating system
running on web server three as compared to the other two.
However, the important thing here to note is that we now have a pool of three web servers in which
one of these servers is running a different version of software as compared to the rest.
Over time with multiple updates and changes to this pool of servers.
It is a possibility that each of these servers vary from one another, may be in software configuration
or operating system, etc..
This is known as a configuration drift.
For example, after a few update windows over three Web servers could look like this Web server one
and two have Engine X version of 1.19 and Web server three has a version of 1.18.
And all three Web servers may also be running slightly different versions of operating system on them.
This configuration drift can leave the infrastructure in a complex state, making it difficult to plan
and carry out subsequent updates.
Troubleshooting issues would also be a difficult task as each server would behave slightly differently
from the other because of this configuration.
Drift.
Instead of updating the software versions on the web servers, we can spin up new web servers with the
updated software version and then delete the old web server.
So when we want to update engine X 1.1721.18, a new server is provisioned with 1.18 version of Engine
X.
If the update goes through, then the old web server is deleted.
This is known as immutable infrastructure.
Immutable means unchanged or something that you cannot change as a consequence.
With immutable infrastructure, we cannot carry out in place updates of the resources anymore.
This doesn't mean that updating Web servers this way will not lead to failures.
If the upgrade fails for any reason, the old web server will be left intact and the failed server will
be removed.
As a result, we do not leave much room for configuration drift to occur between our servers, ensuring
that it is left in a simple, easy to understand state.
And since we are working with infrastructure as a code, immutability makes it easier to version the
infrastructure and to roll back and roll forward between versions.
Therefore as an infrastructure provisioning tool uses this approach.
Going back to our example, updating the resource block for our local file resource and changing the
permission from seven seven 7 to 7 zero zero will result in the original file to be deleted and a new
file to be created with the updated permission.
By default, TerraForm destroys the resource first before creating a new one in its place.
But what if we want the resource to be created first before the old one is deleted or to ignore deletion
completely?
How do we do that?
This can be done by making use of lifecycle rules in our resource block, and we'll see how to do that
next.