In this section, we will learn how to set up lifecycle rules in TerraForm.
Previously we saw that when TerraForm updates a resource, it frees the infrastructure to be immutable
and first deletes the resource before creating a new one with the updated configuration.
For example, if we update the file permissions on our local file resource from 7772700 and then run
TerraForm apply, you would see that the older file is deleted first and then the new file is created.
Now, this may not be a desirable approach in all cases, and sometimes you may want the updated version
of the resource to be created first before the older one is deleted.
Or you may not want the resource to be deleted at all, even if there was a change made in its local
configuration.
This can be achieved in TerraForm by making use of lifecycle rules.
These rules make use of the same block syntax that we have seen many times so far, and they go directly
inside the resource block whose behavior we want to change.
The syntax of a resource block with a lifecycle rule looks like this.
Inside the lifecycle block.
We add the rule, which we want our form to adhere to while updating resources.
And one such argument or a rule is the create before destroy rule.
Here we have the same resource block that has been updated with the lifecycle rule of create before
destroy set to true.
This rule ensures that when a change in configuration forces the resource to be recreated, a new resource
is created first before deleting the old one.
Now, there would be cases where we do not want a resource to be destroyed for any reason.
For this we can make use of the prevent destroy option.
When it is set to true that reform will reject any changes that will result in their source getting
destroyed and display an error message like this.
This is especially useful to prevent your resources from getting accidentally deleted.
For example, a database resource such as my SQL or PostgreSQL may not be something that we want to
delete once it's provisioned.
One important thing to note here is that the resource can still be destroyed if you make use of the
TerraForm destroy command.
This rule will only prevent resource deletion from changes that are made to the configuration and a
subsequent apply.
The last argument type that we're going to see here is the ignore changes rule.
This life cycle rule, when applied, will prevent a resource from being updated based on a list of
attributes that we define within the lifecycle block.
To understand this better.
Let's make use of a sample AC two instance, which is a virtual machine on the cloud.
This EC two instance is to be used as a web server and can be created with a simple resource block like
this.
Don't worry if this resource block and the arguments look unfamiliar, we will cover it in much more
detail in the EC2 section of the course.
But for now, please note that the resource called web server makes use of three arguments.
The am-I and the instance type are used to deploy a specific type of VM with a predefined specification.
In this case, the values that we have chosen deploys Ubuntu server with one CPU and one GB of RAM.
We are also making use of a tag called name, which has a value of project, a web server using the
tags argument, which is off type map.
When we run TerraForm apply.
The EC2 instance is created as expected with a tag called name and a value of project a web server.
Now, if changes are made to any of these arguments, TerraForm will attempt to fix it during the next
apply as expected.
For example, if we modify the tag called name and change its value from project a web server to say
project be web server either manually or using any other tool, TerraForm will detect this change and
it will attempt to change it back to what it was originally, which is project a web server.
In some rare cases, we may actually want the change in the name by any other method to be acceptable.
And we want to prevent our form from reverting back to the old tag.
To do this, we can make use of the lifecycle block with ignore changes argument like this.
The ignore changes argument accepts a list as indicated by the square brackets and it will accept any
valid resource attribute.
In this particular case, we have asked our form to ignore changes which are made to the tags attribute
of the specific EC2 instance.
If a change is made to the tax, a subsequent form apply should now show that there are no changes to
apply.
The change made to the tags of a server outside of their reform is now completely ignored.
And since it's a list, we can update more elements like this.
You can also replace the list with the all keyword.
And this is especially useful if you do not want the resource to be modified for changes in any resource
attributes.
We will learn more about life cycle rules later in the course when we work with resources.
But for now, here is a quick summary of the three argument types that we have seen in this lecture.
And now let's head over to the Hands-On Labs and practice working with lifecycle rules in TerraForm.