In this lecture, we will take a look at meta arguments in TerraForm.
Until now, we have been able to create single resources such as a local file and a random pet resource
using TerraForm.
But what if you want to create multiple instances of the same resource, say three local files, for
example?
If we were using a shell script or some other programming language, we could create multiple files
like this.
In this example, we have created a Bash script called Create Files SE, which uses a for loop to create
empty files inside the root directory.
The files will be called pet, followed by the range from 1 to 3.
While we cannot use the same script as it is within the resource block, TerraForm offers several alternatives
to achieve the same goal.
Now, these can be done by making use of specific meta arguments in their form.
Meta arguments can be used within any resource block to change the behaviour of resources.
We have already seen two types of meta arguments already in the scores.
That depends on for defining explicit dependency between resources and the lifecycle rules, which define
how the resources should be created, updated and destroyed within TerraForm.
Now let us look at some more meta arguments specifically related to loops in TerraForm.