In this lecture, we will take a look at the current meta argument and its uses in TerraForm.
One of the easiest ways to create multiple instances of the local file is to make use of the count meta
argument.
To do this, simply add an argument called count with a value greater than one.
Here we have used count is equal to three.
When we try to run TerraForm plan now we can see that the form tries to create three resources instead
of one.
In the output of the TerraForm Apply Command, we can see that three resources are created.
The resources are identified by pet of zero, where zero is within square brackets.
PET one and PET two.
The resource is now considered to be a list of resources with elements at Index zero one and two.
However, there's one problem with this approach.
Since we have only specified the count, TerraForm will try to create the same resource three times
since the file name is not unique to form.
Recreate the same file three times rather than creating three separate files, which defeats the purpose
of this task.
A better way to do this and make sure that all three resources have unique file names is to make use
of a list variable for file name.
And to do this, we have used default values with three elements, each corresponding to the name of
the file that we want to create.
Next, we want a form to make use of each element of this list as the value of the file name argument.
In this example, TerraForm should make three iterations as the count has a value of three.
The first iteration should pick up the element at Index zero, which is the file called Sdcard.
This is followed by the element at index one, which is docs.
TXT.
And finally cast txt at index two.
To use this within the configuration file.
We can make use of count index in the expression for the file name like this.
Now when we run from apply, we can see that there are three files created inside the slash root directory.
But what if we were to add a few more elements to the list in the future?
Say we wanted to add a few more files by the name of slash root slash costs RD and extract.
If we were to apply this configuration now, we would see that it will still create only three files
because we have set the account to a static value of three.
We want the count to automatically pick up the number of items that are defined within the filename
variable.
And to do this, we can set the value of count to use a built in function that would return the length
of the list.
This built in function called length will set the value of count to five.
TerraForm offers several built in functions that allows us to manipulate values within expressions.
And one simple function that we can use here is the length function.
The length function is used to calculate the size of a list, and we can use this function in the current
meta argument to dynamically determine the size of the name variable.
We are now ready to run from apply.
But before we do that, let's change the default value for the file name variable back to three elements.
And that's it.
If you run to reform plan and apply now, we should see that three resources with distinct file names
have been created.
There is, however, another significant drawback when we use the current meta argument to loop through
variables this way.
To illustrate this, let us use the same example, but this time let us remove the element slash root
slash pegs from the list.
If we run a reform plan now, we can see that instead of deleting just one resource with the file name
slash route slash sdcard TerraForm is replacing two resources and deleting one resource.
Why does it do that?
We only want to remove the first element in this list, but it looks like all elements are going to
be replaced by this operation.
To see why this is happening.
Let us first understand how it works.
As we saw before, when we use count the resources become a list of resources.
To see this using TerraForm.
Let us add an output variable to the main file to print all details of this resource.
Using the TerraForm Output Command, we can see that the resource is now in the format of a list.
Additionally, the resource called PET is a list with three resources each identified by its index.
The first resource in the list creates the file by the name Pet, and it is identified by pet with the
index zero zero enclosed within square brackets since it's a list.
The second resource element is pet of one, which creates a file called Dogs.
And the third resource is Pet of two, which creates a file called Castex D.
The first element in a list is always zero.
And as a result, when we deleted the element called slash root slash, which was at index zero to begin
with, the element with the value slash root slash dogsbody shifts up and takes its place at index zero.
Likewise, slash root slash becomes the element at index one and the list now only has two elements
in it.
When we run a reform plan.
Now reform can see that the resources at Index zero and PET one have to be destroyed and replaced.
This is owing to the change in their file names and there is no resource pet to so it will delete that
resource entirely.
Although after the apply operation, we will have the resources created as per our intended end state.
This is not an ideal approach.
We may not want the resources to be destroyed and recreated just because we removed an unrelated element
from the list and we will see how to fix that in the next lecture.
Now let's head over to the hands on labs and practice working with the account meta argument in order
for.