In this section, we will talk about setting up a lab for beginning your studies on DevOps and cloud
technologies.
At Code Cloud we have embedded labs for our courses and we provide you a readily available environment
to work on.
But at times you may want to set up your own personal learning environment, an environment where your
changes are persistent and an environment where you can develop your own custom solutions.
And this section will help you create your own lab as well as troubleshoot and maintain it, which is
something that most students struggle with.
We will discuss the different options available to set up a lab environment such as laptops or cloud.
We will discuss using VirtualBox as a solution to set up labs on your laptop.
We will discuss how to deploy multiple VMs in a virtual box environment.
We will discuss networking in VirtualBox, which is one of the topics that a lot of our students have
trouble with, such as getting the VMs to talk to each other, accessing the Internet from the from
the VMs setting to to the VMs, etc..
We will also discuss how to take snapshots to save the state of VMs and restore those snapshots.
We will then discuss how to automate the deployment of VMs using Vagrant.
A background is a really neat tool that can help you set up a local lab environment very easily and
it is.
I highly recommend you to learn that.
And finally, we will also look at some options available on the cloud to set up your own lab environment.
You have two options.
One is your laptop, either office or home.
The second is on the cloud, a private cloud within your organization or a public cloud provider like
Google or Azure.
There are many cloud providers that offer free tier where you can create VMs and use them for free.
We will talk about some of those later.
For now, let's start with a lab setup on a home, laptop or desktop environment.
This could also be an office laptop.
I personally prefer a home laptop as I can do anything with it as I want.
I don't need to take approvals or erase requests to open up firewalls or get permission to install software
on it.
I want to be independent and do whatever I want to do.
So you need such an environment to play around with and to break and and then fix it back together and
basically do anything that you want to do with it.
So what is a home lab environment and what are the kind of things that you will be needing it for while
going through DevOps Cloud or I.T automation courses, you will often come across a set of tools that
you will need to work with tools such as Git for source code management, Build tools like Jenkins for
running builds programming language frameworks like Java, Python or Node.js.
There dependent libraries and packages web servers like Apache web server, engine X Tomcat servers
or databases like MySQL, MongoDB, etc. or containerization tools like Docker or Kubernetes and automation
tools like Ansible, Chef or Puppet, as well as cloud management tools like Cloud SDK or Cloud Command
line tools and even different operating systems, even such as Ubuntu, CentOS, Fedora, etc..
Now you can install all of these directly on your laptop and play around with them, but at some point
it's going to start impacting the performance of your laptop and you might run into compatibility related
issues.
Different applications may have a requirement for different versions of these softwares and then you
will try to uninstall and reinstall them and soon you'll see yourself in an installation and cleanup
loop, trying to get it all working.
And soon you will end up reimaging your laptop and losing all your configurations and all of the personalization
that you did to your laptop.
So one way to combat that is to do everything that you need to do within a virtual machine on your laptop.
So this way, if things go south, you can simply delete your virtual machine and provision a new one
or take a backup of your virtual machine and restore state from backup.
We will discuss how to do that later in this section.
This also allows you to try different things in different virtual machines and have different operating
systems on different virtual machines.
Irrespective of what OS you are on, say you are on a mac or windows, you can have one VM with Ubuntu
and other with CentOS.
You can run Windows or Linux on Mac or a Windows server on Linux or a Linux on a Windows or Mac, etc.
and you can have as many systems as you want as long as you have sufficient hardware resources.
Now, of course, all of all of these tools that are listed here, some of them definitely need to be
on your laptop, such as Git or the a few other popular tools that you would use on a day to day basis
for development purposes.
But what I'm referring to here are more of the tools like programming language frameworks or build tools
or a web servers or databases, etc..
So what is a software that can help you create these virtual machines, these virtual machines into
which you can, you know, those which we can play around with or install applications on.
It's called as a virtualization software or hypervisors.
Now, you might have heard about VMware ESX servers or Windows Hyper-V servers that can create virtual
machines.
These are known as Type one hypervisors.
They're installed directly on bare metal, such as a laptop or server, and then the VMs are created
on that.
Now these are used in enterprises and production environments where you need to create and manage large
number of virtual machines.
And as such, these hypervisors have high resource requirements.
They also need to be installed and configured directly on the laptop and they are expensive as well.
A lot of people do use this for home labs, especially if they have systems with high resources.
But that's not what we want here for our purpose.
There are other solutions available that better suit our needs and are easy to manage.
And those are type two hypervisors.
They're hypervisors that runs on an existing operating system.
Examples are Oracle, VirtualBox and VMware Workstation.
These allow you to easily get started with virtual machines on your laptops without having to install
any other operating system or re image your laptop.
So going forward, when we say host operating system, we are referring to the main OS on our laptop.
And when we talk about guest operating systems, we are referring to the VMs that are created on the
hypervisors which are on the operating system.
And so these are our topic of interest Oracle, VirtualBox and VMware Workstation.
Both of these are very easy to get started with.
Just download and install and off you go.
But which one?
Among the two?
Oracle VirtualBox is a free and open source tool.
It can be installed and used to create virtual machines on Windows, Linux or Mac exactly the same way
it supports backup and recovery with snapshots and clone features.
It lets you run multiple VMs together and also helps you create separate networks within your laptop
for different groups of VMs.
VMware Workstation is, on the other hand, is not a free software.
It can only be installed on Windows or Linux and not Mac, and it supports advanced features like snapshots
and clones.
There is a free version of VMware Workstation known as VMware Player that's available for Windows and
Linux and VMware Fusion, which is available for Mac.
However, these do not have many features that VMware Workstation or VirtualBox support, such as running
multiple VMs at the same time or taking snapshots or performing advanced networking configurations.
So if you ask me, considering the cost benefits and the features, Oracle VirtualBox is my choice for
a home lab environment.
So Oracle VirtualBox is supported on Windows, Linux, Mac or Solaris platforms.
Visit this link to go to the download page and download the package for your operating system and this
link gives you the list of supported operating system versions with respect to resource requirements.
Oracle VirtualBox can be installed on a system with an x 86 hardware with memory as small as 512 GB
and only consumes around 30 MVA of disk space for itself.
However, since virtual machines require resources, it's a good idea to have additional resources on
your host system a lot more actually.
So a dual core or quad core processor and a memory of at least four GB and disk space of at least 100
GB or more will help you set up one or two small VMs and you can be really smart in managing resources
by allocating VMs with only sufficient resources that that it requires and using lightweight OS images
instead of the full blown OS images.
So once it's installed, open up the VirtualBox tool by starting the executable, it should be available
in your application section or in your program section on Windows to create a new virtual machine.
Hit the new button at the top, then give your VM a name and specify the location where you want the
files of the VM to be created.
The VM itself and the disks of the VM are stored as a file on the host operating system.
Set the type of the OS to Linux and since the VM that I intend to create is a CentOS machine, I choose
RedHat 64 bit as my OS version because Central West is a community fork of Red Hat enterprise Linux,
so they are kind of the same except that Red Hat Enterprise Linux has a lot more advanced packages and
and built in features, but at the core they are the same.
So from the list of options available now you have Linux and Debian fedora, you don't see center OS,
but instead of that you can just select red hat and then you have others like open source, ubuntu etc..
The next step is assigning memory resources.
This may differ between different oss.
If your OS is lightweight, you may assign a smaller amount of memory.
One GB is usually good.
And next, we select the hard disk.
Here's where you can create and attach a new disk to the VM.
Now, a new disk means it's blank and does not have anything on it.
It doesn't even have an operating system on it.
Now, creating a new VM is like buying a new PC or a laptop.
Without an operating system, you decide what CPU memory and disk configurations are needed and then
you buy the laptop and get the disks.
Attach the disk to the machine and then the disk is a blank disk and there is no operating system on
it.
So you need to install an operating system using an OS CD.
So just like how you would install an OS on a laptop, you would need to install an OS on a virtual
machine created like this.
Now, that's one approach.
But there's a better way.
And what if the disk you attach already has an OS on it?
A pre configured pre built OS.
That way when the VMM is created, we attach the disk which has the OS on it and then when it boots
it's ready to go.
You don't have to manually install the OS.
So how do we create those disks and where do we get such disks from?
Well, it so happens that a large collection of such pre configured disks or images as it is called,
are available on the internet and one such website is OS boxes dot org.
They have a list of images for all kinds of operating systems like Ubuntu, Debian, CentOS, fedora,
etc..
Once an image is downloaded, use that as an existing virtual hard disk file while creating the VM.
And that's it.
The VMM is now created.
Now all you need to do is start the VMM by right clicking and selecting the normal start option from
the menu.
In the next lecture we will see the different ways of connecting to the VM and working with it.
And that's one area a lot of people have problems with, like how do you ssh into the VM, how do I
access a service hosted on the VM, etc. and that's what we will cover in the next lecture.
So.
Thanks for watching and I will see you the next video.