Hello and welcome to this demo.
In this demo, we're going to see how to set up a lab environment.
So in our case, we're going to install VirtualBox.
So go to VirtualBox dot org and in the website you will have find a link to download the VirtualBox
software.
In the download page, you will find links to download VirtualBox for specific operating systems and
I'm going to download the software once downloaded, run the executable and follow the instructions
in the installation Wizard to complete installation after you install Open up the Oracle Virtual Box
interface and it will look something like this.
Now the next step is to deploy virtual machines.
In order to do that, you can either create a machine, attach a CD, drive of an operating system,
and follow the instructions to install the operating system as we are familiar with.
However, there's also another easy way.
There are pre installed pre configured operating system images available on the internet.
We could use those to easily deploy as many virtual machines as we need.
For this, if you go to the website OS boxes dot org.
You will find a lot of pre-installed pre configured images of various operating systems.
Go to this site and select the VM images, virtual box images link at the top and then you will be you
will find a list of various different operating systems.
From this we will select CentOS.
And then it will take us to the center of this page.
Here you can see information on downloading the center image.
In our case, we're downloading the VirtualBox image for Center seven and we're downloading the 64 bit
version.
So remember to download that particular version.
It is downloaded as a7z file, which is a compressed file.
So you need a software to uncompressed it.
Wait for it to finish the extraction process.
Once finished if you go into the folder.
You will see that there is a folder called 64 bit.
And inside that folder you will find a file with the extension VDI that stands for virtual disk, and
that is what we will use to create our virtual machine.
We're now ready to create a new virtual machine.
So we go back into the Oracle virtual box interface, click on New and we fill in the name and operating
system.
I will now select the type as Linux and click next.
In the next here we select a memory size.
In the next step, we select the hard disk that we downloaded.
So in this case, the default selection is create a virtual hard disk now, but that is not what we
want.
We already have a pre-built image of a hard disk downloaded, so we're going to specify that select
the user, an existing virtual hard disk file option, and click on Browse and Browse to the file that
we downloaded and extracted, which is the center is seven file with the VDI extension.
Click on.
Okay.
And that creates the file.
Now, before powering on the template, we will go into settings and make a few more changes.
Go to system and we'll increase the CPU to around two.
I will now go ahead and power on the system.