Hello and welcome to this demo.
In this demo we are going to see how to set up a lab environment.
So in my case, I have a Windows system, so I will be setting up a lab environment on my Windows system.
It doesn't really matter what operating system you're on.
You could follow the same instructions to set up a lab environment on Linux or your Mac operating systems.
So in our case, we're going to install VirtualBox, so go to VirtualBox dot org and in the website
you will have find a link to download the VirtualBox software.
In the download page, you will find links to download VirtualBox for specific operating systems.
In my case, I'm mine is Windows.
I'm going to click on Windows and I'm going to download the software once downloaded, run the executable
and follow the instructions in the installation Wizard to complete installation.
In my case, I've already installed it, so I'm just going to cancel that.
After you install open up the Oracle VirtualBox interface and it will look something like this.
Now the next step is to deploy virtual machines.
In order to do that, you can either create a machine, attach a CD, drive of an operating system,
and follow the instructions to install the operating system as we are familiar with.
However, there's also another easy way.
There are pre installed pre configured operating system images available on the internet.
We could use those to easily deploy as many virtual machines as we need.
For this, if you go to the website OS boxes dot org.
You will find a lot of pre-installed pre configured images of various operating systems.
Go to this site and select the VM images.
VirtualBox images link at the top and then you will be you will find a list of various different operating
systems.
From this we will select CentOS.
And then it will take us to the center of this page.
Here you can see information on downloading the center image.
In our case, we're downloading the VirtualBox image for Center seven and we're downloading the 64 bit
version.
So remember to download that particular version.
We will.
Then it is downloaded as a seven zip file, which is a compressed file.
So you need a software to uncompressed it like guitar or winzip.
In my case, I'm using the seven zip software to extract the contents of the file into a folder.
Wait for it to finish the extraction process.
Once finished if you go into the folder.
You will see that there is a folder called 64 bit.
And inside that folder you'll find a file with the extension VDI that stands for virtual disk.
And that is what we will use to create our virtual machine.
We're now ready to create a new virtual machine.
So we go back into the Oracle VM VirtualBox interface, click on New and we fill in the name and operating
system.
Now I will name the virtual machine that I'm creating as CentOS template because as we discussed, we're
our goal is to create a template and then use that template to create as many virtual machines as I
need.
So I'm going to name it as CentOS template.
I will now select the type as Linux and the version.
Since it does not have CentOS listed, I could simply select other.
Now, as you can see under the versions there are 32 bit as well as 64 bit options.
In our case we downloaded the center was 64 bit version, so we must select 64 bit option.
Now in case you do not see the 64 bit options in this list, and that is most probably because you do
not have the virtualization technology enabled on your laptop to enable virtualization technology on
your laptop.
It is usually under the BIOS settings.
So if you simply Google enable virtualization in bios followed by your laptop model, you will see a
set of results.
It's usually usually looks something like this under the BIOS, under the advanced BIOS features.
You'll have something called as virtualization technology and you must ensure that it is set to enable
state.
So once you do that, restart your laptop and you will find the 64 bit option and click next.
In the next here we select a memory size.
By default, it's set to 512 NB and let's change that to around two GB So we'll set it to two two gigs.
In the next step, we select the hard disk that we downloaded.
So in this case.
The default selection is create a virtual hard disk now, but that is not what we want.
We already have a pre-built image of a hard disk downloaded, so we're going to specify that select
the user, an existing virtual hard disk file option, and click on Browse and Browse to the file that
we downloaded and extracted, which is the center is seven file with the VDI extension.
Click on.
Okay.
And that creates the file.
Now, before powering on the template, we will go into settings and make a few more changes.
Go to system and we'll increase the CPU to around two and we go to network section and we will set the
adapter one to bridge network.
This way my virtual machine gets an IP address as well as it can connect to the internet to download
and install packages as required.
I will now go ahead and power on the system.
I'm now at the login prompt.
Select the default user, which is the which is O's boxes.
Now the password to find out the password for any images downloaded from boxes dot org.
Go to the info section and then you'll see that the username is o's boxes and the password is always
boxes dot org.
So I'm going to use that password.
O's boxes dot org.
I will click on Sign in.
To log in to the centre.
System.