In this lecture, we will look at how to connect to the VM we created in the previous video.
Now, some of the most frequently asked questions about setting up a local lab environment revolves
around connectivity.
How do we connect to the VM and how do we ssh into it?
Why can't I access the something that's hosted on the VM such as the web browser?
And we'll find answers for these in this video.
So on our laptop, which we will call as the host system, we have deployed Oracle VirtualBox and created
a VM having CentOS image which happens to be the same.
The guest system I'm using Mac, but it works the same for Windows or Linux.
Now, when a VM is installed and ready, you can start the VM either in a normal mode or a headless
mode.
Now, a normal mode gives you a console to the VM.
You can see the UI of the VM as you would see a Linux laptop boot up.
It's like looking at the monitor of a machine.
If the image we downloaded came with a Linux GUI as well, then we can see the UI on the screen and
work with the VM, like working with any other GI.
The GI is okay to explore and maybe play around with initially, but when you get into real dev ops
and cloud and automation tasks, it would be better to have CLI access.
So I personally never used the GI because it's in fact a bit painful to work with switching between
your system and the VM UI.
And since it's a v m, the UI and console may be a bit slow, you can't easily copy and paste stuff
from your host to the guests or copy files back and forth.
You can, but it's just not that easy.
Now, eventually you need a terminal to work with a Linux system that is to run commands for installing
packages, working with services, etc..
So instead of using the terminal inside the GI, it is a lot more convenient to use a terminal on your
host laptop.
In the normal mode.
When the console is closed, the VM must be shut down or suspended.
It props up this message where it gives you these three options.
The first one says Save the machine state, which is suspend and then sent or the other options are
sent a shut down signal or power of the machine.
The other option shown here is the head start.
So if that is selected, the VM still starts, but the console window won't be opened.
The VM can only be accessed remotely using SSH or remote desktop tools for Windows.
The third option is where it can be started in a normal mode, but closing the console won't require
you to suspend or shut down the VM.
Instead, you have you now have a new option that says continue to run in the background.
So that just selecting that option simply closes the console alone and it continues to keep the the
VM running in the background.
Depending on what OS has been used on the guest system, we have different ways of connecting to it.
For example, say we had a Windows system to remotely connect to the Windows system without using the
console.
You could use the some kind of remote desktop client such as the one provided by Microsoft.
Now if the guest has a Linux operating system as it is in case of Santos, we can connect to it remotely
through SSH using SSH clients like the terminal app in Linux or Mac and tools like putty in Windows.
Although the VMs are within our laptop, think of them as separate machines connected to the same network.
So whatever you need for one system to connect to another system, you would need that here.
For this to work, you must have these VMs configured with IP addresses and the relevant services must
be configured.
And running on Windows, you need the remote desktop service to be running and on Linux you need the
SSH service to be running.
So make sure SSH server is installed and is in a running state.
If so, you can SSH into the VM from the host system using the terminal on the host and the IP address
of the remote VM.
But how do you configure set service and IP addresses on the VM if you can't connect to it on the first
place?
For that, you could use the console to perform initial configuration.
It's a common practice to use the console to perform initial configurations and then once SSH is enabled,
switch over to the terminal for all future interactions.
So if you run into issues connecting to a VM check to make sure that the VM has an IP address set and
that you are using the right IP address and that SSH service on the remote VM is running.
So here's a quick example on how to check or set IP addresses in a centralized machine.
Run the IP address, show command, and it lists all interfaces and IP addresses assigned to them.
The first interface is the loopback interface with the IP.
120 7.0.0.1 and the second interface is zero, which is the interface used for connectivity.
And it has IP addresses one 92.1 68 or 1.10.
Now, if the IP address was not set, you can set the IP using the IP address, add command and specify
the IP address followed by the subnet mask and the device you want to set the IP on, which happens
to be e zero in this case.
Now, with different operating systems, the device names as well as commands may differ.
So refer to the operating system documentations and find out the right relevant way to set IP address.
And here's a quick tip on checking the SSH service.
The SSH service comes by default with sent OS image to check if the daemon is running.
Run.
The service has saved status command.
If it's not running, run the service.
Ssh the start command to start it.
Well, that's it for now.
We will now head over to a demo and see this in action.
And in the upcoming lectures, we will discuss more about networking in VirtualBox.