So there are different ways to connect to a Linux VM on VirtualBox depending on how you set up your
networking.
I used two different approaches while deploying the VMs in Windows and Mac, so I kind of had two demos
there, Windows and Mac.
You don't have to go through them.
It's kind of the same demo.
The only difference between the two is that on one I set up a bridge networking and on the other I didn't.
So the one on the left, as you see here, is the setting on Mac.
And on the one on the right is the setting on Windows.
On the Windows deployment, I added a bridge adapter and on the Mac OS, I didn't.
I just configured the default NAT option for the networking adapter.
Now if you had configured the bridge adapter as in Windows, the VM becomes part of the external network
and it gets an IP address assigned to it.
You can simply SSH to it as you would as a switch to another system in your network.
In case of Nat, as in the Mac setup, it doesn't connect to the external network and so does not get
an IP address on the external network that we can use to SSH to.
So we will use port forwarding as we discussed in the previous lecture.
I also want to point out that this doesn't have anything to do with Windows or Mac.
Both these network configurations can be configured on either OS and it works the same.
I just chose two different options just to show you the difference between the two.
So let's proceed with the connectivity on Mac.
Once the system is powered on, if the console looks too small, you can go to the view menu and scale
visibility to 300%.
There is a welcome screen and wizard within the console, so just go through that and close them.
From the application's menu select terminal.
We'll now check the IP address of the system so we type in IP address, show command to see the IP addresses.
As you can see, it gets an IP address of ten .0. 2.15.
Now this is a private internal IP assigned by the NAT router for this VM.
So this IP is not reachable from anywhere else.
Neither the host or nor any other VMs created on this network.
So don't try to ping this IP address access to this IP from the host.
You'll not be able to do that.
If you had multiple VMs, you will see that all VMs configured with Nat are isolated and they all get
the same IP address assigned and they cannot reach each other.
However, with network address translation, they can reach the external world.
So you should have internet connectivity.
If your host has Internet connectivity, you can verify that by trying to ping an external website like
this.
Okay, so that looks good.
So how do you remotely connect to the system?
Like, if you want to ssh into this VM to perform, you know, to carry out operations, to run commands.
How do you do that?
So first, verify that the SSH service is running for this.
Run the service SSH the status command.
We see the status is active.
Now our goal is to ssh into this VM from a terminal on our host.
Since it doesn't have an IP address that we can ssh to, we will set up port forwarding.
Go to the settings menu of this VM and under the network section select port forwarding.
Add a new rule.
We will forward a port on our local host to a port on the VMM.
The SSH service listens on Port 22 on the VM, but we also have an SSH service on our host that uses
Port 22.
So we cannot forward 22 on our host to the VM.
So we will configure another port, say port 2222 on the host to forward to port 22 on the VM.
So we add a rule for that and we name it as SSH port.
Now I could try to switch to my local host IP or a loopback IP address, which is 120 7.0.0.1 and specify
port 2222 And if you'd like to log in as route user, specify the username before the IP address and
enter the password ohs boxes dot org and you're in.
Well, we have now connected to our VM and we can now run any commands.
We'll inspect the release files under the ETSI directory, using the CAD command to verify the version
of OS.
And as we can see that it's CentOS seven.
So we've connected to the right system.
So that's it for this demo.
I will see you in the next video.