Okay.
I'm now at the login prompt.
Select the default user, which is the which is O's boxes.
Now the password to find out the password for any images downloaded from boxes dot org.
Go to the info section and then you'll see that the username is o's boxes and the password is always
boxes dot org.
So I'm going to use that password as boxes dot org.
I will click on sign in to log in to the centre.
A system.
I will open up a terminal.
And typing i f config.
The f config.
Command.
Tells me the IP address currently assigned to the virtual machine.
As you can see, it is 190 2.168.1.112.
Now I will open up a SSH terminal to SSH into that virtual machine.
Now in my case I'm using a terminal software called as mobile XTERM.
I like to use this.
This is a free software that is available.
You could use any SSH terminal software.
You could simply use putty as well.
So create a new SSH session and specify the IP address, which is 190 2.168.1.112.
And the username is Oz Boxes.
Click on.
Okay.
Now we'll specify the password which is Oz boxes dot org and I'm logged in.