In this lecture, we will look at the various networking options available within VirtualBox.
Some of the common issues that our students face with respect to VirtualBox is around networking.
A lot of our students struggle with understanding the different kinds of networks such as Nat Bridge
and host only and what they mean and what type of network to be used when.
Also, how do multiple VMs connect with each other and how to troubleshoot issues where you can't reach
the Internet.
And that's what we will discuss in this video.
So before getting into networking and VirtualBox, let us first revise some of the basic networking
concepts.
Now computer systems like our laptops or servers have different kinds of interfaces or adapters that
are used for connectivity, such as wired Ethernet interfaces to connect to a LAN network through a
hub or a switch using a cable and wireless interfaces to connect to the network through wi fi.
Now, irrespective of how they connect to a network, once they do, they get an IP address assigned
either manually or dynamically.
If there is a DHCP server in the environment, an IP address is assigned to an interface.
In this case, we have a laptop that's connected using an ethernet cable to a switch in our home.
Once the connection is established, our laptop gets an IP address.
When you run the IP address show command, you see the interface in p0s3 and it has the IP address.
One 92.1 60 8.1.5.
Now say you have another adapter, a wi fi adapter, and you attach that to the same network, but this
time through wi fi.
Then that interface gets another IP address assigned to it and can be seen in the output of the same
command.
The same laptop now has two separate IP addresses on the same network.
If any other host were to try to reach our laptop, they may do so using any of these IP addresses.
So what I'm trying to say is every system, every computer system has different interfaces and it can
have multiple such interfaces and adapters to connect to different networks.
So it could be the same network, which is which is as it is in this case, but it could be to connect
to different networks.
And some interfaces have internet connectivity depending on what network they are connected to and the
others do not.
Once a virtual machine is provisioned in VirtualBox, if you go to the settings of that VM and in the
network tab, you will see different networking options to start with.
There are four adapters.
This means that you can configure your VM to have up to four network connections.
Now how you configure those and what do you connect these adapters to is up to you.
By default, only the first adapter is enabled and it is attached to NAT.
As you can see, there are multiple options available here.
Nat bridge adapter host only adapter being some of them.
And we will see what these options are next.
So let's start with a simple example.
Say we have a physical system like our laptop or a PC and it's connected to the network with the address.
190 2.168.1.0.
So you set an IP for your PC to one 92.1.
68 .1. ten.
And we have virtual box on it.
Say, for example, A on VirtualBox, we have provisioned multiple virtual machines, so there are four
virtual machines provisioned.
Now, how do these VMs talk to each other?
How do they read systems outside of your PC?
Now, as of now, these virtual machines are simply created.
They don't have any network or any IP address assigned to them.
So if you log in to any of these VMs through their console and try to ping one another, it would fail.
It wouldn't be you wouldn't even know what the IP address is to do a ping in the first place.
So we create a private network within our PC.
It's called as a host only network and has an address.
190 2.168.5.0.
So we attach the virtual interfaces of the VMs to this network.
Now, I'll explain how we do that in a bit, but let me first cover the concepts.
So once you attach the interfaces or the virtual interfaces of the VMs to this network, they all get
an IP address in the one 92.1 68 five series in that range.
So one system gets 190 to 168 5.2.
Another one gets 5.3, 5.4 and 5.5.
Our PC is a part of the network, so a virtual interface is created on our PC and connected to the same
network.
And it gets an IP one 92.1 60 8.5.1.
So all the VMs and PC itself are now part of a virtual private host only network.
The reason it's called host only is because the connectivity is contained within this host.
All the VMs can reach each other, but they cannot reach the outside world, nor can anyone outside
this host reach these virtual machines.
They're all on a private, internal host only network.
So how do you create this host only network, and how do you attach VMs to this?
To create this host only network on VirtualBox.
On Mac, go to file and then host network manager.
You will have a similar option available for Windows and Linux as well.
So just find out where that is.
Once you go into the host network manager.
Inside the host network manager, create a new network by clicking on the create button.
This creates an internal virtual network in our laptop and creates an interface by the name V Box Net
zero and assigns our laptop the first IP address on this interface.
Now, if you run the F config command, you see the two IP addresses assigned to my laptop, the 1i21
68 1.10 on the internet adapter and 180 to 168 5.1 on the V box net zero adapter.
So that's the network, the first network created by VirtualBox.
And you can create multiple such host only networks.
With within Marshall Box.
So now that we have created the network to attach a VM to this network.
Go to the settings page of a VM and under network, select the adapter and select attach to host only
adapter and select the new network that we created.
So do that on each VM.
And since this host only network also has DHCP enabled, the VMS get an IP assigned automatically.
Okay.
So that was one scenario.
Let's look at another option.
So say we have another physical machine in the network.
So just building off of that previous example where we have on one side we have our host only network
and the and the VMs inside it, but we also have another host that's attached to this particular network
and it has an IP 192 168 1.11 The PC has some kind of service running on it, such as, let's say a
database instance, for example, and our VMs on the first PC would like to access this particular database.
Now, in the current setup with the host only network, the VMs are not going to be able to do that
is because they are on a host only network and they cannot really reach outside of that host.
So for this we introduce a NAT network.
So instead of creating a host only network, we create a NAT network.
The NAT network is similar to the host only network where, as in we create a private network within
the physical system and we attach all the VMs to it and they all get an IP address.
But this time these VMs can access the outside world.
The VMs can now access the database using its IP address.
Now, for every packet that is sent from the VM to the database, the NAT engine which sits on the on
our host is going to replace the source IP with its own IP address so that when the database receives
a request, it's going to think that it's all coming from the first PC.
It is unaware of the VMs that are present on the first PC.
So it processes the request and sends back the data to the first PC.
The NAT engine on receiving the response, intercepts the packet and changes the address back to the
original VMs IP and forwards it back to the VM.
So that's what's called address translation, and that's why network address translation, when a request
is sent, the net from address is actually translated to the host address and then the request goes.
And then when the response is received, the two address is changed back to the original address of
the VM that in fact send the request.
So with this setup, the VMs within can access the outside world.
But remember, the outside world is still unaware of the VMs that exist within the system.
So no systems from the outside world can access the VMs inside.
So how do you do that?
To create a net network.
Go to the virtual box preferences page and select network, and there you will find NAT Networks.
Click the plus button and create a new NAT network.
Once created to attach a VM to this NAT network, go to the VM settings and under network, attach the
adapter to NAT Network.
Now note that it is different from Nat.
So Nat and Nat Network are different.
And then select the name of the NAT network.
And that's all.
So what is Nat and Nat Network?
What is the difference between Nat and Network and Nat?
NAT is the default setting of a V on virtual box.
It works similar to NAT network as in the VMs can reach the external world and uses NAT network address
translation so that when records go out, they go out with the address of the host, and when responses
are received, the address is replaced by the virtual nat router within that VM.
However, you don't have that internal network here.
So as such, the VMs are not able to reach each other.
So each VM is isolated, They cannot talk to each other, but they can talk to external systems through
the host.
So in this case, each VM kind of gets its own nat router, whereas in the earlier case there was a
NAT network and there was a single nat router that there works for all VMs.
In this case, there's more isolation between the VMs within the host.
So that was about Matt.
Now let's look at another scenario where an external host requires access to the internal VMs.
So we've been talking about internal VMs trying to access external services, but now let's see what
happens if we want to external services or external VMs to access internal VMS services or services
running on these internal VMs.
So say for example, there is a web application running on one of these VMs and there are other systems
that are on our network such as laptops, and these laptops want to access the web server that's running
inside one of these VMs.
So let's look at another kind of network known as a bridge network.
The bridge network acts as an extension of the land network, so you don't really have to create a bridge
network like how we created the host only network or the net network before the bridge network is always
there, so you just have to connect to it.
So once the VMs connect to this network, this time they get an IP address in the same IP range as that
of the external land network.
So they are assigned IPS in the range 190 to 168 one series.
And it is as though they are all part of the same external network.
Any device on the network can see them as just another virtual machine on the network.
So even though they are within the the the first host there, in fact it is as if they are all part
of the same network because the host also gets an IP address in the range 190 to 168 1.10 and the VMs
within the host also get an IP address in the same range, 1.12, 1.13.
So it's as if they are all part of the same network.
But in fact these VMs are inside this host.
So since they are all part of the same network through the bridge network, these laptops can access
any services that are that are run on these VMs.
So that's about brain network.
Okay.
So we've talked about the three kinds of network host only and Nat and Bridge.
Let's now talk about Internet connectivity in each of these cases.
In case of a net setup, whether it's a NAT network or just NAT, we learned that internal VMs can reach
external network through network address translation.
So VMs configured with a NAT interface can reach Internet as long as the host VM has Internet connectivity.
You don't really need to do anything else.
The best option, as we know, is an extension of the external network, so it makes the VM as another
host on the network.
So just like all hosts on a network, the VM should be able to reach the internet easily.
So there's nothing really required over there too.
However, in case of a host only network, the VMs are on an internal private network.
All VMs attached to that internal network can see each other, but they can't connect to any systems
outside of the host machine.
The host machine is connected to two networks the internal host only network where the VMs are.
There and the external network that has Internet connectivity and that has connectivity to the rest
of the network.
So now we can enable the host machine to forward traffic from the internal network to the external network.
Now for this you must enable IP forwarding on the host VM.
So this is by default disabled on our laptops.
Most laptops have that that functionality.
So enabling the IP forwarding feature essentially makes our laptop a router.
So a router that can route traffic one from one network to another.
Now, if you think about it, you don't really have to do that.
If all you need is to establish Internet connectivity for the VMs.
There are other ways to do that, such as by adding an additional adapter to these VMs.
Because as we learned earlier, that there are each of these has four adapters, so you can configure
a second adapter and attach it to NAT.
And that way through those adapters, those VMs will have Internet connectivity.
So that's just another additional option.
So here's what I was talking about.
So earlier we said that their of each beam can have four adapter, so you can configure the second adapter
to be attached to that.
So now when you run into connectivity issues, you know where to look at and you know that you should
be looking at the number of interfaces that are configured on the VM.
Look at what type of network they are attached to.
Check if those interfaces have IP addresses assigned and you should be able to get a fair idea why you
weren't able to reach the Internet.
Now, before I let you go, one more thing that's worth mentioning is about port forwarding.
So a lecture about VirtualBox networking is incomplete without discussing about port forwarding.
So let's look at what that is.
Let's look at a simple scenario where we have a single VM configured with NAT.
The default option Port forwarding allows us to map a port on the host to a port on the guest.
For example, Port 80 on the host could be mapped to port 80 on the guest so that any traffic that comes
in on port 80 on the host is forwarded to port 80 on the guest.
Now maybe the guest is running a web server and it's since it's a not setup, as we discussed before,
external hosts can't reach the VM, so configuring a port forward can help the web server receive requests
from external hosts, even though it's in a setup because the port forwarding forwards traffic from
the port on the host to the port on the guest.
Now it need not be the same port either.
You can map port 8080 to port 5000 on the VM.
Earlier we discussed that to SSH into the VM, we assign an IP address and then use that IP address
to SSH from the host to the guest.
Another way to do that is if you don't know the IP address of the VM and you can map port 22 of the
guest, which is the port used to establish SSH connection to another port say 2222 on the host then
you can simply ssh to the loopback IP address of the host and port 2222 and that will in fact forward
those requests to port 22 on the VM and you should be able to switch into that.
So this way you can have multiple VMs and multiple different services running on them and you can map
those services to ports on the host.
Now this is done under the Veeam network settings and by going into the port forwarding options here,
you can see the different rules to map host port to guest port as well as specify the protocols that
are used.
Well, that's it for now and I'll see you in the next lecture.