Let us now look at deploying multiple VMs on VirtualBox and configuring networking between them.
We will also look at some cloning and snapshot functionalities.
One way to create multiple VMs is to simply clone an existing VM.
So if you plan to create multiple VMs, then it's good to plan ahead so that you could first create
a template VM and then just create multiple clones from it to create a clone for an existing VM.
Right Click the VM and select the clone option.
Note that for this option to appear, the VM must be powered off.
Then give the new VM a name.
I'll limit VM two and then select the type of clone.
So there are two types of clones a full clone and a linked clone.
A full clone creates a full copy of the disk used by the existing VM.
Consuming equal amount of new space.
A linked clone uses the disk of the existing VM and only consumes space for the changes made in the
new VM.
The only concern is when you plan to move a VM from one system to another in case of the linked clone.
You will have to copy the disk of the original VM as well.
Or in case you decide to delete the original VM, you will run into issues as the linked clone has a
dependency on it.
So if you don't plan to copy your VMs, then linked clone is a good option as it consumes less space
on your on your laptop.
Okay, so I'll just select the linked clone and continue with it and create the VMM.
So we now have two VMs before turning them on.
Let us make some changes.
So we want the two VMs to be able to reach each other.
So they both must be part of the same network as per the current setting.
They are configured with Nat and so they are isolated from each other.
We also want the VMs to be able to reach the Internet as we plan to install software on them.
So we will leave adapter one with NAT, that's for the Internet and we will configure a second adapter
to connect to a host network.
For that we must first create the host network.
So go to file and select host Network manager.
Our Windows systems should also have this option.
Once it's open, create a new network.
I already have a network in this case.
I'll add a new network.
It's named V Box net one.
And as you can see, it has an IP address range one 92.1.
68.50 7.1.
If you'd like the Vrms to get an IP address assigned to them automatically, then check this box and
then click close.
Then go to the VMS network settings and set the second adapter to connect to host only network and choose
the newly created network.
Do that for both VMs.
Also note that if your system is low on resources, feel free to reduce the CPU and memory on these
VMs as necessary.
Then power on the VMs and wait for them to boot up.
Once they are up log in using the OS boxes dot org user account.
I had created a user account named Matthew on one system.
That's why you see that there.
You can also see that on the other system.
And that's because when we cloned it, all the settings get cloned as well.
Now, once logged in, open up the terminal and inspect the IP addresses.
Here you can see the new interface that was created to connect to the new host only network.
It's named NPE zero SE eight.
The IP address that got assigned automatically is one 92.1.
68.50 7.3.
Let us now check on the second system.
The second system gets IP one 92.1.
68.50 7.4.
And remember, we said that our host is also part of the network.
So our host also gets an IP address of one 92.1, 68.50 7.1 on the network.
Now they all can reach each other through these IP addresses.
We can now SSH to these VMs using these IP addresses.
We don't really need that port forwarding rule we configured in the previous demo anymore.
So ssh and use the root password.
And I will use another terminal to SSH to the other VM.
We will also test Internet connectivity.
Since we have the first adapter configured for NAT, we have Internet connectivity through that and
we see that successful.
Now just to test and show you the difference, we'll change the first adapter to use the other host
network we had instead of the NAT configuration.
Now, when we check the IP address, we see that it now has another IP on the first interface, which
earlier was configured with NAT.
And if we try to reach internet now, it is not possible.
So remember that depending on your requirements, you must set up your networking configurations.
If you simply want the VM to have internet connectivity, then set it to NAT.
Each VM is isolated, if you like multiple VMs to talk to each other and have internet connectivity,
choose NAT network.
If you want multiple VMs to reach each other, but no internet connectivity, choose host network.
In this case, your host will also be part of the same network and can reach the VMs without any port
forwarding.
If you'd like the benefits of multiple networking options, then you can have both of these on a single
VM, as we did in this demo.
So have one adapter configured to host network and the other adapter with Nat.
Now, none of these options really make your VMs visible to the external network, so your VMs are essentially
hidden.
If you like all of these and also have your VMs visible on the external network, then choose the bridged
option.
Let us now look at the snapshot feature.
With the snapshot feature, you can create a snapshot or backup of your VMs state at a particular point
in time and then restore it to that backup at a later point in time.
Let's just pick the first VMM for this demo.
Say we have an application or a file created in a directory.
And for example, we create a directory slash opt slash app and under that we create a file named Explorer
with the contents and example file.
So that's the current good state.
Let us now take a snapshot.
So click on this option on the VM and under that select snapshots, there should be a similar option
for that on other platforms as well in Windows and Linux.
So try to find that out.
Here you can see the current state.
Click on the take button to create a snapshot.
We will name it the Good state and provide a description.
You can now see a good state snapshot created here.
Now we are going to simulate a failure.
We will echo some junk data to the file to simulate some kind of corruption.
Okay, Now that we have mixed up our system and lost the original contents of the file, how do we restore
it?
Go to the snapshots window and right click the snapshot named Good State and select the restore option.
Now the restore option is grayed out because the VM is still up.
So let's first shut it down.
Now the restored option is available.
Click on it to restore state to the snapshot.
Once restored start the VMM.
We again connect to it and if you go to the opt app path, you see the exemplar TXT file and if you
look into its contents you see that it has the right contents.
Great.
So this functionality is especially useful when you are testing different software and functionalities
on VMs, for example, before making a major change to your VM, such as upgrading the version of software
or packages, you could take a snapshot of the working state to get back to in the future.
You can also clone a new VM from the snapshot.
Say you made a lot of changes and something went wrong and you're not sure what that is.
And if you'd like to create a new VM from the previous snapshot, that's possible too.
So right click the good snapshot and choose clone and then follow the same process we followed earlier
to create a new VM from that clone.
Well, that's it for now.
I will see you in the next lecture.