Let us now get introduced to the basics of Vagrant.
In the previous videos and demos, we looked at how to deploy a VM on VirtualBox.
We followed this process of first downloading the image from the OS boxes dot org website, and then
we created a new VM.
We then configured networking such as creating host networks, and then we went into the settings of
each VM and configure the interfaces to use those correct networking settings.
And then we also configured port forwarding and finally booted up the VM.
We then repeated these tasks for every VM that we wish to create.
Vagrant helps us automate all of these tasks and do all of these with a single vagrant up command.
That way, you don't have to go searching for images of operating systems or download them or create
networks or configure port forwarding manually.
Vacheron does all of that automatically.
So Vacheron is especially useful when you have complex systems involving multiple VMs.
And if you plan to deploy and manage the entire setup together.
To get started with it wagon dot com and click on the download option and then download and install
the appropriate version for your OS.
Once installed, run the vagrant in its command and specify the name of the box you'd like to deploy.
I'd like to deploy a Centaurus seven box.
So what is a box?
A box is a vagrant term and refers to a packaged format of a vagrant environment.
It contains an OHS image as well as scripts required to configure the environment.
You can find a list of all publicly available vagrant boxes at Vagrant cloud by visiting app dot vagrant
app dot com slash boxes.
Search and find the box of your choice.
Running the vagrant init command initializes the vagrant box in the current directory and creates a
vagrant file.
The vagrant file has instructions on customizing your box.
We will look at that in a bit.
To start the wagon box, run the vagrant up command.
And when this is done, Vagrant downloads the image required to create the VM.
It then creates the VM, gives it a random name and configures any settings such as port forwarding
or anything like that and waits for it to be ready.
Running the vagrant command without any options, lists, all available commands.
You can see the vagrant box command used to manage installation and removal of boxes.
We just saw the init and up command that initializes a box and brings up the VM.
You may use the suspend command to suspend a VM.
The resume command to resume a VM and the halt command to stop the VMM.
They destroy command to stop and delete the VM and the status command to get the status of a VMM.
If the vagrant file is changed, use the reload command to reload the VMM.
You can also take and restore snapshots using the vagrant Snapshot command.
You could ssh into the VM by simply running the vagrant ssh command.
Vagrant will identify the port configured for port forwarding and use that to SSH.
Vagrant also sets up ssh key based authentication, so it uses that as well.
Let's take a look at the vagrant file.
A vagrant file starts with a configuration block within the vagrant configuration block.
The image used by the box is specified.
In this case, it happens to be CentOS seven.
This is all there is configured in the default background file.
If you would like to customize this VMM, this is where you would do it and then you can share this
file with others and the VM will boot up the same way in exactly the same way with the same configurations
for everyone.
For example, you could configure port forwarding here and say Port 8080 on the host will be forwarded
to port 80 on the guest.
Or you could configure a directory to sync between the host and the VM.
That way you can easily move files from your host machine to the VM.
If you'd like to configure the CPU and memory settings on the VM, then you could do that within the
provider virtualbox block like this.
You can also configure a simple shell script to run at boot up using the shell provision block like
this.
So when you run the background up command now background provisions, EVM following the specifications
given in this vagrant file and also runs the Shell script given here, you may also include multiple
VMs in this.
This approach can help you automate the deployment of complex environments on your laptops, such as
small clusters of popular systems.
There are boxes that have automated clusters, such as Kubernetes clusters, which has multiple VMs.
VirtualBox is just one provider among the many supported by Vagrant.
You can also use Vagrant in a VMware environment such as VMware Workstation or VMware Fusion or in a
microsoft Hyper-V environment as well.
So I'd highly recommend you to check out Vagrant and get comfortable with it.
This will help you easily create and deploy a virtual machine or local lab environments, as well as
save all the work that you did and your configurations in a vagrant file that way.
In the future, you can just, if you'd like to deploy the same kind of lab environment.
All you need to do is run a background up command and then you can share that vagrant, file your custom
file with others in the community, and help others benefit from that as well.
Well, that's it for now.
Thank you for watching and I'll see you in the next lecture.