Let's take a quick demo of Vagrant to download and install vagrant.
Go to Vagrant up dotcom, then go to the downloads page and select the right version for your OS.
I'm on Mac, so I'm going to select Mac OS.
And this works the same on all operating systems, so you can follow the same instructions that I'm
following in this demo.
Once the executable is downloaded, install it on your system.
Once installed, the command vagrant should be available on your system.
That is now open up a terminal and create a directory for Vagrant where we will store all our vagrant
configurations.
We then CD into that directory and we are now ready to deploy a VM using Vagrant.
Now remember, you must have the virtual machine provider, which in this case is VirtualBox already
installed on the system.
So I already have that.
It could also be VMware Workstation or Fusion as well.
So whatever it is that you plan to use, remember it must exist on the system before you actually try
to bring up a VM using Vagrant.
Now, if it's anything other than VirtualBox, then when you run the background up command, you must
also specify that provider using the provider option.
Now we need to find vagrant boxes to deploy.
Searching for vagrant boxes in Google will land you on the vagrant cloud page.
And here you can search for various boxes for different operating systems and solutions.
I'll go with CentOS seven.
Select that in that CentOS seven page, we see a template for the vagrant file.
We could copy this and create a vagrant file by ourself manually, or if we want Vagrant to create that
file for us.
Go to the new tab and copy the command.
The command is vagrant in it and followed by the name Central seven.
All this command does is create a vagrant file with the image set to CentOS seven.
If you see the contents of the vagrant file, we see that it is really just a template with all the
options commented out.
Any line that begins with a hash is commented out.
The only line set is the line with the box name.
Running the vagrant up command now downloads the image and then creates a virtualbox VM with it.
If you open VirtualBox, you can see the VM being created.
It takes a while for it to boot up, so give it some time.
And once it's booted up, we see the machine booted and the ready message.
Now, when you run this vagrant up command and if you were using an environment other than VirtualBox,
then this is where you must also specify the provider using the provider option.
We can now ssh into the VM using the vagrant ssh command.
So even if you are on a windows environment, you don't really need another SSH terminal tool or putty
or anything.
This command just works.
It also takes care of authenticating you into the VM using SSH keys.
We are now in and we can test the version by viewing the ETSI release files.
And I check the status of the VM using the Vagrant Status command.
We see it's in a running state to shut down.
Run the vagrant.
Halt!
Command.
We now see the status is powered off.
Let's now go into the vagrant file and make some changes.
If you go all the way to the bottom, we see the VMs resource settings like memory and configuration.
It's currently commanded out.
If you look at the settings of the VM, we see that it has 512 GB of RAM and one V CPU.
Lower resources can increase boot time for the VM, so we'll increase the resources for the VM from
the vagrant file.
So let's uncomment the memory specification as well as the starting and ending of that block.
Now we will leave the memory to one gbps to provide CPU configuration, used the VB CPU's property and
we set it to two CPUs.
We can also rename the VM here.
Not sure if you notice, but the VM has a random name assigned to it.
And all of these settings can be found in the vagrant documentation page.
We save that file and every time you modify the vagrant file for the changes to take effect, you must
run the vagrant reload command.
We wait for it to boot up and we can see that the VM name is already updated to the name we specified.
Go into settings and we see the memory and CPU are set correctly as well.
At times when you boot up VMs using the background up command, you might see an error like this.
It's a timeout error.
What's happening here is that Vagrant starts the VM and waits for it to boot up completely.
However, the VM took more time to boot than Vagrant expected.
This could be because the VM is configured with very few resources and it takes a long time for the
VM to load.
The VM may end up booting properly eventually, and then you should be able to access the VM as you
would normally.
But in case you are not sure and you think it's stuck power of the VM using the vagrant hold command.
And then go to the vagrant file and you can increase the timeout by adding a property config VM boot
timeout like this.
Reloading.
The vagrant file restarts the VMM and the next time vagrant waits longer before throwing an error message.
Well, that's a quick introduction to Vagrant, and I hope it will help you set up labs quickly.
If you'd like to learn more about Vagrant.
Please let us know and we can probably create a separate course just for Vagrant, because there are
so many things that you can do with Vagrant.
You can configure multiple VMs, you can configure scripts as we saw in the lecture.
So it's a very neat tool to really set up a custom lab environment and then save that configuration
so that you can share it with others.
Well, that's it for this section.
I will see you in the next.