As with any server, any application running on any server, that server needs to be administered.
So you need to think about backing up that server and backing up specific files and folders that are
necessary for Jenkins to run.
You need to think about your restore strategy.
A backup is only as good as the RESTORE policy.
You could have a million backups in the world, but if you can't restore it properly, those backups
really don't mean much because it's a system, because it's an actual application running on a system.
Yes, Jenkins is nothing more than an application running on a system.
You need to think about how to monitor Jenkins.
Now when you're monitoring Jenkins and let's say something is going wrong, you're diagnosing errors.
You're looking at errors that pop up in the monitoring.
You're going to have to understand how to diagnose and how to fix.
Now, just like restores are only as good as a backup.
A system is only as good as how it can scale.
So, for example, let's say you're running two Jenkins servers and you need to scale up to three.
You need to scale up to four due to the load.
You need to understand how to do that because it's pretty easy in a large organization to need to scale
up those servers, depending on how many people are hitting those servers and how many jobs in the pipelines
they're running.
And then finally, you need to fully understand how to manage Jenkins.
Jenkins isn't one of those platforms that you can just put up and walk away and not touch it for ten
years.
You have to actually manage it because there is a system underneath.
There are updates that need to be done.
There are patches that need to be done.
So with that, let's go ahead and talk about administering Jenkins in this section.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.