When you think about backups on Jenkins really on any system, it's pretty similar.
You have full backups, you have snapshots, you have decremental backups, all those different types
of backup styles are available with Jenkins and primarily for the system.
So even though the application is running, the system itself still needs to be backed up.
Now here's the important bit of what to backup.
Now, of course, you should backup everything but the the end all, be all of if these things go away,
you're probably going to lose 90% of your workload.
And the primary place is the Jenkins underscore home folder.
Now, in that Jenkins underscore home folder, you're going to have your configuration files, You're
going to figure out XML, which is the configuration of Jenkins, what Jenkins looks like and what does
that mean?
Well, how you actually have Jenkins set up inside of your environment.
All of those configurations are in those config XML files.
And then again under Jenkins underscore home, there's a folder called Jobs, and those jobs are all
of your pipelines.
You need to make sure those bad boys are backed up or else you could literally lose every single CI
pipeline, every single CD pipeline, all of your work, essentially everything that you use to deploy.
So ensure that the Jenkins underscore home folder is backed up.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.