When it comes to backups and.
JENKINS There's not like a specific solution that you would use.
Really, it's kind of up to three different ways.
Number one, you could either do file system snapshots, which snapshots aren't real backups.
So I wouldn't recommend that as a long term solution.
But it's good for a daily kind of thing, maybe instead of an incremental route.
Next, you have plug ins for backups, which again, plug ins.
We have the ability to install and extend different services and different features in Jenkins.
Or you could write a shell script that backs up the Jenkins instance.
Now, for this section, what we're going to do is we're going to go and we're going to use one of the
plug ins.
But if you'd like to check out a Shell script, I did find this Shell script online, which you can
get to via this GitHub organization and then this GitHub repository right here.
And at that point, you can check it out.
See if this works for you.
But for me, I think it made more sense to kind of use a plug in because it's a little bit more managed
than maybe a one off script.
So what I'm going to do is in the Jenkins portal, I'm going to go to manage Jenkins.
And then I'm going to go to manage plugins.
And I'm going to go to available and then I'm going to type in back up.
Now, there are a few here, but from what I saw and what I see in the field, a lot of people typically
do use thin backups.
So we'll go ahead and we'll go with that one.
But I don't see anything wrong with trying out some of these other ones, like the Google Cloud backup,
for example.
Sounds kind of interesting, actually.
So I'm going to go in and I'm going to click thin backup and then I'm going to say install without restart.
I'm going to scroll down here and we can see that it did just install successfully.
So if I scroll back up and I click on Manage Jenkins again, now I just go and I scroll down here,
I can see then back up now back up your global and job specific configuration.
So I'm going go ahead.
I'm going to click on that.
And then I have a few options.
I can either backup, restore or click settings.
Let's kind of see what's in settings.
Backup directory, which if we click on that, specify the backup directory.
The Hudson process needs write access to directory.
Really, what this means is the backup directory of where this is being backed up.
So like on a local server on a file share somewhere, something like that, we can set up some backup
schedules, backup schedules for differential and full backups, number of backup sets, files excluded.
And then what files?
We want to back up here.
I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to click back and then I'll click back up now.
Now that, of course, will not work.
I just wanted to go ahead and showcase that.
The reason why is because we need a backup directory.
So what we're going to do is we're going to search into our server type in my password.
And then I'm just going to do just to see my home directory here and then I'm going to say MK Dear Jenkins
backup.
If I just see Jenkins back backup again, and this is my path.
So I'm going go ahead and I'm going to copy this.
And as we can see, the directory does exist, but it's not writable.
So depending on the permissions that you have on a server in an organization, the policies that are
available, you're going to need to set up these permissions for the directory here.
So what I did was I just C.H. modify it to seven, seven, seven.
That pretty much just means open it up to everything.
It's obviously not ideal.
Again, depending on your organization is totally going to depend on the policy, but for testing purposes
and just to showcase how the backup works, this is fine.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to save that.
Now I can click a back up now.
So now what we can do is I'm going to CD into Jenkins back up LZ here, and we can see now I have a
backup that was successful.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.