Now that Jenkins is backed up, what if we want to actually restore Jenkins to this backup right here?
Well, let's go ahead and test that out.
So we're going to go to thin backup.
We're going to click on Restore.
And now, as you can see, I actually have an option right here, restore from this backup.
What I want to do really quick is I want to take another backup.
And then I'm going to go to settings really quick.
I'm going to scroll down and we're literally going to back up everything.
Oop.
Right.
I'm going to save that.
Then I'm going to click back up again.
Okay.
And then just to confirm, as we can see, we have our three backups now.
So if I click on Restore, I now have three different backups and it'll tell me in the time so I can
just restore from the latest here.
Go ahead and I'll click Restore.
Right.
And just like that, we are back up and running it really quick.
Obviously, there isn't a whole bunch of stuff going on on this server, so it didn't take too long.
But that's essentially how you can back up and restore on your Jenkins server.
Well, that's it for this lecture we'll see in the next.