All right, everybody.
So now let's go ahead and look over the application.
So the application that we're going to be deploying is this go Web app sample app.
So I went ahead and I forked it to my GitHub organization under admin turned DevOps and you can find
it under the Go Web app sample repo.
So this is a very, very straightforward go app.
It uses go for the database backend.
And essentially what we could do is we come up, we log in and we get to this page, we go ahead and
we sign out here, we can type in test, test, and then we log in and then there are a few different
things that we can do inside of the application.
So if I scroll, you see, for example, we have access to a Swagger API.
So if I open that up, we can see all of the different API endpoints that are available.
So for example, we have one called auth log in account.
So let's go ahead and maybe check that out.
And to do that we'll just have to type in API auth log in status.
We can see that the login is true.
We go ahead and we look up account for example log in account.
We can see that this is the account that we're logged in as.
So this is the application that we're going to be using to deploy with Jenkins.
If you want, please feel free to check this out on my GitHub repo, download it, play around with
it locally if you'd like, but we will see the full deployment process here throughout this course using
this application.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.