Before we jump into Jenkins, let's go ahead and take a look at what we ultimately need to do to get
this application actually up and running.
And I'm on my local host here and you could literally do the same thing.
Just go to my GitHub, pull down the Go Web app sample repo and you could follow along here.
So the first thing that I'm going to do is I'm going to do go run, main dot, go.
And the reason why is because our main go configuration is right here in our root directory.
So when I run that the application is running successfully as we can see.
Now let me just head over to my web browser really quick and we can see that the app is up on 8080.
So I'm going to go and I'm going to log in here.
Test.
And we can see that I am officially logged into the application.
Now, something else that we could do here is I do slash API slash books.
We can see here that we get a little bit of some information back here regarding books.
We could also do slash API slash log in status.
As we can see, we're logged in.
So point being we can see if the application is up and running.
Let's head back over to VS code.
Now within VS code we can see here that we were hitting our application, we can see the output on the
terminal.
But what if we don't want to literally go through each API and hit the application?
That's pretty manual.
Well, we could run our tests.
So if I go into my controller directory here, for example, we can see that I have a bunch of tests
in here.
So I'm just going to go ahead and I'm going to open up another terminal right in vs code.
If you want to do that, you can just click the plus button and then open up a new terminal here.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to run, go test minus V dot.
What that means is run every single test inside of the controller directory.
And as we can see, all of our tests did pass successfully.
We got the pass at the end and the OC at the end and we got the 200 for the API call for all of our
get APIs, which is great.
But here's, here's the problem.
As you're kind of going through this and as you're kind of setting this up like this is a lot of manual
effort.
Imagine if you have to go in as a DevOps engineer, go through each directory and run your tests and
then confirm that your tests are good.
And to even be able to run the test, the application needs to be running.
So you have to also get the application up and running and then to confirm that the application is up
and running, you have to open up a web browser, you have to go in, you have to confirm that the APIs
are able to be hit.
There's a lot of manual effort here that goes into this.
Now, let's not forget, you can only do this with the application state as it is right now.
Let's say you do all of this testing and you're like, Yep, we're good to go here.
I tested it manually locally.
Well, you know what?
What if five changes happen in a day?
What if ten changes happen in a day?
What if they're the littlest changes?
A variable name, a function name?
It could be a super small change.
And yet you still have to go in and manually test it.
Now think about how many fires that you're going to have to put out to just do this.
You're going to have to stop everything that you're doing, any value driven work, and you're just
going to have to jump right in here and do all the tests manually.
But let's say you had your PSI solution set up in Jenkins Well, guess what?
You could actually run this command here.
This let me just up here, right here.
There you go.
Go test minus V dot.
You could run that command inside of your Jenkins CI pipeline because as we're going to learn inside
of a CI pipeline, that's where you do all of your tests, like your unit test and your integration
test, mock test.
ET cetera, etc., which is what these tests are.
So you would actually do all of this automatically inside of your CI pipeline versus you having to,
again, go spin up the application, spin up another terminal, get the test stub, go into the right
directory, run the test, confirm that they're all good.
No.
Instead of doing that, you could just set it all up in your CI pipeline.
Now, really quick, something that I did want to show.
Let's just head back over to the web browser really quick.
There is this Swagger API.
So all of these APIs that are set up on this web sample application, there's a Swagger API.
So let's say you wanted to do.
Slash swagger slash index dot HTML.
You can see every single API.
So this is actually really, really cool if you want to get a visual of what's happening inside of the
application.
All right, everybody.
That's it for this lecture.
Head over to the labs and start practicing what you've just learned.