In this lecture.
Let's take a look at providers in more detail.
We saw in the previous lecture that after we write a TerraForm configuration file, the first thing
to do is to initialize the directory with the TerraForm Init command.
When we run TerraForm in it within a directory containing the configuration files, TerraForm downloads
and installs plugins for the providers used within the configuration.
These can be plug ins for cloud providers such as AWS, GCP, Azure, or something as simple as the
local provider that we use to create a local file type resource.
TerraForm uses a plugin based architecture to work with hundreds of such infrastructure platforms.
Different providers are distributed by Hashicorp and are publicly available in the TerraForm Registry
at the URL Registry dot TerraForm dot o.
There are three tiers of providers.
The first one is the official provider.
These are owned and maintained by Hashicorp and include the major cloud providers such as GCP and Azure.
The local provider that we have used so far is also an official provider.
The second type of provider is a verified provider.
A verified provider is owned and maintained by a third party technology company that has gone through
a partner provider process with Hashicorp.
Some of the examples are the big IP provider from Fine Networks, Heroku, Digital, Ocean, etc..
And finally, we have the community providers that are published and maintained by individual contributors
of the Hashicorp community.
The TerraForm init command went run shows the version of the plugin that is being installed.
In this case we can see that the plugin name Hashicorp slash local with the version 2.00 has been installed
in the directory.
Deter from init is a safe command and it can be run as many times as needed without impacting the actual
infrastructure that is deployed.
The plug ins are downloaded into a hidden directory called TerraForm slash plugins in the working directory
containing the configuration files.
In our example, the working directory is slash root slash terraform dash local file.
The plugin name that you see here.
Hashicorp Slash Local is also known as the source address.
This is an identifier that is used by TerraForm to locate and download the plugin from the registry.
Let's take a closer look at the format of the name.
The first part of the name, which in this case is Hashicorp is the organizational namespace.
This is followed by the type which is the name of the provider, such as local.
Other examples of providers are AWS, Azure, ARM, Google, Random, etc..
The plugin name can also optionally have a hostname in front.
The hostname is the name of the registry where the plugin is located.
If omitted, it defaults to registry dot terraform dot IO, which is Hashicorp public registry.
Given the fact that the local provider is stored in the public from registry within the Hashicorp namespace,
the source address for it can be represented as registry dot, terraform, dot IO slash Hashicorp slash
local or simply by hashicorp slash local by omitting the hostname.
By default, TerraForm installs the latest version of the provider.
Provide The plugins, especially the official ones, are constantly updated with newer versions.
This is done to bring in new functionality or to add in bug fixes and these can introduce breaking changes
to your code.
We can lock down our configuration files to make use of a specific provider version as well.
We will see how to do that later in this course.