Now let's take a look at the configuration directory and the file naming conventions used in TerraForm.
So far, we have been working with a single configuration file called local ATF, and this is within
the directory called TerraForm Dash local file, which is our configuration directory.
This directory is not limited to one configuration file.
We can create another configuration file like this.
The ADF is another configuration file that makes use of the same local underscore file resource.
When applied, it will create a new file called cad dot txt.
TerraForm will consider any file with the TTF extension within the configuration directory.
Another common practice is to have one single configuration file that contains all the resource blocks
required to provision the infrastructure.
A single configuration file can have as many number of configuration blocks that you need.
A common naming convention used for such a configuration file is to call it the main F.
There are other configuration files that can be created within the directory, such as the variables
ATF output.
ATF and providers.
ATF.
We will talk more about these files in the later sections of this course.
Now let's head over to the Hands-On Labs and explore working with providers.