In this lecture, we will take a close look at the variables block in TerraForm.
First, let us look at the different arguments that a variable block uses.
The variable block inter form accepts three parameters.
The first one, which we have already used is the default parameter.
This is where we specify the default value for a variable.
The others are type and description.
Description is optional, but it is a good practice to use this argument to describe what the variable
is used for.
The type argument is optional as well, but when use it enforces the type of variable being used.
The basic variable types that can be used are string number and boolean string variables, as we have
seen in our example so far, accept a single value which can be alphanumeric that is consisting of alphabets
and numbers.
The number of variable type accepts a single value of a number which can be positive or negative.
And the Boolean variable type accepts a value of true or false.
The type parameter as mentioned previously is optional.
If it is not specified in the variable block, it is set to the type any by default.
Besides these three simple variable types, TerraForm also supports additional types such as list,
map, set, object and tuple.
Let us now see how to use all of these in TerraForm.
Let us start with list.
A list is a numbered collection of values, and it can be defined like this.
In this example, we have a variable called prefix that uses a list of values.
Mr..
Mrs..
And Sir.
But why do we call it a numbered collection?
Well, that is because each value, which is also known as an element, can be referenced by the number
or index within that list.
The index of a list always begins at zero.
In this case, the first element of the list at index zero is the word.
Mr..
The element at index one is.
Mrs..
And the final element at index two is sir.
These variables can be accessed within a configuration file like this.
With the index specified within square brackets.
Hence the expression word or prefix with index.
Zero uses the value Mr. wat or prefix with the index one uses the value Mrs. and with index two it uses
the value of sir.
Next, let us look at the type called map.
A map is data represented in the format of key value pairs.
In the variables file.
Let us create a new variable called file content with the type set to map in the default values, we
can specify as many key value pairs in close within curly braces.
Here.
The statement one and statement two are keys and the string data following them are values.
Now, to access a specific value from the map within the TerraForm configuration file, we can make
use of key matching.
In this case, we want the content of the local file resource to be the value of the key called statement
two.
And for that we use an expression war file content, which is the name of the map type variable, followed
by the matching key within square brackets.
We can also combine type constraints.
For example, if you want a list of string type elements, we can declare it like this.
To use a list of numbers, change it like this.
If the variable values used do not match the type of constraint the TerraForm commands will fail.
In this example, we have used the type list where the element should be of type number.
But the default values are all of type string.
Now when we run TerraForm commands such as a plan or an apply, you will see an error like this that
states that the default value is not compatible with the variable type constraint and that a number
is required and not a string.
And the same is applicable with maps as well.
We can use type constraints to make sure that the values of a map are of a specific type.
In the first variable block, we are using a map of type string, and in the second one we are making
use of a map that uses numbers.
Let us now look at sets.
Set is similar to a list.
The difference between a set and a list is that a set cannot have duplicate elements.
In these examples, we have a variable type of set of strings or a set of numbers.
The examples on the left are good, but the ones on the right are not.
They have duplicate values in them that will throw an error.
The default values are declared just like you would do for a list.
But remember that there shouldn't be any duplicate values here.
The next type of variable that we are going to look at are objects.
With objects, we can create complex data structures by combining all the variable types that we have
seen so far.
For example, let us consider a new variable called Bela, which is the name of a cat.
This variable is used to define the different features of this cat, such as its name, which is a string,
the color, which is a string as well.
H Which is the number, the food that it eats, which is a list of strings and a boolean value indicating
if it's a favorite pet or not.
Let us now assign some values to this variable.
Let us use name is equal to Bella.
Color is equal to brown.
Eight is equal to seven.
Food is fish, chicken and turkey and favorite pet, which is set to true.
And we can use the same default values within our variable block like this.
The last variable type that we are going to look at is tuples.
Tuple is similar to a list and consists of a sequence of elements.
The difference between a tuple and a list is that list uses elements of the same variable type, such
as string or number.
But in case of tuple, we can make use of elements of different variable types.
The type of variables to be used in a tuple is defined within the square brackets.
In this example, we have three types of elements defined.
The first is a string.
Second is a number.
And finally, a boolean.
The variables to be passed to this should exactly be three in number and of that specific type for it
to work.
Here we have passed the value of cat to the string element, the number seven to the number element
and true to the boolean.
Adding additional elements or incorrect type will result in an error as seen here.
If you add an additional value of dog to the variable, it will fail as the tuple only expects three
elements of type, string, number and boolean.
That's it for this lecture.
Let's head over to the hands on labs and explore working with variable types in TerraForm.