In this lecture, we will take a look at the different ways in which we can make use of input variables
in TerraForm.
So far, we have created input variables in TerraForm and assign default values to it based on a variable
type.
This is just one of the ways to pass on values to the variable.
Earlier, we learned that the default parameter in a variable block is optional.
This means that we can very well have our variable block look like this.
But what would happen if we run TerraForm commands now?
When we run TerraForm Apply, we will be prompted to enter values for each variable used in an interactive
mode.
If you do not want to supply values in an interactive mode, we can also make use of command line flags
like this.
With the TerraForm Command, we can make use of the dashboard option with the variable name equals to
the value format.
We can pass an as many variables as we want with this method by making use of the dashboard flag multiple
times.
We can also make use of environment variables with the F, underscore waas underscore followed by the
name of a declared variable like this.
In this example, the F underscore waas underscore file name sets the value of the variable called file
name to the value slash root slash postcode.
And similarly, the variable called length now has the value of two.
And finally, when we're dealing with a lot of variables, we can load values by making use of variable
definition files like this.
These variable definition files can be named anything but should always end in either false or false.
JSON.
Here we have declared variables and the values in a file called TerraForm to force.
If you look at the syntax used to create this file, you'll observe that this is using the same syntax
of an SQL file, but it only consists of variable assignments.
The variable definition file if called TerraForm offers or from fast JSON or by any other name ending
with dot auto dot force or auto fast JSON will be automatically loaded by TerraForm.
If you use any other file name such as variable F force, for example, you will have to pass it along
with a command line flag called dash four dash file like this.
Finally, it is important to note that we can use any of the options that we have seen in this lecture
to assign values to the variables.
But if we use multiple ways to assign values for the same variable that a form follows, the variable
definition precedence to understand which value it should accept.
To illustrate this, let us make use of a simple example.
In this case, we have a main configuration file with a single resource, a local file, which will
create file at a path declared in a variable called file name.
In the variables file.
We have not specified a default value for this variable.
And we have assigned different values to this variable in multiple ways.
We have exported the environment variable called tf underscore waas underscore file name with the value
of slash root slash cats dot text.
The TerraForm ETF for file has a value of slash root slash stakes for the same variable.
We have also made use of a variable definition file with the name variable auto force with the value
of slash root slash hypertext.
And finally, we are also making use of the Dash war option while running the TerraForm Apply Command
with the value of slash, root slash best FedEx.
So in this case, which one of these values would be accepted?
There are form follows a variable definition precedence order to determine this.
First it loads the environment variables.
Next the value in the TerraForm ETF was file.
This is followed by any file that ends with the dot auto, dot f or dot auto for JSON in an alphabetical
order.
And finally, TerraForm considers the command line flag of war or dash war dash file, which takes the
highest priority and will overwrite any of the previous values.
In this case, the variable file name will be assigned the value of slash route slash best text.
That's it for this lecture.
Let's head over to the hands on lab and practice working with the concepts that we learned in this lecture.