In this lecture, we will take a look at the different types of resource dependencies in TerraForm.
In the previous lecture, we saw how to link one resource to another using reference attributes by making
use of reference, expression and interpolation.
We were able to make use of the output of the random bit resource as an input for the local file resource.
Now, when TerraForm creates these resources, it knows about the dependency since the local file resource
depends on the output of the random pet resource.
As a result, it uses the following order to provision them.
First, TerraForm creates the random pet resource and then it creates the local file resource.
When resources are deleted, TerraForm deletes it in the reverse order the local file first and then
the random pet.
This type of dependency is called the implicit dependency.
Here we are not explicitly specifying which resource is dependent on which other resource.
TerraForm figures it out by itself.
However, there is another way to specify dependency within the configuration file.
For example, let us make use of the older configuration file without making use of the reference expression
for the file content.
If you still want to make sure that the local file resource is created after the random pet.
We can do this by using the depends on argument like this.
Here we have added a depends on argument inside the resource block for the local file, and we have
provided a list of dependencies that include the random pet resource called the My Pet.
This will ensure that the local file is only created after the random resources created.
This type of dependency is called an explicit dependency.
Explicitly specifying dependency is only necessary when a resource relies on some other resource indirectly,
and it does not make use of a reference expression as seen in this case.
In the later sections of this course, we will see how and when to use this in a real world use case.
Now let's head over to the hands on labs and explore working with resource dependencies in TerraForm.