You know, when you're logging into, I don't know, some site maybe it has a little bit of so so you
can connect and log in via like your Gmail or your GitHub or another type of email service, something
like that.
Well, that's a connection.
It allows you to connect from one service to another or it allows you to connect with one service to
another.
And that's essentially what plugins are.
Plugins allow you to connect to other services.
So for example, let's say you want to connect to Azure from Jenkins.
Well, you would download an Azure plug in, you would have it in your pipeline and then that would
be able to allow you to connect to Azure at a programmatic level and it allows you to ultimately easily
work with other products.
So for example, let's say you want to use Jenkins for the build process and you want to use, I don't
know, GitHub actions or another pipeline tool for the deployment.
You could absolutely do that.
You can do the builds via Jenkins and then send those builds to GitHub actions.
So in this section we're going to talk all about plugins, how to search for plugins, how to install
plugins in Jenkins, how to do everything plugin related.
So with that, let's go ahead and jump right in.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.