So remember in the video when we were installing Jenkins, we had that option to install the basic plug
ins, like the recommended plug ins, and then we could install other plugins.
Well, that's one way to install plugins.
But after Jenkins is actually deployed, how do we install plugins?
Well, we do that with.
The plugins index.
So there are so many different plug ins that are available.
Jenkins You've got to remember, Jenkins has been around for, I believe, over a decade now.
And because of that and because of its popularity, there's always going to be plug ins available for
Jenkins.
So if we go ahead and we look at plug ins.
Jenkins I o and we search for, I don't know, maybe Azure, we can see here that there are a bunch
of different plug ins available.
So if you want to manage Azure credentials using the Jenkins Credentials API, you can do that.
If you want to work with the Azure SDK API, you can do that Azure ad, you can do that Azure VM agents,
you can do that Azure CLY, you can do that.
You get my point.
There is a bunch of different ways that you can do this and then there are other plugins available as
well.
So like eight of us, there are a ton of plugins.
Let's look at maybe Python, there's a ton of plugins here as well.
Let's look up, I don't know, Golang, there's one plug in here that automatically installs and sets
up.
Go for the tools for the build agents, which we're going to get into.
But think of build agents like they're the things that run your pipeline essentially depending on your
platform.
So maybe you want to run a c i C platform for Mac OS.
Anyways, don't worry about that right now.
We're going to absolutely get into it.
But the point being is there are so many different plug ins that are available now.
How do we actually install those plug ins?
Well, that's it for this lecture we'll see in the next.