There's going to be plug ins that you can install without restart or you could download now and install
after restart.
So some plug ins may need you to restart your Jenkins instance, but not all of them will require you
to ultimately do that.
So I wouldn't really worry about it all that much.
But if you need to, of course we could always just do sudo system CTL restart Jenkins.
And then what that's going to do is that's going to restart our instance of Jenkins.
We can do system CTL status.
Jenkins Now we can see that it is up and running, which is great.
But if I just go ahead and I refresh here.
We'll see that Jenkins is restarting right now and the services are just coming up.
And then now we can log back in.
So that's essentially how you restart.
Jenkins If you need to for a new plug in that's getting installed or anything else, really.
Well, that's all for now.
Let's get some hands on practice.