In the previous lectures, we learned about TerraForm State and its benefits.
TerraForm State is the single source of truth for form to understand what is deployed in the real world.
However, there are a few things to keep note of when working with State, and we will learn about them
in this lecture.
State is a non optional feature in TerraForm.
However, there are a few considerations.
First one is that the state file contains sensitive information within it.
It contains every little detail about our infrastructure.
Here is an example snippet of a state file for an eight two instance, which is essentially a virtual
machine on the cloud.
The state file consists of all the attributes for virtual machine that is provisioned, such as the
allocated CPUs, the memory operating system, or the image used type and size of disks, etc..
It also stores information such as the IP address allocated to the VM and the SSH key pair used, etc..
For resources such as databases.
The state may also store initial passwords when using local state.
The state is stored in plain text JSON files.
And as you can see, this information can be classified as sensitive information.
And as a result, we need to make sure that the state file is always stored in a secure storage.
So we have two kinds of files in our configuration directory data from state file that stores state
of the infrastructure and the TerraForm configuration files that we use to provision and manage infrastructure.
When working as a team, it is considered a best practice to store it from configuration files and distributed
version control systems such as GitHub, GitLab or Bitbucket.
However, owing to the sensitive nature of the state file, it is not recommended to store them in git
repositories.
Instead, store the state in remote backend systems such as CSS three, Google Cloud Storage, Azure
Storage, TerraForm Cloud, etc..
We will see how to work with remote state backends in a dedicated section of its own.
But for now, it's important to make a note of these considerations.
TerraForm State is a JSON data structure that is meant for internal use within TerraForm.
We should never manually attempt to edit the state files ourselves.
However, there would be situations where we may want to make changes to the state file, and in such
cases we should rely on TerraForm State commands.
We will cover these in a later section of the course.