In this demo, we're going to deploy the voting application on our mini cube cluster.
So here I have created a new project folder called Voting App.
So the first thing that we are going to do is to create the pod definition files for each component
within the application.
So let's begin with the voting app itself.
So we will name this pod definition file as voting app pod YAML.
And let us build this pod from scratch.
So we will begin with the API version and set it to v one and the kind will be pod.
The metadata section would have the name which will be voting App dashboard.
And let's add a couple of labels.
The first label would be the name, which can be the same as the name of the pod, which is Wooding
Pod.
And the second label will be.
The name of the application, which is the demo voting app.
So we will kind of use that label for all the components part of this application stack.
That way we can group the components of a single application together by assigning the same kind of
label to all of them.
But they would still be a different label for each component to differentiate from each other.
So let's add the spec section.
And here the first thing that we're going to add is the name of the container.
So we'll use Voting App as a name of the container and the image.
We will make use of the custom image that we have built from the Docker samples voting app get Repository
page, which is here.
So we will use the custom images that we built under the Code Cloud Docker Hub Repository.
The name of the image here is called Cloud Sample Voting App underscore Vote.
With a tag of V one.
Now we will also specify the port for this loading application as a container port property.
So this should be the port on which the application listens for this voting app.
And we know that it's port 80, so we will set it to port 80.
Next, let's create the port definition file for the result app.
So again, I'm going to create a new file here called a Result app Port.
And because this is a pod definition file, like like before, we can simply copy the template from
the awarding app file we just created.
And then we will just make changes to the name and labels and the image.
So let us change the name to result app port and we will make the same change to the label and then
the app label will remain the same as all of these are part of the same app.
And again, let's make the change to the container name to result app.
And here the image will also be changed to code cloud slash example boarding app underscore result and
with the same tag of V one and the result application is also exposed on the container port 18.
So we will leave that as is.
Next.
Let's create the port definition file for the reddest port.
So I'm going to name the port definition file as this dashboard YAML.
And again, I'm going to make use of the previous part as the template.
And we will change the name of the pod.
So we'll change it to this part and we will use the same as the label.
And let's name the container as readies and the image should be also be read this.
And the container port for it is we will change it from port 80 to 6 379 because this is the default
port for the reader's image.
So let's save this.
And now let's create another pod.
Now, this time for our database.
We'll name it Postgres dashboard yaml.
And as before, we're going to copy paste one of the port definition files here and we'll make changes
to the name.
So this one will be Postgres Dashboard and the same for the label.
Now the name of the container would be Postgres and the image.
We can also use the post image itself without any tag, which means that it will make use of the latest
postgres image.
The container port for PostgreSQL database is 5432 by default, so we will add that in.
And we also have to add a couple of other environment variables here.
So this is to make sure that we specify the post class username and password for the database.
So as we saw in the previous lecture, the source code of the worker and the result board has the password
for the PostgreSQL database hardcoded in them.
So we must specify the initial password to be set for the database here as environment variables.
Now.
A better way to do this would be to use secrets or some kind of vault to passing these credentials and
not have these credentials in a plain text format in a file.
But those are out of scope.
For this course, we discuss about these concepts in much detail in our advanced courses on Kubernetes,
the CTA, and the courses we discuss about environment variables, services and secrets and other concepts.
So for this example to work, we have to make sure that we specify these two environment variables in
the Postgres code definition file.
So for this we will make use of an E and V section, which is a list of dictionaries, and we will have
the environment, variable name and value entered in them.
So it must be postgres underscore user for the username.
And Postgres underscore password and as a password all in caps.
Now the value for both would just be postgres for now.
And again, just to reiterate, we are adding these values because the work report and the result board
uses these credentials while connecting to the database.
And if you don't configure this, the worker will not be able to connect to the database.
And as a result, the total voting count may not add up.
So in case you run into issues with the vote count, not updating, are not able to view the results,
then this is probably an area that you can check.
So now we have created for pod the postgres pod, the is port, the two front end application ports,
the result app and the voting app.
The last one is the worker pod.
So let's create a new file for the worker pod worker product YAML.
And I'm going to copy paste the definition file.
So in here, let's make changes to the name.
So let's change the name to worker pod.
And the same for labels.
And the name of the container will be Worker app.
And the image is worker instead of what?
And one important change here is that we must remove the ports section because, as we discussed, the
worker app has no services listening, so no port definition is required.
So as a result, we can delete this entire section over here.
So we now have five port definition files for all our microservices.
Next, we will create services to expose these pods except for the for the worker.
So let's get that going.
Let's start by creating the service definition files.
So let's start with one of the internal services which is ready.
So we'll call the file as redis service yaml.
So we will start with the API version, which is we want and the kind is service.
And let's add the metadata.
And the name of the service we will use as readies itself.
So remember that this is important and we'll add a couple of labels.
The name would be set to read this debt service.
And the second one is the the one we have been using for all the other objects, which is demo voting
app.
Now, next, we will add the specs section and within this we will add the ports.
So for Redis, we know that the port to be used is six three, seven, nine and we'll also add the target
port, which is also going to be six three, seven, nine.
Now, we don't need to specify anything else like a node port because this is going to be an internal
service.
Now let us add the selector.
So in order to link the service to the port, we must specify the same labels configured for the port.
So let's copy the labels from the port definition file and we'll paste it under the selector section.
Now, since this is an internal service, we're not going to expose it outside on the network.
So that should be good.
So this file is now complete.
So let's save it.
And next we will proceed with the creation of the post press service.
So now let us create the post service file.
We'll follow the same approach as before.
We'll name this as post press service yaml.
And the easiest way to create a service now is to just copy the contents of the ready service file and
paste it here.
So again, we will make the appropriate chain.
So if you remember the architecture from the lecture, the name of the post database must be DB.
So this is because the worker app expects the name of the Postgres database to be DB.
So if you name it anything else, you'll find that the connection will fail.
So we'll now change the labels.
These labels could really be anything, so it doesn't really matter.
Let's name it as Postgres service and we can even name it as DB service.
And let's change the port to five, four, three, two, because that's the port in which the post gross
database runs.
And again, this will be five, four, three, five, four, three, two.
And let's make sure that we copy the labels from the port definition file.
So here we will copy the name label, which is set to post Chris Pod.
So let's delete the order selectors and the labels and then replace it with the new one.
So now we're done with the two internal services.
Let's now proceed to creating the external facing services, which is the voting service and the result
service.
So let's start with the Voting App Service.
Let's create a new file called Voting App Service YAML, and we will copy the contents of the other
file and then paste it here.
Again, let's change the name to voting service.
Let's change the label as well.
And we we know that this is a front end application which runs on Port 80.
So let's set that port number as the service port and as the target port.
And as before, we'll copy the labels from the definition file.
So the next step would be to create the final service, which is the result service.
So let's call the file as a result app dash service, YAML and let's copy the voting app service definition
file into here.
And then again we change the name to result and everything else is the same.
And we will update the selector section with the labels of the pod.
The result at pod.
We actually created them as internal services like the others.
Now we have created the voting app and result app service as internal services like like the others,
but they are supposed to be externally accessible, so we must set their type to node port.
So since we have not specified any type, it would be considered as cluster IP.
So let's do that now and each service.
Requires will set the type to node port, and each service also requires an additional port specification
for the node port and we will set that to 30,000 for for the voting app.
Okay, Now we will go and update the same on the result service.
So we will set the type to node port and we will add a node port port number of 30,005 for the result.
App service.
Okay, So we are done with all the all the files and we have completed the creation of all the part
and service YAML definition files.
And we will now proceed with the creation of these objects and we will then try to access the application
on the web browser.
So we will switch to the terminal of our system and we are in the voting app directory and which is
where we created all the port and service definition files.
So now we can start creating these objects.
So first let's check if there are any pod or deployments or services running on the server.
So when we see we see that there are there's nothing except for the default Kubernetes service.
There is there's nothing else running.
So let's start with the pod and the service for the voting application.
So we'll start with one by one and we'll test and make sure that they're working as expected, and then
we'll proceed further.
So to create the pod, we will use the create command and specify the pod definition file.
And similarly, let's create the service using the service definition file for voting app.
So let us now inspect the status of the pod and the service.
So if we want to see the pod and the service in a single command, we can run the cube will get pods
command and specify the service as CVC and separated by a comma.
And so it will list both the objects so we can see that the service for the boarding app is created
and it is of type node port and the pod is also created and it is in a running state.
Now, before we proceed further, let's test to see if that bit is working.
So what we could do is simply access the voting App service using a URL which could be formed by the
IP of the mini cube node.
So if you know the IP, you could just use the port number, which is 30,000 and zero for the port number
of the service and view it in a browser.
Or if you're not sure about the IP, you could run the command mini cube service and specify the name
of the service with the URL option and it'll give you the URL that you can use.
So we'll copy the URL and we will try to access this in our local browser on my system.
So here I'm at the local browser and I'm going to try and access this.
And as you can see, we are now able to load the voting application.
So that's that's one step which is complete.
Now let's not try and cast any vote for now as we don't have the databases ready.
Now let's go ahead and create the remaining objects, the ports and services.
So back to the terminal.
The next port and service that we created is the reddest port.
So we run the cube, create command with the reddest port definition file and then the service file.
And as before we run, the car will get parts and service command.
And as you can see, the red is part and service are created.
The service is now the cluster IP because this is an internal service.
And let's create the post gross database now.
We'll create the Postgres database with the post definition file.
And as well as the service definition file for creating the service.
Again, let's check the status and we can see that the Postgres pod is in a running state and similar
to the ready service.
And we can see also that the Postgres service is up as well with its name set to DB.
All right.
So now that both are readies and Postgres ports and services are up and running, we can now create
the worker pod.
And to do this, we will use the create command with the worker pod definition file.
So let's check the status of the pod.
And I can see that the worker pod is also now in a running state.
Now finally, let us create the pod and service for our result application.
So let's do the same thing as before.
Keep run the cube kernel, create a result app command and let us run the Create the result app service
as well.
Okay, so now let's check the status of all the parts and services.
And now you can see that all of our five pots are up and running, and we can see that we have two node
port services, one for our cell service and one for our voting service.
The other two services that we created are the Redis and database service, which are internal only.
So we've already accessed the voting application.
Let us also generate the URL for our results service.
So for that, I'm going to use the same command as before.
The minute Cube Service Voting Service Command will give us the URL to access our voting app and let
us change the name here to get the the URL of the result app.
So we now have both the URLs.
So let's go back to our web page, and here we have the voting application, which is running on Port
30,004.
Let's copy and paste the new URL.
So this is going to be 30,005.
So let's try and cast a vote here.
So I'm going to click on the dogs as selection.
And here you can see that there is a checkmark against the vote that we selected, which indicates that
our vote has been recorded.
Now, as in, it has been saved in the reddest database.
And you can also see that below that there's this particular web page is being processed by the voting
app Pod.
Now, if you go to the results page, you can see that the the dog's application has 100% of votes because
in this case, we just have one vote and that was for dogs.
And I can also change the vote if I want.
So I could go back and click on Cat and I can see that the result has changed to cats.
So that's our demo.
We have successfully deployed a multi tier application on our Kubernetes cluster and we have confirmed
that it's working right.
So the data actually goes through from one end all the way through, through the database, through
the worker pod to the PostgreSQL database and up to the result pod.
So it's working as expected.
Well, that's it for now.
And I will see you in the next one.