Okay, So this is what we saw in the last demo.
So we deployed pods and services to keep it really simple and we were able to access our application
from a browser.
But deploying applications as just pods has its own challenges.
Deploying pods doesn't help us scale our application easily.
If we wanted to add more instances of a particular service and if you wanted to update the application
like an image that was used in the application, then your application will have to be taken down while
the new port is created so that that may result in a downtime.
So the right approach is to use deployments to deploy an application.
So let us now improvise our setup using deployments.
So we choose deployments over replica sets as deployments automatically create replica sets as required.
And it can have it can help us perform rolling updates and rollbacks and maintain a record of revisions
and record the cause of change as we have seen in the previous demos.
So deployments are the way to go, so we'll add more pod if required for the front end applications
like voting app and result app by by creating a deployment and setting the replica to three, we'll
initially start off with just one replica for all for each of these components.
And later we'll see how easy it is to scale them to three or more.
Right?
So we will also encapsulate the databases and the worker applications within deployments.
So let's take a look at that now.
So here I am in the Visual Studio Code, and this is the project directory which has all the ports and
service definition files.
So let's create a new file for the deployment.
So we'll start with the voting app itself.
So I'll name this file as voting app dash deploy YAML and I'm going to use the split screen function
so that I can open the port and the deployment definition file side by side.
So let's create the deployment file for the building the application by using the pod definition file
as the template.
So let's start with the API version and it will be apps slash one.
The kind will be deployment.
And let's add the metadata.
The name of the deployment would be voting app dash deploy and we'll add some labels.
Next, let's add the specs section.
So it has already pre populated a couple of entries for us.
So we should be specifying the number of replicas and for all our parts, we're just going to stick
to one replica to begin with.
And since we are on a single node cluster to save some resources and under the selector section, I'm
going to add the labels from the pod.
So we use the match labels option and then we will copy and paste the labels over from the pod definition
file.
And now under the template section, I'm just going to copy everything from the metadata to the end
of the file and then paste it under the template section.
Once done, we fix the formatting.
All right, So that looks good.
So let's proceed with the next deployment, which will be the ready deployment.
So again, I open a radius, the radius part definition file.
And just like before, we create a new file called radius that deployed YAML.
And then we will copy the contents of the voting app deployment file.
Just to get started.
And we will change the name of the deployment to radius deploy.
And the same for labels as well.
So we'll stick to replica one and we will copy the labels from the pod definition file for radius.
And then we copy over the template from the pods and then paste it and then fix the formatting.
So that's done and we will proceed with the PostgreSQL deployment.
Let's copy the radius deployment file and I'll open the Postgres port definition file for reference.
And let's make the changes to the names and labels and update the selector labels with the ones on the
pod.
And then move over the definition under the template section, and then we fix the formatting.
Okay, So that looks all right.
Next, let's proceed with the worker.
So we're going to close this.
Let's create a worker app deployment file.
And we will copy and paste the template and update the name.
And let's copy the labels from the pod definition file and put it under the selector section.
And the same as before.
Let's copy the pod manifest file and paste it under the template section.
So that's the deployment for worker.
And now we are left with one for the result app.
So again, we close these two and here is our result app.
We will create a new file result app deployed YAML and we copy and paste a template again and we update
the name and labels and the template as we did before.
So we are now done with all our deployment definition files, and I'm going to get rid of all of this.
So here is all the new deployment files that we created.
And now let's head back to our terminal and create these deployments along with the services.
So before we do that, let's make sure that there are no ports and services running in the cluster.
So we have a cleaned up everything that was created for the previous demonstration.
So there are no ports or services other than the default Kubernetes one.
And now let's refresh and make sure that all our deployment files have been created.
So here we have the five new deployments that we created and the services will remain the same.
So we'll first start with the the wording app deployment.
So we'll create it using the create command and passing the app deployment file as input.
And let's also create the service and let's do a quick check on the deployment and make sure that it's
running.
So yes, we see that it is in a running state.
So now let's create the readiness deployment and followed by the ready service.
And similarly, let's create the post service deployment and the post service, and let's make sure
that everything is up.
So we see that all the ports are up, the deployments are running one out of one ports, which means
that the ports are up and running and let's check the service.
So we have the DB service, we have the ready service and the app service created so far.
So now let's clear the screen and we create the worker deployment.
Now, remember, the worker does not have a service.
So let's make sure that everything is running as as expected.
And we see that the worker part of the deployment is running as well.
So finally we create the result app deployment and the result app service.
And we now see that everything is running as expected.
So let's change this to deployment command.
SVC So we have all the the five deployments in the running state and we have four services.
So now let's get the URLs for our two front end services.
So we'll use mini queue service and the name of the service with the URL flag.
And let's do the same for the result service as well.
And we get the URLs with the ports 30,004 and 30,005.
So now I'm going to launch the Web browser and we'll try to access these applications.
So let's look at the first URL, which is the voting app itself, and let's get the word.
And let me open another window here, which will go to 30,005.
And you can see that the result is shown as expected.
So now I'm going to scale up the deployment.
So run the scale command and specify the number of replicas to three to add two more replicas for the
wedding application.
So when we run the Get Deployments command, we see that there are three paths for the voting app right
now.
Now, if we now go to the URL and refresh the page, each time we see that the page is served by a new
pod each time.
So we see how easy it is to scale our applications with deployments.
Well, that's it for this demo.
I will see you in the next.