We will now look at configuring inventory in Ansible.
Ansible can work with one or multiple systems in your infrastructure at the same time.
In order to work with multiple servers, Ansible needs to establish connectivity to those servers.
This is done using SSH for Linux and PowerShell remote for Windows.
That's what makes Ansible agent less.
Agent less means that you don't need to install any additional software on the target machines to be
able to work with Ansible.
A simple SSH connectivity with Surface Ansible needs.
One of the major disadvantages of most other orchestration tools is that you're required to configure
an agent on the target systems before you can invoke any kind of automation.
Now, information about these target systems is stored in an inventory file.
If you don't create a new inventory file, Ansible uses the default inventory file located at Etsy.
Ansible hosts location.
Let's take a look at a sample inventory file.
The inventory file is in an INI like format.
It's simply a number of servers listed one after the other.
You can also group different servers together by defining it like this.
Enter the name of the group within square brackets and define the list of servers part of that group
in the lines below.
You can have multiple groups defined in a single inventory file.
Let's take a closer look at inventory files.
For example, I have a list of servers named from 1 to 4.
However, I would like to refer to these servers in Ansible using an alias such as web server or database
server.
I could do this by adding an alias for each server at the beginning of the line and assigning the address
of that server to ansible underscore host parameter.
Ansible underscore host is an inventory parameter used to specify the FCN or IP address of a server.
There are other inventory parameters too.
Some of them are ansible underscore connection, ansible, underscore port, ansible, underscore user
and ansible underscore.
Ssh underscore pass.
And civil underscore connection is what defines how Ansible connects to the Target server.
As we discussed in the previous slide, is this an SSH connection to a Linux server or a win arm connection
to a Windows server?
This is how we define if the target host we wish to connect to is a Linux or a Windows host.
You could also set it to local host to indicate that we would like to work with the local host and not
connect to any remote host.
If you don't have multiple servers to play around with, you could simply start with a local host in
your inventory file.
Ansible underscore port defines which part to connect to.
By default.
It is set to port 22 for SSH, but if you need to change you can set it differently using ansible underscore
port parameter.
Ansible underscore user defines the user used to make remote connections by default.
This is set to root for Linux machines.
If you need to change this, define it as shown here.
Ansible underscore ssh underscore paths defines the ssh password for Linux.
Note that storing passwords in plain text format like this may not be very ideal.
The best practice is to set up SSH key based passwordless authentication between the servers and you
should definitely do that in your production or corporate environments.
But for now, we want to start with the absolute basics of Ansible without getting too much into security
or other topics.
So to begin with, we'll start with a really basic setup with a username and password.
Otherwise you will be stuck configuring and troubleshooting security issues for the most part of this
course.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
Head over to the coding challenges and practice working with inventory files in Ansible.
I will see you in the next lecture.