We will now look at playbooks and Ansible.
Ansible playbooks are Ansible, orchestration, language.
It is in playbooks where we define what we want Ansible to do.
It is a set of instructions.
You provide Ansible to work its magic.
For example, it can be as simple as running a series of commands on different servers in a sequence
and restarting those servers in a particular order.
Or it could be as complex as deploying hundreds of VMs in a public and private cloud infrastructure,
provisioning storage to VMS, setting up their network and cluster configurations, configuring applications
on them, such as web server or a database server, setting up load balancing, setting up monitoring
components, installing and configuring backup clients, and updating configuration database with information
about the new VMs, etc..
Let's take a closer look at how playbooks are written.
Remember all playbooks are written in YAML format, which is why we spent some time earlier getting
our hands dirty with yaml.
A playbook is a single YAML file containing a set of plays.
A play defines a set of activities to be run on a single or a group of hosts.
A task is a single action to be performed on a host.
Some examples of a task are executing a command or a script on the host.
Installing a package on the host or performing a shutdown or a restart operation.
Let's take a look at an actual playbook.
Shown here is a simple ansible playbook that contains a single play named Play one.
The goal of this play is to run a set of activities one after the other on the local host.
Remember that the host you want to run these actions is defined at the play level.
In this case, we just want to test on the local host, which is why it is set to local host.
This could be anything from your inventory file.
Next, we run a set of commands, one after the other on the host.
First we print the date.
Then we run a script on the server, followed by installing the HTTP feed package using the Yum module
and finally starting the web server using the service module.
Let's look at this sample Playbook format and try to relate it to what we learned in the Yamal section
earlier.
I've made a minor change and split the list of tasks into two separate places.
The YAML file, which is our playbook, contains a list of two plays.
This is noted by the Dash.
So the playbook is a list of dictionaries in YAML terms.
Each play is a dictionary and has a set of properties called name hosts and tasks.
Remember, these are properties of a dictionary and so the order doesn't really matter.
So even if you swap the position of name or host, it's still a valid play.
However, this is not the same for tasks.
The tasks, as you can see, is a list or an array as denoted by the dashes.
Lists are ordered collection, so the position of entries matter.
If you swap the position of entries here, we're instructing Ansible to start the web service first
before installing the HTTP service, which is not desired.
So the YAML format is key while developing playbooks.
You must pay extra attention to the indentation and structure of the file.
The house parameter indicates which host you want these operations to run on.
Remember the host you want to perform this operations against is always set at a play level.
Currently, this is set to local host, which means that all these actions listed under tasks is going
to be performed on the local host.
You could have any host or group specified here, but you must ensure that the host or group is first
defined in the inventory file we created earlier.
The host defined in the inventory file must match the host used in the playbooks and all connection
information for the host is retrieved from the inventory file.
If you specify a group.
Instead, the listed tasks will be executed on all the host listed under that group simultaneously.
Let's move on to modules.
The different actions run by tasks are called modules, in this case command script.
Yum and service are Ansible modules.
There are hundreds of other modules available out of the box.
Information about these modules is available in the Ansible documentation website.
Or you could simply run the Ansible dash dock dash command to get familiar with the basic playbook structure
in the upcoming exercises.
You simply need to know the basic command module.
Later on we will go through some other basic modules in more detail.
Finally, once you successfully build the Ansible playbook, how do you run it?
It's very simple.
Execute the Ansible playbook command and specify the name of the Ansible playbook you just created.
And that's it.
If you do Ansible dash playbook, dash help command, you will get to know more about some additional
parameters available for this command.
We will go through some of them in a later section.
That's it for now.
Head over to the demo and followed by the coding exercises section and practice working with playbooks.