We will now look at modules in Ansible.
Ansible modules are categorized into various groups based on their functionality.
Some of them are listed here.
System modules are actions to be performed at a system level, such as modifying the users and groups
on the system, modifying IP tables, firewall configurations on the system, working with logical volume
groups, mounting operations or working with services, for example, starting stopping or restarting
services in a system, command modules are used to execute commands or scripts on a host.
This could be simple commands using the command module or an interactive execution using the ECS module.
By responding to prompts.
You could also run a script on the host using the script module File modules help work with files.
For example, use the ACL module to set and retrieve ACL information on files.
Use the archive and archive modules to compress and unpack files, use find lining file and replace
modules to modify the contents of an existing file.
Database modules help in working with databases such as MongoDB, MySQL, MySQL or PostgreSQL to add
or remove databases or modify database configurations.
The cloud section has a vast collection of modules for various different cloud providers like Amazon,
Azure, Docker, Google, OpenStack and VMware being just a few of them.
There are a number of modules available for each of these that allow you to perform various tasks,
such as creating and destroying instances, performing configuration, changes in networking and security,
managing containers, data centers, clusters, virtual networking, Voisin and a lot more.
And then there are Windows modules that help you use Ansible in a Windows environment.
Some of these are when copy to copy files, when command to execute a command on a Windows machine.
And there are a bunch of other modules available to work with files on Windows, create an IIS website,
install a software using MSI installer, make changes to registry using REG, edit and manage services
and users in Windows.
These are just a few modules in few categories.
There are a lot more and a comprehensive list can be found at docs dot, ansible dot com along with
detailed instructions on each of them.
Let's look at a few of these modules in detail to understand how you can use them and how to read the
documentation page.
We will start with the command module.
The command module is used to execute a command on a remote node.
The parameters of the command module as listed in the documentation page is shown here.
Shown is a sample Ansible playbook using the command module.
As you can see, to use the module, you simply create a key value pair of the module name and the parameter
which is the command.
And in this case.
In this case, we are instructing Ansible to run the data command on the host, followed by executing
the cat XY resolved or conf command to list the contents of the file.
In case you needed to change directory before executing a command.
For example, I will rewrite the second command in a different form now by removing SC from the CAT
command and setting change directory parameter to slash ETSI.
This will ensure that Ansible changes directory to slash ETSI before executing the command.
This is how a parameter and value is passed to this command module.
The creates parameter is used to perform a check before the command is run.
For example, this command to create the folder will only run if the folder does not exist.
The remaining parameters are self explanatory, so we will skip them.
Except for this one right here called Free form.
This is worth looking at as you may see it in different modules.
Free form indicates that this module takes a free form command to run.
So what does that mean?
You will not be able to input a parameter with the name free form like how we just used change directory
or create options or command input such as cat, etsi, resolved or conf or make directory slash folder
is the free form input.
Not all modules support input like this.
For example, the copy module which is used to copy files from a source to a destination, only takes
parameterized input and not free form input.
So as you can see here, copy requires a source file as CRC parameter and destination as dest parameter.
However, the previous command module did not really require you to specify key equals value format.
For the command to run.
The command in the command module is a free form parameter.
Another module to look at is the script module.
The script module executes a script which is located locally on the Ansible controller machine on one
or more remote nodes after transferring it over to run a script on one or hundreds of servers.
You really don't have to copy it over to all the servers.
Ansible takes care of automatically copying the script to the remote node and then executing it on the
remote systems.
This is done through a very simple play that looks like this.
Use the script module and specify the location of the script on the Ansible controller machine and the
arguments.
Let's look at the service module.
The service module is used to maintain services on a system such as starting stopping or restarting
a service.
This Ansible playbook is used to start various services in a particular order.
First, we start the database service using the service module.
Then the service module, unlike the previous modules, do not have a free form input, which means
you have to pass input in a key value pair format.
We use the name parameter to specify the name of the service we wish to start.
In this case, PostgreSQL and the state parameter indicates the operation we would like to perform in
this case started.
Now, if you're wondering why is it started instead of START?
Well, hold on to your thoughts and we will come back to that in a bit.
Now, there are two ways of writing this statement.
You can either write it like this or write it in a dictionary or a map format like this.
They're one and the same.
Remember in YAML terms, name and state are properties of service.
Let's add a few more tasks to start HTTP PD service followed by Engine X service like this.
So back to our question on why the action is started and not start.
If we were to instruct Ansible to start a service, we would say start the service Hpdi and not start
TED the service http rd.
So then why is it start?
Ted and not start?
We're not instructing Ansible to start the service.
Instead, we are instructing Ansible to ensure that the service http rd is started.
That essentially means if HTTP service is not already started started, if a HTTP service is already
started, then don't do anything.
This is called item potency.
As per the Ansible documentation and operation is item potent if the result of performing at once is
exactly the same as the result of performing it repeatedly without any intervening actions.
Thus started, stopped and restarted actions instruct Ansible to ensure the service is in a particular
state.
Majority of the modules in Ansible are important and Ansible highly recommends this.
The overall idea is that you should be able to run the same playbook again and Ansible should report
that everything is in an expected state.
If something is not, Ansible takes care of putting it to the expected state.
The lime in file module is used to find a line in a file and replace it or add it if it doesn't already
exist.
For example, we are given a task to add a new DNS server into the ETSI resolve dot com file.
This simple ansible playbook using the line in file task adds the new name server information into the
ETSI resolve dot com file.
Remember the line in file module is important.
Let's compare this Ansible playbook with a simple script that tries to achieve the same results.
If this script is run multiple times, it adds a new entry into the file each time, which is not desired.
If you run the Ansible playbook multiple times, it will ensure there is only a single entry in the
file.
Neat.
Well that's it for now on modules and Ansible.
Head over to the coding exercises section and practice working with modules.
I will see you in the next lecture.