We will now look at variables and ansible.
So what are variables?
Just like any other scripting or programming language.
Variables are used to store values that varies with different items.
For example, let's say we are trying to perform the same operation of applying patches to hundreds
of servers.
We only need a single playbook for all 100 servers.
However, it's the variables that store information about the different host names, usernames or passwords
that are different for each server.
We have already worked with variables earlier when we worked in the inventory section.
If you remember in an inventory file that looks like this, the ansible host ansible connection, ansible
SSH paths are all examples of variables.
We can define as many variables as required like this.
We could also define variables inside the playbook.
This is a playbook we created earlier to add a DNS entry into the series of action file.
To add a variable, we could simply add a var directive followed by variables in a key value pair format.
In this case DNS server followed by the DNS server IP.
We can also have variables defined in a separate file dedicated for variables.
We will learn about this more later when we talk about includes and roles.
So we have now defined variables, but how do we use them?
In the previous playbook we have defined a variable DNS server, but we have not used it anywhere.
What would be the right place to use that?
In this line here where we defined the name server IP address, we could replace the hardcoded value
with the value from the variable.
To use a variable, simply enter the variable name and closed in double braces or curly brackets like
this.
When we run the playbook, Ansible will replace it with the value in the variable.
Let's look at another example.
This is a longer playbook that is used to set multiple firewall configurations, which has a number
of values hardcoded in it.
If someone else wanted to reuse this playbook, he would have to modify the playbook to change these
values.
If these values that can vary are moved to the inventory file and refer to it in the playbook using
double curly braces, we could get away with modifying the inventory file alone in the future and not
have to modify the playbook itself.
And even better way to do this would be to move the variables into a file in the name of the host,
in this case, Web HTML.
This is now a host variable file, and all values defined in this file are available for use by the
playbook when it is run for that host.
This way it is better organized.
Remember this format we are using to use variables in playbooks is called Jinja two templating.
We have an entire course on ginger to templating for the absolute beginners on Code Cloud.
So check it out when you get time.
Finally, while using variables with ginger to templating, remember to enclose it within codes if you're
starting your assignment with the variable.
However, if the variable is in between a sentence like this, then that is not really required.
Let's head over to exercises to play around with variables in coding exercises.