Hello and welcome to the Docker for Beginners Course.
My name is Moonchild Manabat and I will be your instructor for this course.
I'm a DevOps and cloud trainer at Code Icloud.com, which is an interactive hands on online learning
platform.
I've been working in the industry as a consultant for over 13 years and have helped hundreds of thousands
of students learn technology in a fun and interactive way.
In this course, you will learn Docker through a series of lectures that use animation illustration
and some fun analogies that simplify complex concepts.
We have demos that will show you how to install and get started with Docker, and most importantly,
we have hands on labs that you can access right in your browser.
I will explain more about it in a bit.
But first, let's look at the objectives of this course.
In this course we first try to understand what containers are, what Docker is, and why you might need
it and what it can do for you.
We will see how to run a Docker container, how to build your own Docker image.
We will see networking in Docker and how to use Docker compose what Docker registry is, how to deploy
your own private registry.
And we then look at some of these concepts in depth and we try to understand how Docker really works
under the hood.
We look at Docker for Windows and Mac before finally getting a basic introduction to container orchestration
tools like Docker Swarm and Kubernetes.
Here's a quick note about Hands on Labs.
First of all, to complete this course, you don't have to set up your own labs.
Well, you may set it up if you wish to, if you wish to have your own environment.
And we have a demo as well.
But as part of this course, we provide real labs that you can access right in your browser anywhere,
anytime, and as many times as you want.
The labs give you instant access to a terminal to a docker host and an accompanying quiz portal.
The quiz portal asks a set of questions such as exploring the environment and gathering information,
or you might be asked to perform an action such as running Docker Container.
The quiz portal then validates your work and gives you feedback instantly.
Every lecture in this course is accompanied by such challenging interactive quizzes that makes learning
Docker a fun activity, so I hope you're as thrilled as I am to get started.
So let us begin.