We're going to start by looking at a high level overview on why you need Docker and what it can do for
you.
Let me start by sharing how I got introduced to Docker and one of my previous projects.
I had this requirement to set up an end to end application stack, including various different technologies
like a web server using Node.js and a database such as MongoDB and a messaging system like Redis and
an orchestration tool like Ansible.
We had a lot of issues developing this application stack with all these different components.
First of all, their compatibility with the underlying OSS was an issue we had to ensure that all these
different services were compatible with the version of OS we were planning to use.
There have been times when certain version of these services were not compatible with the OS and we've
had to go back and look at different OS that was compatible with all of these different services.
Secondly, we had to check the compatibility between the services and the libraries and dependencies
on the OS.
We've had issues where one service requires one version of a dependent library, whereas another service
requires another version.
The architecture of our application changed over time.
We've had to upgrade to newer versions of these components or change the database, etc. And every time
something changed, we had to go through the same process of checking compatibility between these various
components and the underlying infrastructure.
This compatibility matrix issue is usually referred to as the matrix from hell.
Next, every time we had a new developer on board, we found it really difficult to set up a new environment.
The new developers had to follow a large set of instructions and run hundreds of commands to finally
set up their environments.
We had to make sure they were using the right operating system, the right versions of each of these
components, and each developer had to set all that up by himself each time.
We also had different development test and production environments.
One developer may be comfortable using one OS and the others may be comfortable using another one.
And so we couldn't guarantee that the application that we were building would run the same way in different
environments.
And so all of this made our life in developing, building and shipping the application really difficult.
So I needed something that could help us with the compatibility issue and something that will allow
us to modify or change these components without affecting the other components and even modify the underlying
operating systems as required.
And that search landed me on Docker.
With Docker, I was able to run each component in a separate container with its own dependencies and
its own libraries, all on the same VM and the OS, but within separate environments or containers.
We just had to build the Docker configuration once and all our developers could now get started with
a simple Docker run command irrespective of what the underlying operating system they run.
All they needed to do was to make sure they had Docker installed on their systems.
So what are containers?
Containers are completely isolated environments, as in they can have their own processes or services,
their own network interfaces, their own mounts, just like virtual machines, except they all share
the same OS kernel.
We will look at what that means in a bit.
But it's also important to note that containers are not new with Docker.
Containers have existed for about ten years now and some of the different types of containers are lxi,
lxi, lxi, hdfs, etc..
Docker utilizes lcs sea containers.
Setting up these container environments is hard as they are very low level, and that is where Docker
offers a high level tool with several powerful functionalities, making it really easy for end users
like us to understand how Docker works.
Let us revisit some basic concepts of operating systems first.
If you look at operating systems like Ubuntu, Fedora, CC or Santos, they all consist of two things
and OS kernel and a set of software.
The OS kernel is responsible for interacting with the underlying hardware, while the OS kernel remains
the same, which is Linux.
In this case, it's the software above it that makes these operating systems different.
This software may consist of a different user interface drivers, compilers, file managers, developer
tools, etc. So you have a common Linux kernel shared across all OSes and some custom software that
differentiate operating systems from each other.
We said earlier that Docker containers share the underlying kernel.
So what does that actually mean?
Sharing the kernel?
Let's say we have a system with an Ubuntu OS with docker installed on it.
Docker can run any flavor of OS on top of it as long as they are all based on the same kernel in this
case Linux.
If the underlying OS is ubuntu, docker can run a container based on another distribution like debian,
fedora, souce or CentOS.
Each docker container only has the additional software that we just talked about in the previous slide
that makes these operating systems different.
And Docker utilizes the underlying kernel of the Docker host, which works with all OSes above.
So what is an OS that do not share the same kernel as this windows and so you won't be able to run a
Windows based container on a docker host with Linux on it.
For that you will require Docker on a Windows server.
Now it is when I say this that most of my students go, Hey, hold on there, that's not true.
And they install Docker on Windows Run a container based on Linux and go see it's possible.
Well, when you install Docker on Windows and run a Linux container on Windows, you're not really running
a Linux container on Windows.
Windows runs a Linux container on a Linux virtual machine under the hood.
So it's really Linux container on Linux, virtual machine on Windows.
We discuss more about this on the Docker on Windows or Mac later during this course.
Now, you might ask, isn't that a disadvantage then, not being able to run another kernel on the OS?
The answer is no, because unlike hypervisors, Docker is not meant to virtualize and run different
operating systems and kernels on the same hardware.
The main purpose of Docker is to package and containerized applications and to ship them and to run
them anywhere any time as many times as you want.
So that brings us to the differences between virtual machines and containers, something that we tend
to do, especially those from a virtualization background.
As you can see on the right, in case of Docker, we have the underlying hardware infrastructure and
then the OS and then Docker installed on the OS.
Docker then manages the containers that run with libraries and dependencies alone.
In case of virtual machines.
We have the hypervisor like ESX on the hardware and then the virtual machines on them.
As you can see, each virtual machine has its own OS inside it and then the dependencies and then the
application.
The overhead costs, higher utilization of underlying resources as there are multiple virtual operating
systems and kernels running.
The virtual machines also consume higher disk space as each VM is heavy and is usually in gigabytes
in size, whereas Docker containers are lightweight and are usually in megabytes in size.
This allows Docker containers to boot up faster, usually in a matter of seconds, whereas VMs, as
we know, takes minutes to boot up as it needs to boot up the entire operating system.
It is also important to note that Docker has less isolation as more resources are shared between the
containers like the kernel.
Whereas VMs have complete isolation from each other.
Since VMs don't rely on the underlying OS or kernel, you can run different types of applications built
on different OSes, such as Linux based or Windows based apps on the same hypervisor.
So those are some differences between the two.
Now, having said that, it's not an either container or virtual machine situation.
It's containers and virtual machines.
Now, when you have large environments with thousands of application containers running on thousands
of Docker hosts, you will often see containers provisioned on virtual Docker hosts.
That way, we can utilise the advantages of both technologies.
We can use the benefits of virtualization to easily provision or decommission Docker host servers as
required.
At the same time, make use of the benefits of Docker to easily provisioned applications and quickly
scale them as required.
But remember that in this case we will not be provisioning that many virtual machines as we used to
before, because earlier we provisioned a virtual machine for each application.
Now you might provision a virtual machine for hundreds or thousands of containers.
So how is it done?
There are lots of containerized versions of applications readily available as of today, so most organisations
have their products containerized and available in a public Docker repository called Docker Hub or Docker
Store.
For example, you can find images of most common operating systems, databases and other services and
tools.
Once you identify the images you need and you install Docker on your host, bringing up an application
is as easy as running a Docker run command with the name of the image.
In this case, running a Docker run Ansible command will run an instance of Ansible on the Docker host.
Similarly, run an instance of MongoDB, Redis and Node.js using the Docker run command.
If you need to run multiple instances of the web service, simply add as many instances as you need
and configure a load balancer of some kind in the front.
In case one of the instances were to fail, simply destroy that instance and launch a new one.
There are other solutions available for handling such cases that we will look at later during this course.
And for now, don't focus too much on the commands.
We will get to that in a bit.
We've been talking about images and containers.
Let's understand the difference between the two.
An image is a package or a template, just like a VMM template that you might have worked with in the
virtualization world.
It is used to create one or more containers.
Containers are running instances of images that are isolated and have their own environments and set
of processes.
As we have seen before, a lot of products have been tokenized already in case you cannot find what
you're looking for.
You could create your own image and push it to Docker Hub Repository, making it available for public.
So if you look at it, traditionally developers developed applications, then they hand it over to ops
team to deploy and manage it in production environments.
They do that by providing a set of instructions, such as information about how the host must be set
up, what prerequisites are to be installed on the host, and how the dependencies are to be configured,
etc..
Since the ops team did not really develop the application on their own, they struggle with setting
it up when they hit an issue, they work with the developers to resolve it.
With Docker, the developers and operations teams work hand in hand to transform the guide into a Docker
file with both of their requirements.
This Docker file is then used to create an image for their applications.
This image can now run on any host with Docker installed on it and is guaranteed to run the same way
everywhere.
So the ops team can now simply use the image to deploy the application.
Since the image was already working when the developer built it and operations have not modified it.
It continues to work the same way when deployed in production, and that's one example of how a tool
like Docker contributes to the DevOps culture.
Well, that's it for now.
And in the upcoming lecture we will look at how to get started with Docker.