We will now see how to get started with Docker.
Now Docker has two editions, the Community Edition and the Enterprise edition.
The community edition is the set of free Docker products.
The Enterprise edition is the certified and supported container platform that comes with enterprise
add ons like the Image Management Image Security, Universal Control Plan for managing and orchestrating
container runtimes.
But of course these come with a price.
We will discuss more about container orchestration later in this course and along with some alternatives.
For now, we will go ahead with the community edition.
The community edition is available on Linux, Mac Windows or on cloud platforms like AWS or Azure.
In the upcoming demo, we will take a look at how to install and get started with Docker on a Linux
system.
Now, if you are on Mac or Windows, you have two options.
Either install a Linux VM using VirtualBox or some kind of virtualization platform and then follow along
with the upcoming demo, which is really the most easiest way to get started with Docker.
The second option is to install Docker desktop for Mac or Docker desktop for Windows, which are native
applications.
So if that is really what you want to take out the Docker for Mac and the Windows sections towards the
end of this course and then head back here once you are all set up.
We will now head over to a demo and we will take a look at how to install Docker on a Linux machine.