In this demo, we look at how to install and get started with Docker.
First of all, identify a system, physical or virtual machine or laptop that has a supported operating
system.
In my case I have an ubuntu VM.
Go to docs dot docker dot com.
And click on Get Darker.
You will be taken to the Docker Engine Community Edition page.
That is the free version that we are after.
From the left hand menu.
Select your system type.
I chose Linux in my case and then select your OS flavor.
I choose Ubuntu.
Read through the prerequisites and requirements.
Your ubuntu system must be 64 bit and one of the supported versions like disco, cosmic, bionic or
senile.
In my case, I have a bionic version to confirm.
View the ETSI release file.
Next uninstall any older versions if one exists.
So let's just make sure that there is none on my host.
So I'll just copy and paste that command.
And I confirm that there are no older version that exists on my system.
The next step is to set up repository and install the software.
Now, there are two ways to go about this.
The first is using the package manager by first updating the repository using the app git update command,
then installing the prerequisite packages and then adding dockers official GPG keys and then installing
docker.
But I'm not going to go that route.
There is an easier way.
If you scroll all the way to the bottom, you will find the instructions to install Docker using the
convenience script.
It's a script that automates the entire installation process and works on most operating systems.
Run the first command to download a copy of the script and then run the second command to execute the
script to install Docker automatically.
Give it a few minutes to complete the installation.
The installation is now successful.
Let us now check the version of Docker using the Docker version command.
We've installed version 19.0 3.1.
We will now run a simple container to ensure everything is working as expected.
For this.
Head over to Docker Hub at Hub.
Docker dot com.
Here you will find a list of the most popular Docker images like Engine X, MongoDB, Alpine, Node.js,
Redis, etc..
Let's search for a fun image called We'll See.
We'll say is Docker version of Cows, which is basically a simple application that trains a cow saying
something.
In this case, it happens to be a will copy the Docker run command given here.
Remember to add sudo and we will change the message to Hello world.
On running this command.
Docker pulls the image of the Wales application from Docker Hub and runs it, and we have our Vale saying
Hello.
Great.
We're all set.
Remember, for the purpose of this course, you don't really need to set up a Docker system on your
own.
We provide hands on labs that you will get access to, but if you wish to experiment on your own and
follow along, feel free to do so.