Hello and welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture we will discuss about the Kubernetes service cluster IP.
A full stack Web application typically has different kinds of parts hosting different parts of an application.
You may have a number of pods running a front end web server, another set of pods running a backend
server, a set of pods running a key value store like Reddit, and another set of pods maybe running
a persistent database like MySQL.
The web front end server needs to communicate to the backend servers, and the backend servers need
to communicate to the database as well as the ready services, etc..
So what is the right way to establish connectivity between these services or tiers of my application?
The pods all have an IP address assigned to them as we can see on the screen, but these IPS, as we
know, are not static.
These pods can go down any time and new pods are created all the time.
And so you cannot rely on these IP addresses for internal communication between the application.
Also, what if the first front end port at 10 to 40 4.0.3 need to connect to a backend service?
Which of the three would it go to and who makes that decision?
A Kubernetes service can help us group the pods together and provide a single interface to access the
pods in a group.
For example, a service created for the back end part will help group all the back end parts together
and provide a single interface for other parts to access the service.
The requests are forwarded to one of the pods under the service randomly.
Similarly, create additional services for Redis and allow the back end parts to access the ready systems
through the service.
This enables us to easily and effectively deploy a microservices based application on Kubernetes cluster.
Each layer can now scale or move as required without impacting communication between the various services.
Each service gets an IP and name assigned to it inside the cluster, and that is the name that should
be used by other ports to access the service.
This type of service is known as cluster IP.
To create such a service as always, use a definition file in the service.
Definition file first used the default template which has API version kind, metadata and spec.
The API version is v one kind is service and we will give a name to our service.
We will call it backend.
Under specification we have type and ports.
The type is cluster IP.
In fact, cluster IP is the default type.
So even if you didn't specify it, it will automatically assume the type to be cluster IP.
Under ports we have a target port and port.
The target port is the port where the back end is exposed, which in this case is 80, and the port
is where the service is exposed, which is 80 as well.
To link the service to a set of ports we use selector.
We will refer to the port definition file and copy the labels from it and move it under selector and
that should be it.
We can now create the service using the cube control, create command, and then check its status using
the cube control.
Get services command.
The service can be accessed by other parts using the cluster IP or the service name.