Let us now look at another type of service known as the load balancer type.
So we have seen the note port service that helps us make an external facing application available on
a port on the worker nodes.
So let's turn our focus to the front end applications, which are the voting app and the result app.
Now we know that these ports are hosted on the worker nodes in a cluster, so let's say we have a four
node cluster.
And to make the applications accessible to external users, we create the services of type node port.
Now the services with type node port help in receiving traffic on the port on the nodes and routing
the traffic to the respective ports.
But what URL would you give your end users to access the applications?
You could access any of these two applications using IP of any of the nodes and the high port.
What the service is exposed on.
So that would be for IP and port combinations for the voting app and for IP and port combination for
the result app.
So note that even if your ports are only hosted on two of the nodes, they will still be accessible
on the IP of all the nodes in the cluster.
Say the pods for the voting app are only deployed on the nodes with IP 70 and 71.
They would still be accessible on the ports of all the nodes in the cluster.
So that's how a service is configured.
So you would share these URLs to your users to access the application, but that's not what the end
users want.
They need a single URL like example voting abc.com or the example result App.com to access the application.
So how do you achieve that?
Now, one way to achieve this is to create a new VMM for load balancer purpose and install and configure
a suitable load balancer on it like air proxy or Engine X, etc. Then configure the load balancer to
route traffic to the underlying nodes.
Now setting all of that external load balancing and then maintaining and managing that can be a tedious
task.
However, if we were on a supported cloud platform like Google Cloud or AWS or Azure, I could leverage
the native load balancer of that cloud platform.
Kubernetes has support for integrating with the native load balancers of certain cloud providers and
configuring and configuring that for us.
So all you need to do is set the service type for the front end services to load balancer instead of
Node port.
Now remember that this only works with supported cloud platforms.
So GCP, AWS and Azure are definitely supported.
So if you set the type of service to load balancer.
In an unsupported environment like VirtualBox or any other environment, then it would have the same
effect as setting it to Node port where the services are exposed on a high end port on the nodes there.
It just won't do any kind of external load balancer configuration.
So later on when we walk through the demos of deploying our application on cloud platforms, we will
see this in action, right?
So that's it for now.
I will see you in the next lecture.