Welcome to this lecture on Docker engine.
In this lecture, we will take a deeper look at Docker architecture, how it actually runs applications
in isolated containers and how it works under the hood.
Docker engine, as we have learned before, is simply referred to a host with Docker installed on it.
When you install Docker on a Linux host, you're actually installing three different components the
Docker daemon, the rest API server and the Docker CLI.
The Docker daemon is a background process that manages Docker objects such as the images, containers,
volumes and networks.
The Docker Rest API server is the API interface that programs can use to talk to the daemon and provide
instructions.
You could create your own tools using this rest API and the Docker CLI is nothing but the command line
interface that we've been using until now to perform actions such as running a container, stopping
containers, destroying images, etc. It uses the rest API to interact with the docker daemon.
Something to note here is that the doctor Cly need not necessarily be on the same host.
It could be on another system like a laptop and can still work with a remote docker engine.
Simply use the dash option on the Docker command and specify the remote Docker engine address and a
port as shown here.
For example, to run a container based on Engine X on a remote docker host, run the command Docker
Dash H equals 10.1.
23 .2.1.
Colon 2375.
Run NDA annex.
Now let's try and understand how exactly our application's containerized in Docker.
How does it work under the hood?
Docker uses namespaces to isolate workspace, process IDs, network inter process, communication mounts
and Unix timesharing systems are created in their own namespace, thereby providing isolation between
containers.
Let's take a look at one of the namespace Isolation technique Process ID namespaces.
Whenever a Linux system builds up, it starts with just one process with a process ID of one.
This is the root process and kicks off all the other processes in the system.
By the time the system boots up completely, we have a handful of processes running.
This can be seen by running the PS command to list all the running processes.
The process.
IDs are unique and two processes cannot have the same process ID.
Now, if we were to create a container, which is basically like a child's system within the current
system, the child's system needs to think that it is an independent system on its own and it has its
own set of processes originating from a root process with a process ID of one.
But we know that there is no hard isolation between the containers and the underlying host.
So the processes running inside the container are in fact processes running on the underlying host.
And so two processes cannot have the same process ID of one.
This is where namespaces come into play with process ID namespaces.
Each process can have multiple process IDs associated with it.
For example, when the processes start in the container, it's actually just another set of processes
on the base Linux system and it gets the next available process ID, in this case five and six.
However, they also get another process ID starting with ID one in the container namespace, which is
only visible inside the container.
So the container thinks that it has its own root process tree and so it is an independent system.
So how does that relate to an actual system?
How do you see this on a host?
Let's say I were to run an Engine X server as a container.
We know that the engine X container runs an engine X service.
If we were to list all the services inside the Docker container, we see that the Engine X service running
with a process ID of one.
This is the process ID of the service inside of the container namespace.
If we list the services on the Docker host, we will see the same service but with a different process
ID.
That indicates that all processes are in fact running on the same host but separated into their own
containers using namespaces.
So we learned that the underlying Docker host, as well as the containers, share the same system resources
such as CPU and memory.
How much of the resources are dedicated to the host and the containers, and how does Docker manage
and share the resources between the containers?
By default there is no restriction as to how much of a resource a container can use, and hence a container
may end up utilizing all of the resources on the underlying host.
But there is a way to restrict the amount of CPU or memory a container can use.
Docker uses C groups or control groups to restrict the amount of hardware resources allocated to each
container.
This can be done by providing the dash dash CPU's option to the Docker run command, providing a value
of 0.5.
We'll ensure that the container does not take up more than 50% of the host CPU at any given time.
The same goes with memory.
Setting a value of 100 MB to the dash dash memory option limits the amount of memory the container can
use to 100 megabytes.
If you're interested in reading more on this topic, refer to the links I posted in the reference page.
That's it for now on Docker Engine.
In the next lecture we talk about other advanced topics on Docker storage and file systems.
See you in the next lecture.