Hello and welcome to this lecture and we are learning advanced Docker concepts.
In this lecture we're going to talk about Docker storage drivers and file systems.
We're going to see where and how Docker stores data and how it manages file systems of the containers.
Let us start with how Dockers stores data on the local file system.
When you install Docker on a system, it creates this folder structure at where lib Docker you have
multiple folders under it called FS containers, image volumes, etc..
This is where Docker stores all its data by default.
When I say data, I mean files related to images and containers running on the Docker host.
For example, all files related to containers are stored under the containers folder, and the files
related to images are stored under the image folder.
Any volumes created by the Docker containers are created under the volumes folder.
Well, don't worry about that for now.
We will come back to that in a bit.
For now, let's just understand where Docker stores its files and in what format.
So how exactly does Dockers store the files of an image and a container?
To understand that, we need to understand Dockers layered architecture.
Let's quickly recap something we learned When Docker builds images, it builds these in a layered architecture.
Each line of instruction in the Docker file creates a new layer in the Docker image with just the changes
from the previous layer.
For example, the first layer is a base Ubuntu operating system, followed by the second instruction
that creates a second layer which installs all the empty packages.
And then the third instruction creates a third layer, which with the python packages followed by the
fourth layer that copies the source code over.
And then finally the fifth layer that updates the entry point of the image.
Since each layer only stores the changes from the previous layer, it is reflected in the size as well.
If you look at the base window image, it is around 120 megabytes in size.
The apt packages that I installed is around 300 MB B and then the remaining layers are small.
To understand the advantages of this layered architecture.
Let's consider a second application.
This application has a different docker file, but it's very similar to our first application as in
it uses the same base image as Ubuntu uses the same python and flask dependencies, but uses a different
source code to create a different application and so a different entry point as well.
When I run the Docker build command to build a new image for this application.
Since the first three layers of both the applications are the same.
Docker is not going to build the first three layers.
Instead it reuses the same three layers it built for the first application from the cache and only creates
the last two layers with the new sources and the new entry point.
This way, Docker builds images faster and efficiently, saves disk space.
This is also applicable if you were to update your application code.
Whenever you update your application code such as the API.
In this case, Docker simply reuses all the previous layers from cache and quickly rebuilds the application
image by updating the latest source code, thus saving us a lot of time during rebuilds and updates.
Let's re-arrange the layers bottom up so we can understand it better.
At the bottom we have the base Ubuntu layer, then the packages, then the dependencies, and then the
source code of the application and then the entry point.
All of these layers are created when we run the Docker build command to form the final Docker image.
So all of these are the Docker image layers.
Once the build is complete, you cannot modify the contents of these layers and so they are read only
and you can only modify them by initiating a new build.
When you run a container based off of this image using the Docker run command, Docker creates a container
based off of these layers and creates a new writable layer on top of the image layer.
The writable layer is used to store data created by the container such as log files written by the applications,
any temporary files generated by the container or just any file modified by the user on that container.
The life of this layer, though, is only as long as the container is alive.
When the container is destroyed, this layer and all of the changes stored in it are also destroyed.
Remember that the same image layer is shared by all containers created using this image.
If I were to log in to the newly created container and say, create a new file called temp txt, it
will create that file in the container layer which is read and write.
We just said that the files in the image layer are read only, meaning you cannot edit anything in those
layers.
Let's take an example of our application code.
Since we bake our code into the image.
The code is part of the image layer and as such is read only after running a container.
What if I wish to modify the source code to say test a change?
Remember the same image layer may be shared between multiple containers created from this image.
So does it mean that I cannot modify this file inside the container?
No, I can still modify this file, but before I save the modified file, docker automatically creates
a copy of the file in the read write layer, and I will then be modifying a different version of the
file in the read write layer.
All future modifications will be done on this copy of the file in the read write layer.
This is called copy on write mechanism.
The image layer being read only just means that the files in these layers will not be modified in the
image itself.
So the image will remain the same all the time until you rebuild the image using the Docker build command.
What happens when we get rid of the container?
All of the data that was stored in the container layer also gets deleted.
The change we made to the API and the new temp file we created will also get removed.
So what if we wish to persist this data?
For example, if we were working with a database and we would like to preserve the data created by the
container, we could add a persistent volume to the container.
To do this.
First, create a volume using the Docker volume, create command.
So when I run the Docker volume, create data, underscore volume command, it creates a folder called
data underscore volume under the VAR lib Docker volumes directory.
Then when I run the Docker container using the Docker run command, I could mount this volume inside
the Docker containers read write layer using the Dash V option like this.
So I would do a Docker run Dash V, then specify my newly created volume name followed by a colon and
the location inside my container, which is the default location where my SQL stores data.
And that is where lib my SQL and then the image name my SQL.
This will create a new container and mount the data volume we created into our lib MySQL folder inside
the container.
So all data written by the database is in fact stored on the volume created on the Docker host.
Even if the container is destroyed, the data is still active.
Now, what if you didn't run the Docker volume?
Create command to create the volume before the Docker run command?
For example, if I run the Docker run command to create a new instance of MySQL container with the volume
data, underscore volume two, which I have not created yet, Docker will automatically create a volume
named data, underscore volume two and mounted to the container.
You should be able to see all these volumes if you list the contents of the WAAS lib Docker volumes
folder.
This is called volume mounting as we are mounting a volume created by Docker under the var lib Docker
volumes folder.
But what if we had our data already at another location?
For example, let's say we have some external storage on the Docker host at forward slash data and we
would like to store database data on that volume and not in the default where Docker volumes folder.
In that case we would run a container using the command Docker run Dash V, but in this case we will
provide the complete path to the folder we would like to mount that is forward slash data, forward
slash MySQL.
And so it will create a container and mount the folder to the container.
This is called bind mounting.
So there are two types of mounts, a volume mounting and a bind.
Mount volume mount mounts a volume from the volumes directory and bind Mount mounts a directory from
any location on the Docker host.
One final point to note before I let you go.
Using the Dash V is an old style.
The new way is to use dash mount option.
The dash dash mount is the preferred way as it is more verbose, so you have to specify each parameter
in a key equals value format.
For example, the previous command can be written with the dash mount option as this using the type
source and target options.
The type in this case is bind.
The source is the location on my host and target is the location on my container.
So who is responsible for doing all of these operations?
Maintaining the layered architecture, creating a writable layer, moving files across layers to enable
copy and write, etc..
It's the storage drivers.
So Docker uses storage drivers to enable layered architecture.
Some of the common storage drivers are a UFS beta of FFS ZFS device mapper overlay and overlay to.
The selection of the storage driver depends on the underlying OS being used, for example, with Ubuntu.
The default storage driver is a UFS, whereas this storage driver is not available on other operating
systems like Fedora or CentOS.
In that case, device mapper may be a better option.
Docker will choose the best storage driver available automatically based on the operating system.
The different storage drivers also provide different performance and stability characteristics.
So you may want to choose one that fits the needs of your application and your organization.
If you would like to read more on any of these storage drivers, please refer to the links in the attached
documentation.
For now.
That is all from the darker architecture concepts.
See you in the next lecture.