We now look at networking in Docker.
When you install Docker, it creates three networks automatically bridge null and host.
Bridge is the default network a container gets attached to.
If you would like to associate the container with any other network, you specify the network information
using the network command line parameter like this.
We will now look at each of these networks.
The Bridge Network is a private internal network created by Docker on the host.
All containers attached to this network by default, and they get an internal IP address usually in
the range.
One 72.17 series.
The containers can access each other using this internal IP if required.
To access any of these containers from the outside world, map the ports of these containers to ports
on the Docker host, as we have seen before.
Another way to access the containers externally is to associate the container to the host network.
This takes out any network isolation between the Docker host and the Docker container.
Meaning if you were to run a web server on Port 5000 in a web app container, it is automatically as
accessible on the same port externally without requiring any port mapping as the web container uses
the host's network.
This would also mean that unlike before, you will now not be able to run multiple web containers on
the same host on the same port as the ports are now common to all containers in the host network.
With the non network.
The containers are not attached to any network and doesn't have any access to the external network or
other containers.
They run in an isolated network.
So we just saw the default burst network with the network ID one 72.70 .0.1.
So all containers associated to this default network will be able to communicate to each other.
But what if we wish to isolate the containers within the Docker host?
For example, the first two web containers on internal network 172 and the second two containers on
a different internal network like 182.
By default, Docker only creates one internal bridge network.
We could create our own internal network using the Command Docker network, create and specify the driver,
which is bridge in this case and the subnet for that network, followed by the custom isolated network
name run.
The Docker Network LS command to list all networks.
So how do we see the network settings and the IP address assigned to an existing container?
Run the Docker, inspect command with the ID or name of the container, and you will find a section
on network settings.
There you can see the type of network the container is attached to its internal IP address, MAC address
and other settings.
Containers can reach each other using their names.
For example, in this case I have a web server and a MySQL database container running on the same node.
How can I get my web server to access the database on the database container?
One thing I could do is to use the internal IP address assigned to the MySQL container, which in this
case is one 72.70 .0.3.
But that is not very ideal because it is not guaranteed that the container will get the same IP when
the system reboots.
The right way to do it is to use the container name.
All containers in a docker host can resolve each other with the name of the container.
Docker has a built in DNS server that helps the containers to resolve each other using the container
name.
Note that the built in DNS server always runs at address.
120 7.0.0. 11.
So how does Docker implement networking?
What's the technology behind it like?
How were the containers isolated within the host?
Docker uses network namespaces that creates a separate namespace for each container.
It then uses virtual ethernet pairs to connect containers together.
Well, that's all we can talk about it for now.
More about these are advanced concepts that we discussed in the advanced course on Docker, on Code
Cloud.
That's all for now from this lecture on networking.
Head over to the practice test and practice working with networking in Docker.
And we'll see you in the next lecture.