In this demo, we're going to create a pod again.
But this time, instead of making use of the color run command, we are going to create it using a YAML
definition file.
So our goal is to create a YAML file with the pod specifications in it.
Now there are many ways to do it.
You could just create one in any text editor.
So if you're on windows you could just use notepad or if you're on Linux as I am just using native editor
like VI or Vim, an editor with support for YAML, language would be very helpful in getting the syntax
right.
So instead of notepad at all, a tool like notepad plus plus in Windows or vim in Linux would be better.
Now I'll talk more about tips and tricks and other tools and IDs that can help with this more in the
upcoming lectures.
And for now, let's take with the very basic form of creating a YAML file using v editor on my Linux
system.
So here I am on my Linux terminal and I'm going to make use of whim text base editor to create this
pod definition file.
So the name of the file I'm going to call as pod YAML and as seen in the lecture, we will start off
with the four root level elements or the root level properties that we that we saw, which are API version
kind, metadata and spec.
So we know that the value for API version for a pod is V one.
The kind is pod with a capital P, so it is case sensitive.
So that's important.
And metadata is a dictionary and it can have values where we define the name of the pod.
So I'm going to use name as an X and we can have additional labels that we can specify under it.
So labels again is also a dictionary and it can have as many labels as you want under it.
So we can specify a label which is a key value pair such as an app and engine X.
And we can also add more labels like tier and set it to front end.
Anything that can help us group this particular pod.
Next, we have to define the spec.
So spec is also a dictionary and it has an object called containers.
So before we move on to that, we have to make sure that we get the indentation right.
For example, the app and tier are children of the labels property, so it has to be in the same kind
of vertical line here.
And similarly under metadata, you have name and labels which are the children of metadata.
So they both have to be within the same vertical line.
So you have to make sure that the spacing is correct.
Typically it would be two spaces or a tab, but it is recommended not to use tabs.
So always stick to two spaces and and stick to that throughout.
So the next thing that we're going to configure is the container.
So a container is a list of objects.
Now we first give it a name and note that this is the name of the container within the pod, and there
could be multiple containers and each can have a different name.
So one container could be named app and another container could be named helper.
Any name that makes sense to you.
We're going to use the same name as that of the container image.
So we will just name it Engine X.
And the second object that we're going to add here is the image name, which is the Docker hub image.
Name of the container that we're going to create.
So the image name is again, Engine X, and if you're using other registries than Docker Hub, then
make sure to specify the full path to that image repository here.
Now remember that we can add additional containers to the port as well.
So if you have to do that, we have to declare the secondary element to the list, which would be the
second object in the list.
So here I can, for example, add a busy box container using the busy box image, and that would be
the second element of the array.
So in this case, we're going to stick to one single container.
So I'm going to just delete that.
And I'm now going to hit escape colon WQ to save this file and we will just use the CAT command to make
sure that the file was created with the expected contents.
So make sure the format is correct.
So the name and labels are children of metadata, and you can see that they are on the same kind of
vertical line.
And similarly, labels have two children, which are the two labels app and Tier and Speck has a list,
and we are defining it as a list with a hyphen followed by the objects.
So we can make use of the card, create command or the cattle apply command.
So the create and apply command kind of works the same.
If you're creating a new object, right, you can either use, create or you can use apply.
It doesn't matter.
And we pass in the file name using the F option.
And here we can see that the pod has been created.
So let's check the status real quick.
And you can see that it's in container creating state.
And then when we check again, we see that it's in the running state.
And as before, if you want to get more details about the port, you can always run the described command
and specify the name of the port.
And you should get a much more in depth information about the port.
So that's it for this demo.
In the next section, we will learn some tips and tricks of developing YAML files easily using IDs.