In the previous demo, we used the Vim Command line editor to create our pod definition file.
We created a pod called Engine X with a couple of labels, and we use the index image.
Now, while this works well, the editor is quite basic and it can be quite difficult to make use of
them.
If you want to create and edit long or even large number of YAML files.
The same goes with notepad or other tools in windows.
They are very basic and prone to errors.
They don't really tell you if you made a mistake.
The Kubernetes object definition files using YAML can be developed much easier using IDE tools.
Now there are many IDs out there that are free to use, such as those from chat brains, IntelliJ Idea
and Pi charm.
Atom is another free tool eclipse or netbeans that a lot of Java developers use.
And all of these come with support for YAML files and they will help in highlighting errors in a YAML
file and make making sure that you develop them right.
But they won't natively tell you if there are errors within the Kubernetes manifest files that you are
developing.
For example, if you typed in a wrong property name or if you are using a dictionary instead of a list.
And that's where you need some kind of an extension or a plugin that could help point those out for
you.
So those tools that can first verify the structure of your YAML, file the syntax, making sure that
it works fine, and also point out errors related to Kubernetes.
Write support for Kubernetes.
And so these IDs come with support for extensions and plugins that can help with that.
And those plugins could either be free or paid.
Now, one ID that we found that is freely available and works on all different operating systems and
also has a free extension for YAML.
Validation for Kubernetes is the Microsoft Visual Studio Code ID.
It's easy to set up and get started and so we will use that as our ID for the rest of this, for the
rest of the demos in this course.
Now, you don't necessarily have to use the same tool.
Feel free to use any ID of your choice and try to find a plugin or extension that can help with developing
Kubernetes YAML files for the ID of your choice.
So in this demo we're going to first install vs code.
So here I am at the code dot Visual Studio dot com website, and since I'm running on an Ubuntu based
distribution, I'm going to download the Debian package.
It should automatically list the right version to download for you depending on your operating system.
And as it says here, we shall studio code is free and open source software.
We will wait for the download to complete.
The download has been completed and since it's a Debian package, I'm just going to install it directly
on my system.
So let's wait for the installation to complete.
The installation has been completed now and I'm going to launch vs code.
Once open, this is what it would look like after refresh installs.
So we will go to the extensions section first and search for YAML and look for the extension which is
published by Red Hat.
This is the extension that has support for kubernetes yaml files.
Now in most cases this particular yaml extension is installed by default, but if it's not in your case,
then you'll see that here and you can go ahead and click on the install button to install and enable
it.
Now before we get started with developing Co-presenters definition files, using this extension, we
have to make a small change in our settings to configure VTS code to use the YAML extension for Kubernetes
files.
Right.
So by default, this YAML extension provides basic YAML validation functionality to enable Kubernetes
support.
We must configure it to work with YAML files that we plan to develop.
So there are two ways to do it.
One way is to click on this gear icon on the YAML file yaml extension and go to extension settings and
scroll all the way to the bottom where there is a YAML schemas option and click on the edit in settings
json file option.
Now this will take you to the settings json file.
This file may or may not have some contents already based on other extensions or configurations that
you might have already done.
So if it's a new installation, it might look empty like this.
So whatever it may be, our goal is to simply add a small section of code into this file.
It should have the YAML schema section if you came here following the path that I showed.
We're going to add an entry for Kubernetes schema support.
We add a schema for Kubernetes for all YAML files using the start YAML pattern.
So we're basically saying that we want to use Kubernetes schema for all YAML files that we developed
using VS code.
If you don't really want to do that, if you don't want to use the Kubernetes schema for all the files
instead if you plan to create.
Kubernetes fires using a particular pattern, then you can specify that pattern or extension here.
So we will just leave it as it is.
Now, this is a case sensitive as well.
So make sure that you use all small case for the word Kubernetes in this file.
So one thing that you'll have to do is to reload the Visual Studio code after making this change so
it takes effect.
So just exit and restart vs code at this point.
Now, another way, get to these settings JSON file is to use the control plus P shortcut key where
a search bar would open at the top.
And then there you type in settings JSON and then go to the settings JSON file from there.
But if this doesn't work, use the gear icon approach that I just showed.
Okay, So here again, as you can see that this file has already been saved so we don't have to do anything
else.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to close this Visual Studio Code editor and I'm going to open it
up again.
Once it is up, I'm just going to make sure that the YAML extension is enabled.
And so we don't have an option to enable or install here, which means that it is already enabled.
Okay, so let's now open a folder on our system.
So in this case, I'm going to open the directory called Kubernetes for Beginners, which is where our
pod definition file resides, the one that we created earlier with the VIM editor in the previous demo.
For the purpose of this demonstration.
Let's create another file.
So click on a new file and let's call it index.html.
So now we are going to create a new YAML file using the Visual Studio code editor and we'll make use
of the YAML extension that we just installed.
So we'll see how that works.
But to make this work.
First, we have to create the first root level property or the element called API version and which
for POD will be V one.
Now once you put that in the Kubernetes support part of the extension we installed kicks in.
And then it'll start suggesting additional properties and performing validations.
So note that you must have that one line in the first line in for the rest of the suggestions to work.
Now, if I type in K four kind, it will suggest the available root level properties, starting with
K and it suggests kind.
So if I just press tab it will auto finish it auto completed for me and then press control, spacebar
and type P and it will show you the list of all different objects that are available, starting with
P.
So in this case, we're interested in pods.
So I'm going to select pod.
And if I hit enter and plus M, then metadata is suggested and again hit control space and it will suggest
supported options.
The YAML extension knows that this metadata is a dictionary, so it has already kind of intended the
lines to the right for me.
So I'm going to add a name field here and again, we use the control space to complete and you will
notice that there is this error indicated here below the name and it is expecting a string type field
here.
So as long as this is empty, it will continue to show that error.
So let me add a name of the part which could be index two.
And as soon as I complete that, you'll see that the error indicator is gone.
So now again, if I hit enter, you'll see that it maintains the right indentation and it keeps it at
the same vertical line.
As the child of metadata, which is name.
So now the next one that I'm going to add is label again, press control space and it will autocomplete
label for me.
And now if I press tab, it knows that labels is also a dictionary.
So it has maintained that additional formatting.
Now here it won't suggest any properties or labels because labels could really be anything.
So it's up to you to decide what labels to add or for that pod.
And that's why there is no suggestions here.
Now I will add a label such as environment and set it to production so that that would be the only label
that I want to add right now.
So now to go back to the root level again, I'm just going to press backspace twice and it takes me
to the level of metadata and in the same vertical line.
So now the next thing that we want to add is a specs section.
Again, we make use of the control space shortcut and it will suggest options.
Note that if the suggestion does not include what you're expecting, then there is probably something
wrong with the format of your file.
So you're probably not in the right place to add that file.
So that's an additional support the extension provides to prevent you from creating a file with an incorrect
structure.
So I hit tab to choose that suggestion.
And the extension knows that for part, what comes directly underneath the specs section is the container
section, and that containers is a list.
So it has created a list here with the first element already populated and waiting on you for the name.
So let us set a value for the name of the container here.
We can use Engine X and if I hit enter, it maintains the right indentation for me to add another container
and say we would like to specify an image for the first container.
So if I make a mistake here, for example, if I add an image property and set it to say engine X,
again, it knows that there is an error because and if I just highlight on top of that, it says bad
indentation for a mapping entry.
So we have to make sure that all properties of a single container are correctly aligned under it.
One thing to remember here is that it doesn't really validate if the image name that you're using are
valid image names.
So the names of images you specify or the names that you use for your pot or containers or the labels
that you assign to objects could really be anything.
So those are not validated and it won't give you an error if you used an image that's not available
on Docker registry.
So that's up to you to make sure that you get those right.
However, it does validate certain fields that has to have values supported by Kubernetes, such as
the kind field at the top being said to POD or a deployment.
So if you used a value other than a kind that is supported by Kubernetes, then it will throw an error.
Okay, So now if you want to add another element to this array, we can do that by hitting enter and
using backspace to go back to the same level as the previous element.
And I can add additional containers here.
For example, add a new array element with the hyphen.
Then let us, for example, say busy box as the new name of the new container and the image is set to
a busy box as well.
So now our code is clear and as you can see, there are no errors.
Now, I don't really need the second container for now, so I'll just go ahead and delete this line
and make sure that everything else is is clean.
Okay, so now let's save this file.
Now, let us check out another property of the editor.
So if we click on the outline field here, we can see the entire data structure of the YAML file and
in a graphical format.
So this is the YAML file on the on the right.
And here you can see the four root elements here, the kind and if I click on this it'll highlight the
line where we have the root element.
So we have the API version which is V one, we have kind, which is port, and you'll see that it also
has the other two root elements.
For example, metadata, which is a dictionary, as you can see with this curly braces here, which
indicates a dictionary.
And if you open that, you can see that the the children of metadata, which the first one is labels
and labels, is also a dictionary object which has a value of and we.
So it presents in a hierarchal or a tree kind of structure.
And similar to that, we also have the spec section, which is a dictionary which has an array called
containers, and you can spot an array using the double square brackets.
And if I narrow it down, the first element of the containers array, which is the element zero, has
two values key value pairs, which has an image which is equal to index and which has a name and an
X as well.
So this is quite handy to help you explore the structure of the file if you are not sure what's wrong
and where.
So we have successfully created our port definition file, easily using the YAML extension and the auto
completion features.
So we can now create a port from this yaml file from the command line as you normally would.
So you would go to the terminal and just type the LS command and you can see that the engine x yaml
file is here under the Kubernetes for beginners directory.
And just let us quickly view this file.
And you can see that it's exactly as it's supposed to be.
And you could now create a pod using the cube cutter, create or apply command and passing in this file
as input.
Okay.
So in this in the upcoming coding exercises section, you will first gain practice on getting the YAML
files right?
So if you are already familiar with YAML files and the formatting etc., then feel free to skip those.
But if you are new then we have we've created these coding exercises so that you get really really comfortable
with YAML files, especially the Kubernetes YAML files before you actually head into the real labs.
So just like the coding exercises that you worked with earlier, feel free to work through these.
And then once you're done with these coding exercises, then you'll have the real lab environments where
you will explore existing parts and creating new parts on real Kubernetes clusters by developing YAML
files.
So that's it for this lecture and I will see you in the next one.