Hello and welcome to this demo on The Solution.
Once you click start scenario, you will be in the terminal.
The terminal is to a master node in a Kubernetes cluster.
At the top you have the link for the quiz portal.
So we'll click on the portal link to open up the quiz Portal.
And here you have all the questions that you need to solve, all the questions and challenges that that
are presented to you.
So we have a list of about 12 to 13 questions available and about one hour to solve all the challenges.
So we will start with some of the information gathering exercises.
So the first question here is how many pods exist on the system in the current default namespace?
So I go back to my terminal and I run the cube control, get Pods command, and I see that there are
no resources found.
So that's zero.
So we'll select the answer as zero.
So that's correct.
In the next question, we are asked to create a new pod with the engine X image.
Now we can do that in different ways.
You can either create a pod definition file and create a pod with the engine X image, or in this case
I'm just going to run the cube control, run command and create a deployment with the engine X image.
This in fact creates a deployment.
However, the deployment in turn creates a pod with the image engine X.
So to answer the question, all you need to do is somehow create an animate pod with the engine and
x image.
So.
That's right.
The next question is how many pods exist on the system now?
So I'm going to run the cube control, get pods command, and I can see that there is the engine X image
that we just created.
However, there are also a few other parts that are created as part of this question, so we'll count
the number of pods.
So that's one, two, three, four, four is the answer.
So I'm going to select four.
So that's correct.
Next, we're asked to find out the image used to create the new pods.
So if you go back to the terminal, we will now run the cube control, describe pod command and specify
the name of any one of those new pods.
And this will give us detailed information about the pod.
And under this we can look at the container section and the image that is used is busy box.
So PC box is the right answer.
Next.
Which notes are these parts placed on?
So if you go back and run the command cube control, get pods.
But with the dash o wide option, it prints some additional columns.
And here you can see that all the parts are on Node zero one.
So Node one is the answer to that question.
Okay, now we're setting up some changes.
So a new part is created, which is called this web app Pod, and we're asked to find the number of
containers in the Web app pod.
So if you look at this output here itself, you see that under the ready column, it says 1/2.
And so that two indicates the total number of containers part of that pod.
You can also run the cube control, describe pod command and look under the container section and count
the number of pods.
So we have an X and agent X.
So there are two containers part of that pod.
So two is the right answer.
What images are used in the new Web app iPod.
So if you look under the same output, you see that there is Y and X, and there is H and x.
So those are the two images used, SGI and X, and Agent X is the right answer.
Okay.
Now, what is the state of the container Agent X in the pod web app.
So if you look at the agent section for Agent X, you see that the state is waiting.
So if you go back.
It should be one of either error or waiting.
So that's the right answer.
Now, why do you think the container age index in the pod web app is in the error state or in the waiting
state?
So if you look at the reason right in the next line, it says image, pull back off.
If you're not clear what that means, you can scroll down and look at the under the events section and
you see that it says fail to pull image is an X error response from daemon repository, an index not
found.
What that basically says is that there is no repository in Docker hub called Agent X or there's just
no image with the name Agent X.
So the right answer is a docker image with this name does not exist on Docker Hub.
It should be Docker Hub.
It's kind of truncated there.
So that's the right answer.
So what does the ready column in the output of the Cube control get pod command indicate?
So let's run the cube control, get pods command.
The ready column has two numbers separated by a slash, so it indicates.
The second part indicates the total number of containers in the pod.
And the first pod indicates the total number of number of containers that are ready.
So it's the containers that are ready and the containers, total number of containers in the pod.
So the answer is not the first one, not the second one, but it is the third one running containers
in pod and the total containers in pod.
Now we are asked to delete the Webmap pod.
So if you try to delete it, if you try to check the answer without deleting, it will tell you that
it's failed.
So just to delete the pod from the cube control delete pod web app command and that should delete the
pod when you check again.
That is successful.
Now we are asked to create a new pod with the name readies and with the image ready is one, two, three.
Now you can create a pod using the pod definition file.
Now, if you're not sure about the format of the pod definition file, head over to the Kubernetes documentation
page.
Now, this is one area that you must be you must practice.
And browsing through the Kubernetes documentation page, this is especially helpful if you are preparing
for the Kubernetes certification exam.
So in the Kubernetes certification exam, you are given one tab of your browser to access Kubernetes
documentation.
So you can only have one tab, and you must walk through that single page at all times to find information.
So you should know how to find whatever you're looking for in the you can use the search button, so
you should know what to search for.
In this case, I'll just search for pods and I'll just select the first result.
If I walk through, I do not find a pod definition file, so it should be in the other languages, the
pod overview section.
And if you look under that, you can find the template.
So I'm going to copy that.
I don't need the last line because I'm not going to specify a command, so I'm just going to skip that
and I'll go back to my terminal and I'm going to create a pod definition file.
I'll call it Redis pod Ammo, and I paste the contents here and then I go in and edit the HTML file
contents.
Now all I need is to two specifications.
The name of the pod should be read is, and the image name should be read as one, two, three.
So I'm going to update the name to read this.
I'm not asked to create any labels, so I'm just going to delete that the container name could be read
is it doesn't really matter in this case as it has not been checked.
The image should be read is one, two, three.
So I'm going to update the image to read this.
One, two, three.
Okay.
So I'm now going to save that file and I will now create the pod using the cube control, Create command.
The pod release is created.
I'm going to check my work.
And it's good.
Now, the red is one, two, three was not a good image, as you might have noticed.
So the next task is to fix it.
So here what we're trying to do is given a pod.
Given an existing pod, how do you edit values in it?
So in the current pod, we have an incorrect image that's being used, so we're asked to fix it.
There are different ways to do it.
You can either update the file with the right image name and then use the control applied command,
or you could delete the pod and recreate it.
Or you could simply use the cube control edit pod command.
So we'll we'll do that.
Now we'll use the cube control, edit pod, read this command.
And what this does is it opens up a.
Evi ed instance with the file that has the definition.
Now, this is not the file that we created.
This is a file that was generated by Kubernetes in the background, and it gives you access.
It just gave you access to the port definition file used internally by Kubernetes.
And so you can see that there are a lot of additional fields in it, like the create timestamp, resource
version, etc..
So these are fields that were created automatically by Kubernetes internally.
Now, all we need to do is make the changes that we were asked to make in this case.
We'll just go over to the Readies image name and update the image name to remove the extra one, two,
three.
Okay.
And then you can just save the file as you normally would.
And so that basically has updated the pod with the radius image.
So when you now run the cube control, get pods command, you can see that the red is pod is in the
running state.
If you describe the pod to view the image, you will see that the image name is red.
So that's good.
So we're going to check the work now.
Okay, perfect.
So that's done.
So in this coding exercise, we've practiced viewing information about existing pods.
A little bit of troubleshooting, identifying why a pod is in a failed state, going through the events
and trying to figure out what could be the problem.
We also looked at editing an existing pod or creating a new pod given a set of specifications.