In this demo, we are going to create a replica sets based on the pod definition file that we created
earlier.
So in the last demo we created a pod using YAML.
So here what I've done is I've created a directory called Pods under the Kubernetes for Beginners Directory,
which is my project directory.
And here are the two files that we created earlier for pods.
So now let us create a new directory for replica sets called replica sets.
And inside this directory let's create a new file called replica set YAML.
So let's start with the API version.
And if you remember from the lecture, the version four replica set should be apps slash V one.
And next we'll use kind and we'll use the suggestions available.
And here we are going to make use of replica sets.
The next root element is the same as that of the board.
So we are going to add metadata and the name of the replica set, which would be my dash, my app dash
replica set, and we'll assign a label for our replica set as well.
So the key would be app and the value will be my app.
Now I'm going to set the last the last property, which is the spec.
And as you can see for replica set, the Visual Studio code extension, the ML extension is automatically.
Understood that the object is a public asset and that it needs a selector.
So it has already created the selector field for us.
So we'll just have to fill it in.
So here we are and we have two possible options.
It can be match expressions or match label.
So let's use the match label option.
And here we're going to use the same label that we used for the pot, which will tie the pot to the
replica set.
So let us use the same label that we used before while creating pots.
So for this, let me first open the the engine X bar definition file on the right side of the screen
so you can just right click and open it on the right side.
The labels we used there where the E and V label, which is set to production.
So I'm just going to copy that over.
Now the next property is replicas.
So for this example, let's make use of three replicas and then the next mandatory value that we need
to add here is the template.
So for template, we can make use of the part definition file that we created earlier and copy the template.
So I'm just going to copy this whole section here from metadata and paste it under the template section.
So now as soon as we paste the the contents, we see that the indentation is all out of order.
So in order to fix this, one easy way to do it is to select the, the whole section that we just pasted
except for the first line and then press tab twice and then or until it fixes the, the, the indentation.
Right.
Now some editors are intelligent enough to automatically correct that for you.
However, this this one doesn't.
But I know that there is an extension available for this.
And so if you're interested in that, check it out.
I think it's called paste and indent or something like that.
So for now, we will just stick to the manual way of fixing it.
So now the the format is corrected and there are no more errors in the file.
So one thing to note here is the labels used for the pod and the labels used under the selector at the
top.
So they have to be the same, right?
The label used at the top of the replica set itself doesn't really matter.
The it is the the two labels that are set on the pod and then the one set on the selector that matters.
That's what ties them together.
So they have to be the same.
So say we changed the labels on the pod template or something else like app and set it to my app.
Then we must change it at the top as well to use the same right?
So now we're done with the file.
Okay, so now that we have the replica set definition file ready, let's go back to the terminal.
And here in the project root directory we see that we have the new directory called replica sets, and
underneath that there is the replica set YAML definition file that we just created.
So let's quickly check to make sure that the file has the contents we created.
So I'm just going to use cat to view the contents of the file.
So it does everything as expected.
So now let me clear the screen and we're going to create this replica set using the cube to create command
with the dash F option.
So as soon as the replica set is created, let's check the status using QB model.
Get replica set command and we notice that there is one replica set which is created already.
The desired number of replicas is equal to three and the current and ready number of replicas are three
as well.
And it was created about 8 seconds ago.
So we can further inspect the status of the pods by running the cube, get pods command.
And we notice here that we have three replicas or three pods for the replica set we created and all
of the pods have a unique name, but you will notice that the name of the pod begins with the name of
the replica set, which is my app replica set.
So that way you can look at the pod, any pod and you can identify that if it is a standalone pod or
a pod, that is part of a replica set.
Now all of them are in the running state.
So we said that a replica set ensures that a sufficient number of replicas or pods are available at
all times.
Now, let's see what happens if we were to delete one of these pods.
So let's go back and copy one of the pod names.
So in this case, I'm copying this one here that has a name that ends with eight and x x L, So I'm
going to use the delete pod command and I'm going to paste the pod name here.
Now, whenever you delete a pod, it takes a few seconds for the pod to fully terminate, so just give
it a few seconds for the pod to fully terminate.
So once we get the prompt back, let's check the status of the pods again.
But you'll notice that the replica set still has three pods running.
And you'll notice that one of the pod was just created.
15 seconds ago.
And you'll notice that the name of the older pod that that ended with the eight and ZL has been deleted.
And a new pod with the name with a different name has been created.
So that's the replica set, ensuring that sufficient number of pods are always available on the cluster.
Now if you run the cube candle, describe replica set command for the new replica set.
We will see that the desired number of replicas in history.
And here we see more information about the replica set.
Just like what we saw with the cube cattle describe pod command.
So here we see the name of the replica set, the selectors, the label for the replica set itself.
If you scroll down, you'll see the labels that the selector about makes use of, which is the labels
on the pod.
And we also see the engine x container definition.
And if you scroll down below, we see the events.
So initially when we created the replica set, it actually came up with three replicas, but then we
deleted one of the replicas and then it spun up one additional replica for it to maintain that desired
number.
And you see all of that in the history of events here.
So this is a handy tool and command.
If you'd like to inspect what happened to a replica set in case you're troubleshooting something or
you're just looking for more information on what's happening with the replica set, etc..
So so we said that a replica set ensures that a minimum number of replicas are available all the time.
But what if there are more number of replicas than what's required?
So let's try to let's try something else.
Let's try to create a new pod by making use of the the same label that the replica set select our users,
which is the app set to my app.
And to do this, let's go back to our pod definition file.
And so here I have the index.html file that we created and we'll notice that we have a pod template
which tries to create a pod by the name and next to.
But we also but we have now changed its label to the same label as the pod definition template used
in our replica set.
So now let's create the pod directly and not through the replica set, but just directly the pod like
as we have done before.
And we'll see what happens when we create a new pod outside of the replica set, but one that has the
same labels that the replica set select our users.
So before doing that, let me run the cube cuddle, get pods command and I see that there is only the
three parts that were created by the replica set.
And so now I'm going to use the cube cutter to create command and with the dash F option and I'll specify
the index.html file and you will see that the engine x-2 pod has been created.
But if I run the cube cattle get pods command now and we'll see that the status of that pod is in a
terminating state.
Already the replica set is terminating the new pod that we just created.
It's not allowing more pods with the same labels than the number of replicas configured on the replica
set.
So if we run the cube cattle describe command now we'll see that at the bottom under the events section
of the output of described command, the replica set controller deletes the new engine x-2 pod that
we just created.
So now if I go back and run the cube, we'll get pod command.
I see that it is under terminating state and soon it should go away from it from the list altogether.
Okay, so now let's see how to update a replica set.
So what?
What if we want to change the number of replicas to say, four instead of the current three?
Say, for instance, we are trying to scale up our application.
So for this we must edit the replica set definition file and update its replicas.
Count to four.
For this we will make use of a new command called cube edit replica set and we will provide the name
of the replica set which is my apt replica set.
And now when we run this command, we see that it opens up the running configuration of the replica
set in a text editor in a text format.
In this case, it opens up in vim.
So note that this is not the actual file that we used that we created at the beginning of this demo.
This is a temporary file that that's created by Kubernetes in memory to allow us to edit the configuration
of an existing object on Kubernetes.
And that's why you'll see a lot of additional fields in this file other than the details that you provided.
So changes made to this file are directly applied on the running configuration on the cluster as soon
as the file is saved.
So you must be very careful with the changes that you are making here.
So now if I scroll down all the way to the spec section, which is over here and we can see the running
configuration and the current number of replicas, which is set to three, I can change this to scale
it up by another part.
So four in this case.
And then I will save and exit from the editor.
Now it should now spin up a new pod in addition to the three that we already had to match the new number
of replicas that we specified.
So if you run the cube, get Pod's command.
Now we see that there is a new pod which was spun up 6 seconds ago, and we can use the same approach
to scale down as well.
And there's also a command available to scale the number of replicas without having to go in and edit
the definition file, and that is using the cube scale replica set command.
So we will provide the name of the replica set and we will set the number of replicas for it to scale
to two.
So you could specify a number which is greater or less than the current number of replicas.
And note taking note of the double dashes before the replicas option.
So if I run the cube code, we'll get Pod's command again.
We will see that the replica set is now scaling down to two replicas by terminating two of the pods.
Well.
So let's wait for these two replicas to be terminated.
And there you go.
And now we just have two parts.
Well, that's it for this demo.
I will see you in the next.