Hello and welcome to this demo.
We are going through the Kubernetes certification course, and in this demo we will look at the solution
for the practice test on replica sets.
Now, this is a beginner's level test, so we will see how to solve the challenges.
So first, go to the link for taking the practice test.
When you're ready, click on start scenario and this is the terminal where you'll be working and click
on Quiz Portal to open up the portal.
So you have about an hour to go through about 15 questions.
Now, these are all very simple questions.
So to start with, we will go through some of the information gathering questions like read the environment,
understand, inspect the environment and understand the number of pods, replica sets that are available.
Look at the existing replica sets and try and figure out information from that.
Troubleshoot issues with replica sets and try and fix them as well as creating your own replica sets.
So let's get started.
So the first question is how many pods exist on the system?
And all operations are done in the current or the default namespace, so you don't have to change the
namespace.
So let's go back to the console and we'll try to figure out how many parts exist.
So I'm going to run Kube control, get parts command so there are no resources found.
So the answer is zero.
The next question is how many replica sets exist on the system?
So I'm going to run the cube control, get replica sets, command and so there are no resources found.
So there is the answer is zero.
Okay, So some changes were made.
So how about now?
How many replica sets do you see?
So let's go back and run the command again.
And we see that there is one replica set created.
So let's select one.
How many parts are desired in the new replica set.
So if you go back and look at the output of the command that we just ran, the desired column says four.
So that means that there are four parts desired for this replica set.
So the answer is four.
What is the image used to create the pods in the new replica set?
So there are a number of options given and we need to find out what the image is on the replica set
or on the parts.
So for this we can run the command cube control.
Describe replica set.
And it prints out the detailed information regarding the replica set.
If you look under containers, under the template, under containers, the busy box container, there's
only one container in each pod.
And the image used is busy box seven, seven, seven.
So that's.
That's the answer.
It's busy.
Box seven, seven, seven.
How many parts are ready in the new replica set?
So again, if you go back and look at the output of the command we ran earlier.
The ready column says zero.
So that's the answer.
None of the parts are ready.
So we could also run it again.
We could also run the command again just to see if it's updated.
Nope.
So the answer is still zero.
So let's go back and select zero.
So why do you think that the parts are not ready?
So let's go back and see.
Let's try and troubleshoot and see why it's not ready.
So if you go back and look into the output of the cube control, describe replica set command.
You can see that four parts or four replicas are desired and all four are in a waiting state.
None of them are succeeded or none of them are running.
If you look under the events here, you see that all four parts were created.
You do not see anything further.
So let's dig in and look at the state of the parts.
So I'm going to run the first.
Let me clear the screen.
I'm going to run the cube control, get Parts command.
And I see that there are four parts and they all have the name of the replica set as a prefix and the
status is image.
Pull back off.
Now, if you're not sure what that means, we can actually dig in further and look inside one of the
pod.
So, cube control, describe pod, and then I'm going to type in
the name of one of the pods.
New replica set six two and B two.
And now, if you look under the events, you see that you see this, the different events.
So it's trying to pull the image visible.
X seven, seven, seven failed to pull the image busy box seven, seven, seven.
And the error, the actual error towards the end is repository busy box 777 not found does not exist
or no pull access.
So that tells us that the repository, the image box 777 does not exist on Docker and that's the reason
why it's not able to pull the image.
That's the reason why the pods are not running.
So it's not the first one.
The second one that says the image box seven, seven, seven doesn't exist.
So that's the correct answer to this question.
Okay, next, delete any one of the four parts.
So let's go back to the terminal and.
Let's first cleared the screen.
We'll say cube control, get Parts Command, and we will run the cube control delete pod, and then
we'll use one of the pod names.
So we're going to try and delete the first pod.
We'll wait for the prompt to come back so the part is deleted.
Click done.
How many parts exist now?
So let's go back and run the Get Pods command again to see how many pods exist.
So we can see that there are still four pods.
One, two, three and four.
And earlier two.
There were four pods even though we deleted.
There are still four pods.
So the answer is four.
So why are there still four parts even after you deleted one?
So the answer is not because I didn't delete it properly, I did delete it and it did say that the part
is deleted.
You cannot delete a part from a replica set.
That's not true either because we were able to delete the part from the replica set.
The third one that says replica set ensures that desired number of parts always and exist.
So that's the right answer.
So the purpose of your replica set is to ensure that a given number of parts always exist.
So even if you manually delete any of these parts or if any of the parts were to get deleted or, you
know, due to a program being terminated or an error inside the image or the application and if the
part were to get deleted automatically.
Replica set will fire up a new part to ensure that the desired number of parts always exist.
So that's the right answer.
Now getting into a little bit of yaml file replica set configuration and troubleshooting create a replica
set using the replica set definition.
One yaml file located at root.
So let's look at so the current directory is root.
So let's list the files here.
So this is the file that the question is referring to.
Replica set definition dash one yaml.
So the task is to create the replica set using this definition file.
So we can take a look at the file real quick.
Replica set definition one point yaml.
And that's the.
That's the definition.
So let's just try try to let's first try to create the replica set.
Create minus F.
Public Asset Definition one point M0.
So that has failed.
It says unable to recognize replica set definition yaml file no matches for kind replica set in version
one.
Now the purpose of this exercise or these kinds of troubleshooting exercises is to make you comfortable
working with YAML files and definition files.
You will very often come across such errors in real life while working with Kubernetes.
Or if you're actually giving the binary certification exam, you'll come across a lot of such errors
and you need to know what these error messages mean.
You you must be able to look into the error messages, read them, understand them, and know exactly
what that means and how to fix it.
And that's the whole purpose of these kinds of exercises.
So if you look at the error message in this case, it says no matches for kind replica set in version
V one.
So it's actually talking about the first two lines in our replica set definition file.
This particular version which we one has no match for replica set.
So it's either a problem with this or a problem with this.
Sometimes when you give the case of this kind incorrectly, you will come across the same error message.
So you need to know.
You need to know what that is.
Now you don't have to memorize what what is here and what is here.
You can always refer to the documentation site in such cases.
So go to the Kubernetes documentation site at Kubernetes, dot slash docs and search for replica set.
So in the search bar.
And from the result, I usually go with the first.
Outcome.
And if you just scroll down here, you should be able to see a sample definition file.
What we are concerned about is the first two lines.
As you can see, it's not v one, it's APS v one and replica set is correct.
So this is the issue.
So let's go and change that.
So I'm going to update the hazard definition file.
And right here, I'm going to add the apps.
I will save the file and I will create it again.
So that's successful and the file is created.
Let's go back and check our work.
So that's successful.
The next task is to fix the issue in the replica set definition to YAML file and create a replica set
using that.
So let's try that right now.
I will directly try to create the replica set using the definition file.
That's cube control.
Create minus f replica set definition to yaml.
So this is failed again and it says this time that invalid value selector does not match template labels.
So let's take a look at the file.
I got set definition to YAML.
And if you look in here you see that?
So the error message is selector does not match template labels.
So the selector is this selector that is talking about.
So this has a selector with match labels of tier front front end and it is trying to match this with
the labels defined here.
And so the issue here is that this label to your front end does not match this label, which is tier,
tier and index.
So when the replica set is created, Kubernetes first tries to create a template, a pod, or the record
number of pods using this particular template.
And so everything under here is a pod definition.
Everything under template is a pod definition, and it tries to create that, and then it tries to create
a replica set and link the replica set with these pods.
And in order to do that, these two must match.
And that's why it's important that these two are the same.
Otherwise the replica set will not have any pods under it.
So this is what links the replica set and the parts to each other and they should always match.
And that's the check that is being performed here before even Kubernetes tries to create these objects.
So in this case, we either need to use front end in both in both places or use engine in both the places.
So it doesn't really matter what you use.
You just need to fix the error and get the replica set created.
So in this case, I'm just going to update the label here to match whatever is given up.
Okay.
I will now try to create the replica set again and it's successful.
I will go back and check.
Okay.
Now, while we are there, I just wanted to give a quick tip, especially for the certification.
So if you are attempting the certification, your work is not validated like.
Like this.
So in that case, you need to make sure that whatever you've done is working and is correct.
So, for example, if you are asked to create a replica set named replica set two with this particular
labels and this particular image for the pod, you need to do a quick check of your work to ensure that
you've done it correctly.
Even if you're successful in creating the replica set.
You must ensure that you used the right information.
So I believe exam evaluation is automated.
I don't know how, but it could be or it should be automated.
So if that is the case, then these whatever tasks you're asked to do may be checked automatically and
so it will have to match.
Exactly.
So if you're asked to use an X image, you have to use engine X image, and for that it's best you do
a quick check of your work after you do something.
So in this case, it's best you check your replica set by running a cube control, get RS command and
make sure that it's named as replica set dash two and also do a quick check like this.
Cube control describe RS.
It's a short for replica set and that'll come handy in the exam, especially when your time constraint.
And it's good to make sure that the image that was asked to use the labels that are asked use are the
same.
So that's a quick tip.
So the next task is to delete the two newly created replica sets so you could do a cube control delete.
And I'm going to use the short form for replica set going forward.
RS And then the replica set one replica set to.
Okay, so they are deleted.
Click on check That is successful.
Now the next task is to fix the original replica set new dash replica that's set to use the correct
busy box image.
So remember earlier we identified that the parts were not starting due to the image which was wrong,
which was busy bug seven, seven seven.
So it has to be updated to busy box.
Busy box.
So let's go and try to do that.
Now, whenever you're asked to update an existing object, you know, the first thing that comes to
your mind is probably to use the cube control edit replica, set command and then specify the name of
the replica set, which is new replica set.
And when you do this for most of the objects in Kubernetes, it opens up a definition file for that
object in a bi editor, and you can make changes to that object from here.
So in this case, I'm just going to make a change to the image name.
It's busy Box seven, seven, seven.
I'm going to get rid of the seven, seven, seven from here and then save the file.
So it says the replica set is now edited.
Now let us see the state of the replica set.
Keep control, get set.
And as you can see, it's still in the same state.
There are still only there are still no parts that are ready.
If you look at the state of the parts, you see that they're still in that error state.
And if you further look at the one of the parts in detail, let's say the first one.
You see that it's still in the image pull back off state and it's still using the old image, which
was busy box seven, seven, seven, but we actually updated the image name.
Now the reason for that is the replica set.
Even if you edit an existing replica set, it does not carry forward those changes to the existing part.
Only when a part is deleted and a new part is created, the changes are applied so it does not automatically
apply the changes in the containers for the existing parts.
So we have two options.
We can either delete each part one by one and then have replicas that automatically create new parts.
Or we could delete the replica set itself and create a new replica set.
So let's try the first option.
Get us.
So we get pods.
And as you can see, let's try and delete one.
Delete pod.
The first one.
We'll wait for that to get.
Let's delete it.
But I now run the Get Pod's command.
It's created a new pod and it's actually running.
So that's that's one of my options.
So I can also go ahead and delete all the others.
Let's now just look at the other method as well.
Just so you're aware.
So the other method is to delete the replica set.
But before deleting, remember if I delete this because it right now I do not have the definition file
for it.
So it was already there.
It was automatically created when I came into this environment.
So I do not have a definition file for this existing replica set.
So if I delete it, I may not be able to recreate it.
Now, any time you're in that scenario where you do not have the definition file for any objects in
Kubernetes and you want to capture it or create it, instead of looking at the properties and creating
a definition, file yourself from scratch.
You could simply export the definition file out of Kubernetes.
So if you run a cube control, get replica set command with the name of the replica set.
OC.
It lists the replica set information.
What I'm going to do is you could use the dash zero option along with the YAML option to get the definition
of the replica set in a YAML format, and that's what we can use to edit or to save the configuration.
So when I run that command with the when I run the Q control, get our command with the dash YAML option,
I get the definition file for the replica set.
Now this was not created by me.
It was never there.
So this was automatically generated by Kubernetes for me.
Now, there is a lot of information in this which we can delete.
For example, the creation timestamp, these IDs and links, etc. So or we can just leave it there too.
It doesn't really matter.
So I'm going to.
Save that those contents into my own definition file.
I will name that new replica set dot yaml.
Okay.
Now I can safely delete my replica set.
So I'm going to do a get cube control.
Delete this new replica set.
Okay, let's delete it.
I can now create the new replica set.
Burning the cube control create minus F new replica set.
Don't yaml file.
K the new asset is created.
One Get RS.
It's creating the new replica set.
There are two parts ready.
There are three ready.
There are four ready
there on the get pods command.
I can see that there are four ports ready.
There's still one pod that's left off of the previous replica set, but it should be gone any time that's
gone.
Okay, perfect.
So.
Let me check the work.
Okay.
Successful.
The next task is to scale the replica set to five parts.
For this we can use the cube control scale command, or we can edit the existing replica set using the
cube control Edit command.
So in this case we will use the scale command cube control scale replica set new dash replica dash set
dash dash replicas equals five.
Okay.
It's it's it's scaled.
When I run the get rrs command, I see that the desired number is five.
I run it again.
I see that there are five that are ready.
So if you look at the part, you will see that there's another another additional part that was just
created.
Okay.
The same way you can scale the replica set down as well to two parts.
So I'm going to run the same command to scale it down to two.
Check the number of parts.
As you can see, there are three terminating.
And.
There are two the desert and current and ready count is now to take the work.
Okay, So that's the end of it.