Hello and welcome to this lecture.
In this lecture, we will discuss about Kubernetes deployments.
For a minute.
Let us forget about pods and replica sets and other Kubernetes concepts and talk about how you might
want to deploy your application in a production environment.
Say, for example, you have a web server that needs to be deployed in a production environment.
You need not one, but many such instances of the web server running for obvious reasons.
Secondly, whenever newer versions of application builds become available on the Docker registry, you
would like to upgrade your Docker instances seamlessly.
However, when you upgrade your instances, you do not want to upgrade all of them at once, as we just
did.
This may impact users accessing our applications, so you might want to upgrade them one after the other.
And that kind of upgrade is known as rolling updates.
Suppose one of the upgrades you performed resulted in an unexpected error and you're asked to undo the
recent change.
You would like to be able to roll back the changes that were recently carried out.
Finally say, for example, you would like to make multiple changes to your environment, such as upgrading
the underlying web server versions as well as scaling your environment and also modifying the resource
allocations, etc. You do not want to apply each change immediately after the command is run.
Instead, you would like to apply a pass to your environment, make the changes and then resume so that
all the changes are rolled out together.
All of these capabilities are available with the Kubernetes deployments so far in this course, we discussed
about pods which deploy single instances of our application, such as the web application.
In this case, each container is encapsulated in parts Multiple such paths are deployed using replication
controllers or replica sets.
And then comes deployment, which is a Kubernetes object that comes higher in the hierarchy.
The deployment provides us with the capability to upgrade the underlying instances, seamlessly using
rolling updates, undo changes, and pause and resume changes as required.
So how do we create a deployment?
As with the previous components, we first create a deployment definition, file.
The contents of the deployment definition file are exactly similar to the replica set definition file,
except for the kind which is now going to be deployment.
If we walk through the contents of the file, it has an API version which is APS forward slash v one
metadata, which has name and labels and a spec that has template replicas and selector.
The template has a pod definition inside it.
Once the file is ready, run the cube control, create command and specify the deployment definition
file.
Then run the cube control, get deployments command to see the newly created deployment.
The deployment automatically creates a replica set, so if you run the cube control, get replica set
command, you will be able to see a new replica set in the name of the deployment.
The replica sets ultimately create paths, so if you run the cube control, get pause command, you
will be able to see the parts with the name of the deployment and the replica set.
So far, there hasn't been much of a difference between replica set and deployments, except for the
fact that deployment created a new Kubernetes object called deployments.
We will see how to take advantage of the deployment using the use cases we discussed in the previous
slide in the upcoming lectures.
And one more note before we end this lecture to see all the created objects at once.
Run the cube control, get all command.
And in this case, we can see that the deployment was created.
And then we have the replica set, followed by three parts that were created as part of the deployment.
That's it for this lecture.
We will now head over to a demo and I will see you in the next lecture.