In this demo, we're going to create a deployment.
So let us create a new folder called Deployments within our project directory and within the deployment
directory, I'm going to create a new file called called Deployment YAML.
And we're going to make use of the definition file that we created earlier for the replica sets because
it's quite similar to that of the deployment.
And to make this easier, we're just going to open the replica set definition file on the right.
So I'm going to use the split editor function here.
So on the left we have the deployment YAML file that we're going to create now, and on the right we
have the replica set YAML file that we created earlier.
So as before, we will start off with the API version.
And it is and it is also going to be API v one the same as replica set.
And I'm going to use the kind as deployment.
So let me select that from here.
And then the metadata, I'm going to enter it here as well, and that will have the name and labels.
And we're going to use the name as my app dash deployment.
And I will add a couple of labels as well.
The labels will be a front end to your front end and maybe another one called Engine X.
Now the spec section is very similar to that of the replica sets, so I'm just going to copy this entire
section here for the specs for the specs section and I'm just going to paste it here.
So that should be good enough for us to start the deployment.
And I'm going to change just I'm just going to reduce the number of replicas to three.
So let's go back to our terminal and if we check the root of our product directory, we see the new
directory that we created called deployments.
And I'm going to create this deployment using the create command along with the dash F deployment YAML
file.
And as you can see, the deployment has been created.
So let's run the cube.
Get deployments, Command.
And I can see that we have one deployment which is created and it has three out of three ready pods
and available are three as well.
So if you want to check the pod, we can run.
The cube cutter will get Pods command and I can see that we have three pods which are in the running
state which were created a few moments ago.
Now let us run a cuddle.
Describe deployment command and the name of the deployment is my app Dash deployment.
And here we can see a lot of similar information.
So the name of the pod, the label of the deployment itself and the the front end label that we set.
And we see the selector that we use the same as that of the replica set, which is equal to my app.
And it has three desired and three available pods and which are in a running state.
And here's the pod section.
The label of the pod is my app.
And here's the container details with the image set to engine X.
If you scroll to the bottom, you'll see that it also has an event section and it just shows the deployment
controller and message, which is that the replica set for this deployment has been scaled to three.
And now before we move on, let's run the get all command, which shows all the objects which is created
in the cluster.
So you can see that we have one deployment, which is the deployment that we created, and there is
a replica set which is created for that specific deployment called my app Dash replica set.
And then we have the three pods which have been created using that replica set.
Well, that's it for now.
Head over to the labs and try this out for yourselves.