We will now look at Docker Registry.
So what is a registry?
If the containers were the rain, then they would rain from the Docker registry, which are the clouds.
That's where Docker images are stored.
It's the central repository of all Docker images.
Let's look at a simple engine x container.
We run the Docker run engine X command to run an instance of the engine X image.
Let's take a closer look at that image name.
Now, the name is Engine X, but what is this image and where is this image pulled from?
This name follows Dockers image naming convention and Gen X.
Here is the image or the repository name.
When you say engine X, it's actually engine x slash engine x.
The first part stands for the user or account name.
So if you don't provide an account or a repository name, it assumes that it is the same as the given
name, which in this case is engine X.
The user names is usually your Docker hub account name.
Or if it is an organization, then it's the name of the organization.
If you were to create your own account and create your own repositories or images under it, then you
would use a similar pattern.
Now where are these images stored and pulled from?
Since we have not specified the location where these images are to be pulled from, it is assumed to
be on Dockers default Registry Docker Hub, the DNS name for which is Docker Dot IO.
The registry is where all the images are stored.
Whenever you create a new image or update an existing image, you push it to the registry.
And every time anyone deploys this application, it is pulled from that registry.
There are many other popular registries as well.
For example, Google's registry is at GCR Dot IO, where a lot of Kubernetes related images are stored
like the ones used for performing end to end tests on the cluster.
These are all publicly accessible images that anyone can download and access.
When you have applications built in-house that shouldn't be made available to the public, hosting an
internal private registry may be a good solution.
Many cloud service providers such as US Azure or GCP, provide a private registry by default when you
open an account with them.
On any of these solutions, be it Docker Hub or Google Registry or your internal private registry,
you may choose to make a repository private so that it can only be accessed using a set of credentials.
From Dockers perspective to run a container using an image from a private registry, you first log in
to your private registry using the Docker Login command input your credentials Once successful, run
the application using private registry as part of the image name like this.
Now, if you did not log in to the private registry, it will come back saying that the image cannot
be found.
So remember to always log in before pulling or pushing to a private registry.
We said that cloud providers like AWS or GCP provide a private registry when you create an account with
them.
But what if you are running your application on premise and don't have a private registry?
How do you deploy your own private registry within your organization?
The doctor registry is itself another application and of course is available as a docker image.
The name of the image is Registry and it exposes the API on Port 5000.
Now that you have your custom registry running at Port 5000 on this Docker host, how do you push your
own image to it?
Use the Docker image tag command to tag the image with a private registry URL in it.
In this case, since it's running on the same docker host, I can use local host semicolon 5000 followed
by the image name.
I can then push my image to my local private registry using the Command Docker push and the new image
name with the Docker registry information in it.
From there on, I can pull my image from anywhere within this network using either local host If you're
on the same host or the IP or domain name of my Docker host if I'm accessing from another host in my
environment.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
Head over to the practice test and practice working with private Docker registries.