We will now look at some of the other Docker run commands.
At the end of this lecture, you will go through a hands on quiz where you will practice working with
these commands.
We learned that we could use the Docker run Redis command to run a container running a ready service.
In this case, the latest version of Redis, which happens to be 5.0.5 as of today.
But what if we want to run another version of readers, like, for example, an older version, say,
4.0?
Then you specify the version separated by a colon.
This is called a tag.
In that case, Docker pulls an image of the 4.0 version of Redis and runs that.
Also notice that if you don't specify any tag, as in the first command, Docker will consider the default
tag to be latest.
Latest is a tag associated to the latest version of that software, which is governed by the authors
of that software.
So as a user, how do you find information about these versions and what is the latest?
At Docker Hub dot com.
Look up an image and you will find all the supported tags in its description.
Each version of the software can have multiple short and long tags associated with it as seen here.
In this case, the version 5.0.5 also has the latest tag on it.
Let's now look at inputs.
I have a simple prompt application that when run asks for my name.
And on entering my name Prince, a welcome message.
If I were to dockery's this application and run it as a Docker container like this, it wouldn't wait
for the prompt.
It just prints whatever the application is supposed to print on standard out.
That is because by default the Docker container does not listen to a standard input, even though you're
attached to its console.
It is not able to read any input from you.
It doesn't have a terminal to read inputs from.
It runs in a non-interactive mode.
If you'd like to provide your input, you must map the standard input of your host to the Docker container
using the dash parameter.
The dash parameter is for interactive mode and when I input my name, it prints the expected output.
But there is something still missing from this.
The prompt.
When we run the app.
At first it asks us for our name.
But when Dark arised, that prompt is missing, even though it seems to have accepted my input.
That is because the application prompt on the terminal and we have not attached to the containers terminal.
For this use the dash TX option as well.
The Dash TX stands for a pseudo terminal.
So with the combination of AI and RT, we're now attached to the terminal as well as in an interactive
mode on the container.
We will now look at port mapping or port publishing on containers.
Let's go back to the example where we run a simple web application in a Docker container on my Docker
host.
Remember the underlying host where Docker is installed is called Docker Host or Docker Engine.
When we run a containerized web application, it runs and we are able to see that the server is running.
But how does a user access my application?
As you can see, my application is listening on Port 5000.
So I could access my application by using port 5000.
But what IP do I use to access it from a web browser?
There are two options available.
One is to use the IP of the Docker container.
Every Docker container gets an IP assigned by default.
In this case it is one 72.17 0.2.
But remember that this is an internal IP and is only accessible within the Docker host.
So if you open a browser from within the Docker host, you can go to HTTP colon forward slash forward
slash one 72.17 .0.1 colon 5000 to access the IP address.
But since this is an internal IP, users outside of the Docker host cannot access it using this IP.
For this we could use the IP of the Docker host, which is one 92.1.
68 .1.5.
But for that to work, you must have mapped the port inside the Docker container to a free port on the
Docker host.
For example, if I want the users to access my application through Port 80 on my Docker host, I could
map port 80 of local host to port 5000 on the Docker container using the dash p parameter in my run
command like this.
And so the user can access my application by going to the URL HTTP colon slash slash one 92.1 60 8.1.5.
Colon 80.
And all traffic on port 80 on my dock or host will get routed to port 5000 inside the Docker container.
This way you can run multiple instances of your application and map them to different ports on the dock
or host.
Or on instances of different applications on different ports.
For example, in this case I'm running an instance of MySQL that runs a database on my host and listens
on the default MySQL port, which happens to be 3306 or another instance of my SQL on another port.
8306.
So you can run as many applications like this and map them to as many ports as you want.
And of course you cannot map to the same port on the Docker host more than once.
We will discuss more about port mapping and networking of containers in the network lecture later on.
Let's now look at how data is persisted in a Docker container.
For example, let's say you were to run a MySQL container.
When databases and tables are created, the data files are stored in location for lib MySQL inside the
Docker container.
Remember, the Docker container has its own isolated file system and any changes to any files happen
within the container.
Let's assume you dump a lot of data into the database.
What happens if you were to delete the MySQL container and remove it?
As soon as you do that, the container, along with all the data inside, it gets blown away, meaning
all your data is gone.
If you would like to persist data, you would want to map a directory outside the container on the dock
or host to a directory inside the container.
In this case, I create a directory called slash opt slash data dir and map that to var lib my SQL inside
the docker container using the dash v option and specifying the directory on the Docker host followed
by a colon and the directory inside the Docker container.
This way, when Docker container runs, it will implicitly mount the external directory to a folder
inside the Docker container.
This way all your data will now be stored in the external volume at slash slash data directory and thus
will remain even if you delete the Docker container.
The Docker command is good enough to get basic details about containers like their names and IDs.
But if you would like to see additional details about a specific container, use the Docker, inspect
command and provide the container name or ID.
It returns all details of a container in a JSON format, such as the state mounts, configuration data,
network settings, etc..
Remember to use it when you are required to find details on a container.
And finally, how do we see the logs of a container we ran in the background?
For example, I ran my simple web application using the dash D parameter and it ran the container in
a detached mode.
How do I view the logs, which happens to be the contents written to the standard out of that container?
Use the Docker logs command and specify the container ID or name like this.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
Head over to the challenges and practice working with doctor commands.