Hello and welcome to this demo.
In this demo, we're going to look at some of the advanced options with Docker commands, some of the
advanced options available with the with running Docker containers using the Docker run command.
So in the previous demos, we saw how to install Docker and how to set it up and how to run some images.
And we saw some of the basic commands, such as the commands to run a Docker container to look at the
list of running and dead Docker containers to execute a command inside a Docker container, etc. In
this case, in this demo, we're going to look a little bit more about running Docker containers, but
some advanced options available for us.
So I'm just going to run the Docker command, just check if there are any existing running containers
and I see there are no containers running.
And earlier we saw that we could run an Ubuntu or container based off of an Ubuntu or a center where
by running the Docker run Ubuntu command.
So I'm just going to run docker on Ubuntu and I'm going to append a command next to this docker run
just so it runs the when it runs or starts up the ubuntu container and before it exits it can run this
particular command and give me the output.
So what I want to do is I want to see the version of Ubuntu running.
So we, we downloaded our docker downloaded and image of ubuntu automatically, but I don't know what
version of ubuntu it is running.
So I'm just going to run this.
Append this particular command to the end of the run command.
So get this is for slash star release star.
And so it ran the Docker container, ran this particular command and gave me this output.
And as you can see, the version is 16.04.
But what if I want to run another version of this particular operating system?
So the first thing that I need to do is go to the Docker hub site, identify the repository I'm using.
And if you look inside this particular repository, in this case Ubuntu, you will see a list of supported
tags.
So that's the first thing in the description.
So support tags and respective Docker files.
So these are the tags that it supports.
For example, 16.04 is actually the, the default and the latest.
As we know, if you don't specify any tag, it's going to assume that it's going to assume a latest
tag.
So since we didn't specify any tag when we ran the Docker Ubuntu command right here, it actually assumed
to be the latest tag, which is why it downloaded the 16.4 image.
And what if I want to run another version?
Let's say 17.10.
If I want to run this particular version, what I could do is just append this tag to the the name of
the image.
So I'm going to run the same command as before, which is Docker run Ubuntu.
And I'm also going to print out the version of the OS using the CAT command.
And right here I could append a tag.
So the tag is to be appended following a colon.
And if you look at this list here, it could either be 17.10, it could be artful dash and then this
particular number here, or it could be artful or it could be devil, it could be any of these.
So these are all supported tags for the same version, which is 17.10.
So I'm going to just give 70.10 for now, and it's first going to find out if that image is available
locally.
It's definitely not.
So it's going to go out to Docker Hub and find out the image.
So it's going to download the image from Docker Hub.
And so it's downloaded the image and run it.
And when it ran, it ran the cat command to print out the version of Ubuntu.
And as you can see, the version of Ubuntu is 17.10.
So it's downloaded the right version because we provided a different tag.
So that's that's about tags.
This way you can tag your images differently for different purposes.
You can tag you can use tags for versioning, etc..
The next thing that we're going to do is we're going to see a test and detach modes.
So as we did before, I'm going to run a Docker container with Ubuntu and what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to keep it alive by using the sleep command.
So I'm just going to run the sleep command and keep it alive for, let's say 1100 seconds.
Now I'm just going to change that to 15.
Now, when I run this, what I expect is for Docker to run a container based off of Ubuntu and run this
particular application.
In my case, this the application is just a sleep command, so it's going to run the sleep command for
15 seconds.
And it's going to exit the container.
Now, if I hit enter, I can actually see that I'm I'm kind of stuck in that console.
I don't see anything.
If I do a control C, it doesn't actually take me out.
I'm kind of stuck and I'm not I cannot come out of this particular this particular console until the
O's or the container automatically exits, which it's done now.
So it waited for 15 seconds and it kind of exited.
Now, if I were to run an actual application instead of the test sleep command that I run here, such
as running a web server which is supposed to stay alive permanently, then I wouldn't be able to come
out of this and the console would just show me the output of that application I'm running.
Now, this is the default way how a container runs.
It doesn't really matter.
You could always use another session or terminal to your Docker host.
For example, I'm going to run the same command, but in this case I'm going to add two zeros to keep
it alive for 1500 seconds.
Now, in this case, as you can see, if I hit control C, whatever I try to do, it doesn't actually
come out of that.
It's because the Docker container is running in the foreground.
And what I could always do is I could establish another duplicate connection to my Docker host and once
I'm logged in, I run the Docker command to see the running images and then I can actually stop that
if I want to by using the Docker stop and specifying the container ID.
So this stops my container and if I go back, it takes a couple of seconds to stop and as soon as it
stops the container, I should be back to my console right here.
So as you can see, when I stopped the container from here, I'm actually back to my prompt right here.
It isn't actually anything to anything of a serious concern, but the next time you run the Docker container,
if you'd like to run it in the background or in a detached mode, you could actually specify the dash
D parameter.
So the dash d parameter is used to run it in the test mode in the background when when it starts.
So as you can see, it's listed the this is the actual container ID, the unique container ID, And
so this means that it's actually successful in running.
Now if you run the Docker command here, you can actually see the information about the container.
So if you look at this right now, this is the container ID, unique container I.D. it's actually this
big, but when you see it here, it just takes the first few characters and displays that here.
So it's running the Docker in the detached mode now and.
I'd like to attach back to it.
So I'm going to do a four and four that you could actually do a docker attach and then specify the container
ID.
And this will get you back to the doctor.
This will bring doctor process container and run it in the foreground.
Now I'm back to the same situation again because it's currently am actually attached to the Docker container
and nothing actually works.
So I'm going to go back to the other host and I'm going to stop I'm sorry, I'm going to go back to
the other terminal on the same host and I'm going to stop the Docker container.
Okay, so I'm back to my prompt here.
Okay, So I'd like to show the same example with another Docker image.
For example, I have another Docker image called Timer, which simply prints the time, the current
time into onto the screen every second.
So I'm going to run that image.
And as you can see, it prints the time on the screen every second.
Now, this runs infinitely.
So this Docker container never stops.
It just keeps printing the time onto the screen infinitely.
Now, since I'm running it without any additional parameters, it runs in the foreground or in the attached
mode.
If you'd like to run it in the background.
Run with the RD parameter.
And if you go back, run the Docker command, you'll see that it's running, but you cannot actually
see the output.
So if you run the Docker attach command.
And provide the container ID.
And you're back to the console of the Docker container and you can see the output being displayed.
So let's explore some additional Docker images from Docker Hub.
So something that I'm interested in is Jenkins.
So Jenkins is, as you might know, already is a build system.
And so let's say if you wanted to try a new application like this.
In fact, this is my favorite way of trying out any application.
So Jenkins is a continuous integration and delivery server.
And if I haven't worked with it before and if I just want to play around with it, get some hands on
experience on it, instead of going through the installation instructions and installing a lot of dependencies
on my underlying host, what I would like to do is simply run Jenkins as a container and just play around
with it that way.
So if you look at the site here, you can see instructions on running.
Jenkins.
So the repository name is just Jenkins and that that should get you started.
So the ideal way.
So what we have seen until now is simply running containers like this called Jenkins and it should go
out, pull up the Jenkins images and layers and run an instance of Jenkins.
Now, as you know, Jenkins is a web server.
So what we are expecting is once we deploy this particular container, we're actually expecting to go
to a website, to a browser and browse to this Jenkins server and access the web UI.
So let me just go back.
We'll wait for it to pull down the image.
Okay, so it's just finished pulling the image.
And as you can see, it's extracted and Jenkins is actually running.
So it started Jenkins and is actually running.
Okay.
So all I did was run a Docker, run Jenkins command, and it just pulled down the Jenkins latest version
of Jenkins and run it.
Now how do I access it?
So if I go to the if I go to my the UI of my host, so this is my Docker host and I actually this is
the same host where I have a terminal here and this is just the UI UI of that host.
Now what I'm going to do is if I run the Docker piece command here, I'll be able to see that its Jenkins
is running and it's on port 80, 80 and 50,000.
Now, as we discussed in the lecture, there are two ways to access the web.
This particular application on the web UI, one is using the internal IP and two is using by mapping
a port to the my Docker host and accessing it using the external IP.
Now to access it, using the internal IP, you need to be inside your Docker host, which is where I
am.
This is the user interface for my DB and Docker host.
So if I open up a browser and go to the IP address, so what IP address should I be using here?
So it should be the internal IP to find out the internal IP of the Docker container.
Go back here.
So if around the Docker command I see the container and to find out the internal IP of my Jenkins container,
I could use the Docker inspect command.
So to run the Docker inspect command followed by the container ID.
And when I do that, I actually see a lot of information about my Docker container, the status, the
image that it's using and all of that.
And if you scroll down in the network section under networks, you'll see that it's using the bridge
network.
We'll talk about networks in a bit.
But right here, if you look at the IP address, you can see the IP address here.
So it's one 7217 .0.2.
So this is the IP that I would use if I were to access this Docker container from inside my host.
So I'm going to go back to the UI for my host and I have a Firefox running enter the IP 170 2.79.0.2
followed by port 8080.
And I'm actually at on the Jenkins page.
So and then I follow the instructions that I have here.
So if you look at the output, after you run the Docker run command, you will be able to see that there's
a there's an admin user has been created and a password generated automatically.
So I'd be using this password to unlock and start configurations on the Jenkins.
But as you can see, we're on we are on the web page by using the internal IP, so that's good.
Now how do I access it externally?
So if I open a web page, so if I open a web page and go to the IP of my Docker host, which is 192
to 160 8.1. 14, and if I try to access the Jenkins server using that IP address, I won't be able to
access this is because that particular port or service is not listening on the Docker host.
Now, in order to do that, as we saw in the lecture, you need to add a port mapping so you cannot
add a port mapping while the server is running.
So you have to stop.
So I'm going to try and stop the Docker container and if I do it over here, I see that it's no longer
running and I'm going to run, use the same Docker run command and in this case I'm going to map the
port 8080 to the port on the Docker host.
And I'm going to run it again.
And if I go back to my browser and refresh.
I should now be able to see the Jenkins page.
Okay, cool.
So I can just follow the instructions right here and.
Get started with it.
So that's really cool.
So I don't I didn't have to install dependencies or follow a lot of set of instructions or install binaries,
etc. to get or get started with Jenkins or any application like that.
It's as easy as running the Docker container for that particular application.
So we've done our port mapping and if you look at this instructions right here, it also gives you instructions
on mapping a volume.
This is because, as you can read here, a Jenkins will store the data in your home directory on the
host.
So by default, Jenkins stores the data in where Jenkins home inside of the Jenkins container.
And if you want to save that information, you need to map a volume.
So just to demo that here, I've actually provided the the password and I've set the initial password
and I'm just going to install it and set it up real quick.
So I'm going to install suggested plugins and it's going to take a few minutes for you to install some
of the default plugins.
So I'm just going to give it, give it some time.
So all that I'm trying to do here is I'm just trying to make some configuration changes on my Jenkins.
Setting it up is a configuration change, setting a password, etc. or you know, installing plugins
are all configuration changes.
So I want to see if the changes that I make will live.
If I were to stop the container and restart it or remove the Jenkins container and run another instance
of Jenkins and will I be able to still see the differences that I made?
So it's installed all the default plug ins and I'm going to create a first user.
I'm going to create an admin user, provide a password,
provide a full name and an email address.
And I'm going to save and finish.
So I'm all set.
Jenkins is ready, and I'm going to start a job.
I'll do I'll add something like enter an item name, for example, test job or something.
And I'm going to select a freestyle project.
And click okay.
Okay, So if I go back to my home page on Jenkins, I see that there's a test job created.
So I have made some configuration change.
Now, if I go back and stop my container.
And if I do a Docker piece.
I don't see any container running.
And if I refresh this page, I see that it's gone.
Now, if I were to rerun another container using the same command.
And so it comes back saying Jenkins initial setup is required and Jenkins is fully up and running.
So if I go back to the browser and refresh the page now this is since I ran the Docker run command.
So it's a new container that's running and obviously we are back to square one where we are asked to
set up an initial administrator password and we'll have to do everything that we just did all over again.
Now, in order to persist that data across Docker containers or across Docker container restarts, or
even if you destroy Docker containers and run a new container, and if you'd like to persist your configuration
data, as you can see here in the instructions, you've got to map a volume and this is the same for
MySQL database or anything like that.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a local directory called my Jenkins data.
And what I'm going to do is when I run the Docker container, next time, I'm going to map.
That volume which is route my Jenkins data.
To the location where dock where Jenkins Docker container stores its data by default that's under Jenkins
home.
I'm going to put that and I'm going to run so there's a permission issue.
There's you have that instruction here so we could use you and specify another user.
So I'm going to start it with the root user.
Okay, so since this is the first time we're mapping a directory, we're just going to go back and we'll
have to do everything once.
So I'm going to copy this password.
And I'm just going to quickly redo what we just did before.
And I'm going to create a new job.
Okay, So I've set up Jenkins, and I've created a test job.
Now I'm going to go back and stop this container.
And as you can see, there's no container running.
And unlike before, I'm going to rerun the same command, but this time I'm going to map the directory,
my local directory, into Jenkins home.
Okay, so this time it's a.
Fully up and running.
And if I refresh my page, instead of going to the initial page where we are asked to enter the initial
admin password, I'm actually asked to log in.
So I'm going to log in with the user that I created and once I log in.
I'm able now to see the test job that I created before.
So that shows that all the custom data that is being generated by the Docker container is actually stored
locally on my Docker host.
And so every time I run a new instance of Jenkins, I could just map that folder and all, all the configuration
data will be picked up by Jenkins when it runs the Docker container.
So that shows how to map a port and how to map a volume on an actual Docker container.
It's a real life example of using Docker with Jenkins.
So that's about it for now.
Thank you very much for your time and see you in the next lecture.