In this series of lectures, we get our networking basics right.
We look at basic networking concepts like switching, routing, gateways, etc..
We then understand DNS.
We look at how to configure DNS settings on a Linux system.
So let's get started.
So what is a network?
We have two computers A and B, laptops, desktops, VMs on the cloud, wherever.
How does System A reach B?
We connect them to a switch, and the switch creates a network containing the two systems to connect
them to a switch.
We need an interface on each host, physical or virtual, depending on the host, to see the interfaces
for the host, we use the IP link command.
In this case, we look at the interface named E zero that we will be using to connect to the switch.
Let's assume it's a network with the address.
One 92.1 60 8.1.0.
We then assign the systems with IP addresses on the same network.
For this we use the command IP HDR.
Once the links are up and the IP addresses are assigned, the computers can now communicate with each
other through the switch.
The switch can only enable communication within a network, which means it can receive packets from
a host on the network and deliver it to other systems within the same network.
So we have another network containing systems C and D at address 190 2.1682.0.
The systems have IP address 192 168 2.10 and 2.11 respectively.
How does a system in one network reach a system in the other?
How does system B with the IP one 92.1 68 1.11 Read System C with the IP 2.10 on the other network.
That's where a router comes in.
A router helps connect two networks together.
It is an intelligent device.
So think of it as another server with many network ports.
Since it connects to the two separate networks, it gets two IPS assigned one on each network.
In the first network, we assign it an IP address, 192 168 1.1 and in the second we assign it an IP
2.1.
Now we have a router connected to the two networks that can enable communication between them.
When System B tries to send a packet to system C, how does it know where the router is on the network?
To send the packet through the router is just another device on the network.
There could be many other such devices.
That's where we configure the systems with a gateway or a route.
If the network was a room, the gateway is a door to the outside world, to the other networks or to
the Internet.
The systems need to know where that door is, to go through that, to see the existing routing configuration
on a system run the route command.
It displays the colonel's routing table.
And within that, as you can see, there are no routing configurations as of now.
So in this condition, your system B will not be able to reach system C.
It can only reach other systems within the same network in the range 192 to 1 68 to 1.0.
To configure a gateway on system B to reach the systems on network 2.0, run the IP route ad command
and specify that you can reach the one 92.1 60 8.2.0 network through the door or Gateway at one 92.1
60 8.1.1.
Running the route command again shows that we have a route added to reach the 18216820 series network
through the router.
Now, remember, this has to be configured on all the systems.
For example, if the system C is to send a packet to system B, then you need to add a route on system
C's routing table to access the network at 1.0 through the router configured with the IP address.
2.1.
Now, suppose these systems need access to the Internet, so they need access to Google At one 72.2
17 to 1 94.0 network on the Internet.
So you connect the router to the Internet and then add a new route in your routing table to route all
traffic to the network.
One 72.2 17.1 94 through your router.
There are so many different sites on different networks on the Internet.
Instead of adding a routing table entry for the same routers IP address for each of those networks,
you can simply say for any network that you don't know a route to use this router as the default gateway.
This way, any request to any network outside of your existing network goes to this particular router.
So in a simple setup like this, all you need is a single routing table entry with the default gateway
set to the Router's IP address.
Remember instead of the word default, you could also say 0.0.0.0.
It means any IP destination.
Both of these lines mean the same thing is 0.0000.
Entry in the gateway field indicates that you don't need a gateway, for example, in this case for
system C to access any devices in the 192168220 network.
It doesn't need a gateway because it is in its own network.
But say you have multiple routers in your network, one for the internet.
Another for the internal private network.
Then you will need to have two separate entries for each network.
One entry for the internal private network and another entry with the default gateway for all other
networks, including public networks.
So if you're having issues reaching Internet from your systems, this routing table and the default
gateway configuration is a good place to start.
Let us now look at how we can set up a Linux host as a router.
Let's start with a simple setup.
I have three hosts.
A, B, and C.
A and B are connected to a network.
190 21681 and B and C to another on 190 to 1 68.2.
So host B is connected to both the networks using two interfaces eight zero and eight one.
He has IP 1921681.5 see has 182 168 2.5 and B has an IP on both the networks 1.6 and 2.6.
How do we get a to talk to see?
But basically, if I try to paint 2.5 from a it would say network is unreachable.
And by now we know why that is.
Host A has no idea how to reach a network at 192 to 1 68.2.
We need to tell host a that the door or gateway to network two is through host B and we do that by adding
air routing table entry.
We add a route to access network one 92.1 68.2, while the Gateway 192 168 1.6.
If the packets were to get through to host C host C will have to send back responses to host A.
When host c tries to reach host a at 1921681 network, it would face the same issue.
So we need to let host C know that it can reach host A through host b which is acting as a router.
So we add a similar entry into host C routing table.
This time we say to reach network 182 168 1.0 Talk to host B at 1 to 168 2.6.
When we try to ping now, we no longer get the network unreachable error message.
That means our routing entries are right, but we still don't get any response back.
By default in Linux packets are not forwarded from one interface to the next.
For example, packets received on E zero on host B are not forwarded to elsewhere through it.
One.
This is this way for security reasons.
For example, if you had it's zero connected to your private network and either one to a public network,
we don't want anyone from the public network to easily send messages to the private network unless you
explicitly allow that.
But in this case, since we know that both are private networks and it is safe to enable communication
between them, we can allow host B to forward packets from one network to the other.
Whether a host can forward packets between interfaces is governed by a setting in this system at file
proxies.
Net IPV four IP underscore forward.
By default, the value in this file is set to zero, meaning no forward.
Set this to one and you should see the pings go through.
Now, remember, simply setting this value does not persist.
The changes across reboots.
For that you must modify the same value in the same size control action file.
So let's take away some key commands from this lecture.
This will be handy in the upcoming lectures.
IP link is to list and modify interfaces on the host IP.
DDR Command is to see the IP addresses assigned to those interfaces.
IP ADR AD Command is used to set IP addresses on the interfaces.
Now remember, changes made using these commands are only valid until a restart.
If you want to persist these changes, you must set them in.
The ETSI Network interfaces file.
IP route or simply the route command is used to view the routing table and IP route AD command is used
to add entries into the routing table.
And finally, remember the command to check if IP forwarding is enabled on a host.
If you are working with a host configured as a router, well, the server for this lecture.
In the next lecture we will discuss about DNS configurations.