In this video we get introduced to Dense in Linux for the absolute Beginners.
We will discuss the basic concepts and view some commands that will help us explore DNS configuration
on hosts, specifically Linux Host.
At the end of this section you will go through a practice test where you're given a set of challenges
related to DNS and are asked to solve them on a live, practical hands on lab environment right in your
browser.
We have two computers A and B, both part of the same network, and they've been assigned with IP addresses,
192 168, 1.10 and 1.11.
You're able to ping one computer from the other using the other computer's IP address.
You know that System B has database services on them.
So instead of having to remember the IP address of the system B, you decide to give it a name.
DB Going forward, you would like to ping system B using the name DB instead of its IP address.
If you try to ping DB now, you would see that host A is unaware of a host named DB.
So how do you fix that?
Basically you want to tell system A that system B at IP address 192 168 1.11 has a name DB.
We want to tell system A that when I say DB, I mean the IP 192 168 1.11.
You can do that by adding an entry into the C host file on system A mentioned the IP address and the
name you want your host to C system.
B As we told system A that the IP at 192 168 1.11 is a host named DB Pins two DB now gets sent to the
correct IP and are successful.
Now there is an important point to note here with all System A that the IP at 192 168 1.11 is a host
named DB host.
A takes that for granted.
Whatever we put in the C host file is the source of truth for host A, but that need not be the truth.
Host A does not check to make sure if System B's actual name is DB.
For instance, running a hostname command on System B reveals that it is named host two but host it
doesn't care.
It goes by what's in the host file.
You can even fool system A to believing that system B is Google.
Just add an entry into the host file with an IP mapping to w ww google.com, then ping google and you
will get a response from system B.
So we have two names pointing to the same system, one as SDB and another as Google.
And we can use either names to reach system B.
You can have as many names as you want for as many servers as you want in the Etsy host file.
Every time we reference another host by its name from host a through a pin command or SSH command or
through any of the applications or tools within this system, it looks into its Etsy host file to find
out the IP address of that host.
Translating hostname to IP address this way is known as name resolution.
Within a small network of few systems, you can easily get away with the entries in the Etsy host file.
On each system I specify which are the other systems in the environment.
And that's how it was done in the past.
Until the environment grew and these files got filled with too many entries, and managing these became
too hard.
If one of the servers IP changed, you would need to modify the entries in all of these hosts.
And that's where we decided to move all these entries into a single server who will manage it centrally.
We call that our DNS server and then we point all hosts to look up that server if they need to resolve
a HOSTNAME to an IP address instead of its own Etsy host files.
So how do we do that?
How do we point our host to a DNS server?
Our DNS server has the IP 192 168 1.100.
Every host has a DNS resolution configuration file at ETSI Resolved conf you add an entry into it specifying
the address of the DNS server.
We say name server and point it to one 92.1 60 8.1. 100 and that should be it.
Once this is configured on all of your host, every time a host comes up across a host name that it
does not know about, it looks it up from the DNS server.
If the IP of any of the host was to change, simply update the DNS server and all hosts should resolve
the new IP address going forward.
You no longer need any entries in the C host file in any of the hosts, but that does not mean you can't
have entries in host file.
You still can.
For example, say you were to provision a test server for your own needs.
You don't think others would need to resolve the server by its name, so it need not be added to the
DNS server.
In that case, you can add an entry into your host at c host file to resolve this server.
You can now resolve the server.
However, no other system will be able to do that.
So a system is able to use host name to IP mapping from the C host file locally as well as from a remote
DNS server.
What if you have an entry in both places, one in your Etsy host file and another in DNS?
I have an entry in my local file set to 1921681.115 and someone added an entry for the same host to
19221681.116 on the DNS server.
In that case, the host first looks in the local Etsy host file and then looks at the name server.
So if it finds the entry in the local Etsy host file, it uses that.
If not, it looks for that host in the DNS server, but that order can be changed.
The order is defined by an entry in the file at C and switch conf the line with the host entry.
As you can see, the order is first files and then followed by DNS files.
Refers to ETSI, host file and DNS refers to the DNS server.
So for every hostname, the host first looks into the etsy host file and if it cannot find it there,
it then looks at the DNS server.
This order can be modified by editing this entry in the file.
As per this order, our host would resolve the test server to 192 168 1.115.
What if you try to ping a server that is not in either list?
For example, I try and ping WW facebook.com.
I don't have facebook.com in my etsy host file and I don't have it in my DNS server either.
So in that case it will fail.
You can add another entry into your resolved file to point to a name server that knows Facebook for
example.
8.8.8.8 is a common well known public name server available on the internet hosted by Google that knows
about all websites on the internet.
You can have multiple name servers like this configured on your host, but then you will have to configure
that on all your host in their network.
You already have a name server within your network configured on all the hosts.
So in that case you can configure the DNS server itself to forward any unknown host names to the public
name server on the internet.
You should now be able to ping external sites such as Facebook.com.
Until now, we've been just trying to read systems with their names like Web, DB, NFS, etc. but we
just tried to ping Facebook at W.
What facebook.com?
What is this name with your w w w and dot com at the end?
It's called a domain name and it is how IP is translate to names that we can remember on the public
internet, just like how we did for our host.
Now the reason they are in this format separated by dots is to group like things together.
The last portion of the domain name, the dot coms, the dot nets, dot, edu, dot org, etc. are the
top level domains that represent the intent of the website dot com for commercial or general purpose.
Dot net for network dot edu for educational organizations and dot org for non profit organizations.
Let's look at one in particular.
In Google's case, the dot is the root.
That's where everything starts.
Dot com is a top level domain.
Google is the domain name assigned to Google and w w w is a sub domain.
The sub domains help in further grouping things together.
Under Google, for example, Google's map service is available at maps dot google.com.
So maps is a sub domain.
Google's storage service is available at drive on Google.com.
Mobile apps are available at Appstore.
Google.com.
Google's email service are available at mail, dot Google.com.
You can further divide each of these into as many subdomains based on your needs.
So you begin to see a tree structure forming.
When you try to reach any of these domain names, say apps dot Google.com from within your organization,
your request first hits your organization's internal DNS server.
It doesn't know who apps or Google is, so it forwards your request to the Internet.
On the internet, the IP address of the server serving Appstore Google.com may be resolved with the
help of multiple DNS servers.
A root DNS server looks at your request and points you to a DNS server serving dot coms dot com.
DNS server looks at your request and forwards you to Google and Google's DNS server provides you the
IP of the server serving the app's applications.
In order to speed up all future results, your organization's DNS server may choose to cache this IP
for a period of time, typically a few seconds up to a few minutes.
That way it doesn't have to go through the whole process again each time.
So that was out in the public.
What about your organization?
Your organization can have a similar structure to, for example, your organization could be called
as my company dot com and have multiple sub domains for each purpose.
The w w w for external facing website mail dot my company dot com for accessing your organization's
mail drive for accessing storage page or company dot com for accessing the payroll application, HR
for accessing HR application, etc. All of these are configured in your organization's internal DNS
server.
The reason we discussed all of these is to understand another entry in the ETSI resolved or common file.
Remember, this is the file where we configure the DNS server to be used for our host.
With that, we were able to resolve servers in your organization with just their names like Web.
We have now introduced more standard domain names like web dot, my company dot com or DB, dot, my
company, dot com, etc..
Now when you ping web, you can no longer get a response.
Of course, this is because we are trying to ping web, but there is no record for by the name web on
my DNS server.
Instead it is web dot my company dot com.
So you have to use web dot my company dot com.
Now I can understand if someone outside our company wants to access our web server, he would have to
use web on my company dot com.
But within our company, your own company, you want to simply address the web server by its first name
web.
Just like how you address other members in your family simply by their first names, which is not the
case when someone outside your family addresses us, them using their full names.
So what do you do to configure web to resolve my web dot, my company dot com?
You want to say when I say web, I mean web dot my company dot com.
For that you make an entry into your hosts at C resolved or conf file called search and specify the
domain name you want to append.
Next time you try to ping web you will see it actually tries web dot my company dot com.
Now your host is intelligent enough to exclude the search domain.
If you specify a domain in your query like this, you may also provide additional search domains like
this.
So it would mean when I say web, I mean web dot my company dot com or web dot product, my company
dot com.
So your host would try searching all of these domain names when you look for a host name.
Finally, a word about record types.
So how are the records stored in the DNS server?
We know that it stores IP to host names that's known as air records.
Storing IPV six to host names is known as Quad A records mapping.
One name to another name is called C Name Records.
For example, you may have multiple aliases for the same application, like a food delivery service
may also be reached at eat or Hungry.
That's where a see name record is used, name to name mapping.
There are many more, but that's all we're going to look at for now.
Now, Ping may not always be the right tool to test DNS resolution.
There are a few other tools as well, such as NSS lookup.
You can use NSS lookup to query a hostname from a DNS server.
But remember this lookup does not consider the entries in the local C host file.
So if you add an entry into the local FC host file for your web application and if you try to do an
NSS lookup for that web application, it is not going to find it.
The entry for your web application has to be present in your DNS server and US lookup only queries the
DNS server.
The same goes with dig.
Dig is another useful tool to test DNS name resolution.
It returns more details in a similar form as is stored on the server.
In the upcoming practice exercises section, you will practice viewing, configuring and troubleshooting
DNS in a lab environment on actual systems through some fun and challenging exercises.
Well, that's it for this lecture.