We now look at some of the Docker commands.
At the end of this lecture, you will go through a hands on quiz where you will practice working with
these commands.
Let's start by looking at Docker Run Command.
The Docker run Command is used to run a container from an image running the Docker run engine.
X Command will run an instance of the engine X application on the Docker host if it already exists.
If the image is not present on the host, it will go out to Docker Hub and pull the image down.
But this is only done the first time for the subsequent executions.
The same image will be reused.
The Docker command lists all running containers and some basic information about them, such as the
container ID, the name of the image we use to run the containers, the current status and the name
of the container.
Each container automatically gets a random ID and name created for it by Docker, which in this case
is silly.
Submit to see all containers running or not use the Dash eight option.
This outputs all running as well as previously stopped or exited containers.
We we'll talk about the command and port fields shown in this output later in this course.
For now, let's just focus on the basic commands to stop a running container.
Use the Docker stop command, but you must provide either the container ID or the container name in
the stop command.
If you're not sure of the name, run the Docker command to get it on success, you will see the name
printed out and running Docker again will show no running containers.
Running Docker Dash A however shows the container Silly Summit and that it is in an exited stage a few
seconds ago.
Now, what if we don't want this container lying around consuming space?
What if we want to get rid of it for good?
Use the Docker arm command to remove a stopped or exited container permanently.
If it prints the name back, we're good.
Run the Docker command again to verify that it's no longer present.
Good.
But what about the engine X image that was downloaded?
At first?
We're not using that anymore.
So how do we get rid of that image?
But first, how do we see a list of images present on our host?
Run the Docker Images Command to see a list of available images and their sizes on our host.
We have four images.
Engine X Readies Ubuntu and Alpine.
We will talk about tags later in this course when we discuss about images to remove an image that you
no longer plan to use, run the docker RMI command.
Remember, you must ensure that no containers are running off of that image before attempting to remove
the image.
You must stop and delete all dependent containers to be able to delete an image.
When we ran the Docker run command earlier, it downloaded the Ubuntu image as it couldn't find one
locally.
What if we simply want to download the image and keep?
So when we run the run docker run command, we don't want to wait for it to download.
Use the Docker pull command to only pull the image and not run the container.
So in this case the docker pull Ubuntu command pulls the ubuntu image and stores it on our host.
Let's look at another example.
Say you were to run a Docker container from an Ubuntu image.
When you run the Docker run Ubuntu command, it runs an instance of Ubuntu image and exits immediately.
If you were to list the running containers, you wouldn't see the container running.
If you list all containers, including those that are stopped, you will see that the new container
you ran is in an excited state.
Now why is that?
Unlike virtual machines, containers are not meant to host an operating system.
Containers are meant to run a specific task or process, such as to host an instance of a web server
or application server or a database, or simply to carry some kind of computation or analysis task.
Once the task is complete, the container exits.
A container only leaves as long as the process inside it is alive.
If the web service inside the container is stopped or crashed, then the container exits.
This is why when you run a container from an Ubuntu image, it stops immediately because Ubuntu is just
an image of an operating system that is used as the base image for other applications.
There is no process or application running in it by default.
If the image isn't running any service, as is the case with Ubuntu, you could instruct Docker to run
a process with the Docker run command.
For example, a sleep command with a duration of 5 seconds.
When the container starts, it runs the sleep command and goes into sleep for 5 seconds post, which
the sleep command exits and the container stops.
What we just saw was executing a command when we run the container.
But what if we would like to execute a command on a running container?
For example, when I run the Docker command, I can see that there is a running container which uses
the Ubuntu image and sleeps for 100 seconds.
Let's say I would like to see the contents of a file inside this particular container.
I could use the Docker exec command to execute a command on my Docker container, in this case to print
the contents of the Etsy host's file.
Finally, let's look at one more option before we head over to the practice exercises.
I'm now going to run a Docker image I developed for a simple web application.
The repository name is called Cloud slash Simple Web App.
It runs a simple web server that listens on Port 1880.
When you run a Docker run command like this.
It runs in the foreground or in an attached mode, meaning you will be attached to the console or the
standard out of the Docker container, and you will see the output of the web service on your screen.
You won't be able to do anything else on this console other than view the output until this Docker container
stops.
It won't respond to your inputs.
Press the control plus C combination to stop the container and the application hosted on the container
exits and you get back to your prompt.
Another option is to run the Docker container in the detached mode by providing the dash DD option.
This will run the Docker container in the background mode and you will be back to your prompt immediately.
The container will continue to run in the back end.
Run the Docker command to view the running container.
Now, if you would like to attach back to the running container later, run the Docker, attach command
and specify the name or ID of the Docker container.
Now, remember, if you're specifying the ID of a container in any Docker command, you can simply provide
the first few characters alone.
Just so it is different from the other container IDs on the host.
In this case I specify a zero for three D.
Now don't worry about accessing the UI of the web server for now.
We will look more into that in the upcoming lectures.
For now, let's just understand the basic commands.
We'll now get our hands dirty with the Docker CLI.
So let's take a look at how to access the practice lab environments.
Next.