Hello and welcome to this demo.
In this demo, we're going to look at some of the basic Docker commands, some basic commands that are
necessary for one to get started and in order to play around with Docker.
So in the previous demo, we installed Docker following a set of instructions from the Docker documentation
site and we ran a sample Docker.
Hello world container and a Docker Ubuntu image.
In this demo we're going to look at some other commands.
So just to start with, we will run the Docker.
We'll start with the Docker run command.
So the Docker run command is used to run a container from an image, so you need to specify an image
name to find out what images you can use.
Go to the Docker Hub website and go to explore and you should be able to see a lot of default official
images available like the Hello World that we just saw.
Let's say you would like to try a center as you could.
You could just do.
If you click on this, you'll see the instructions on running the center.
So you could simply do as you can see here, it just says Docker pulls and os.
So you could simply do a Docker run sent OHS and that should first try and find if there's a st OS image
available locally.
If not, it's just going, going, going to go out and download the latest image or the latest version
of the CentOS image.
As you can see here, the name, if you simply specify a name like this as Santos, it's going to look
at the library repository.
And library is a default docker repository, which has the official images.
So if you go to the go back to the Docker Hub website, all the official images such as those that are
available here can simply be downloaded with just the name of that particular image.
On the other hand, if you develop your own images, for example, if I go to my dashboard and I have
some images that I use here, such as the Ansible playable, etc., if I need to run any of these,
then I need to use the name in this particular format called as the first with the user ID, so that
is my user ID and under.
And then followed by a forward slash and the name of the repository.
So these you should use names in this format if you are using your own images or you could simply use
the name directly, but that then these need to be official repositories that are supported by Docker.
So I have this new image downloaded called Docker Santos.
Now, it's not actually going to as you can see, I am back to my prompt.
It didn't it ran, but it exited immediately and that's because we didn't ask it to do anything.
So it's just the Santos image is just a base image for for the central operating system.
As you know, Docker is used to run services and applications.
So if you want to keep that container alive, you need to be running something.
So I'm just going to run, run it again.
And this time it won't take long because the image is already pulled and I'm going to say, ask you
to run the Bash command and if I want to automatically be logged into the Docker container when it's
run, I should be using the dash i.t options.
We look at what these options are in a bit.
So now as you can see, the prompt has changed.
So what's, what's happened is Docker ran this CentOS container, which is a CentOS operating system
and then run the bash command and then it logged me in directly to the container since I specified the
I.T options.
So I'm now inside the Docker container.
If you look at this, the prompt, it says root at an A unique ID, this is the unique ID for the Docker
container.
Whereas earlier I was at the Docker prompt.
So I'm going to just to check the operating system that I'm on.
I'm going to do a cat slash EDC slash star release star.
And as you can see, I am on the Santos Linux OS, so I'm inside the OS.
Okay, so I'm going to exit now and I'm just going to clear my screen.
So that's the first command.
So Docker run and an image name will run a Docker container.
The next command that we're going to see is the PS Command.
So I'm going to run the Docker, PS Command, The Docker, PS Command lists all the running containers
and in this case I do not have a running container because I just ran the st OS, I got, I logged into
that into as I ran a couple of commands and then I exited and that actually took me out of the container
and the container wasn't doing running any service.
So Docker exited that container, the Docker PS command list, all the running containers.
Only now I do not have any running container.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to run the CentOS container once again.
So I'm going to say Docker run st OS and earlier I gave the bash command and now I'm just going to run
the sleep command, I'm just going to sleep for 20 seconds.
So the container is going to come up.
It's just going to sleep for 20 seconds and then it's just going to shut down.
And then I want to run this in the background, so I'm just going to give a dash d.
So that I get back to my terminal.
And as you can see, this is the container ID and it just ran run the container.
Now, if I run the Docker command, I will see that this is a container ID.
This is the image.
It's running off of.
The command that is running is sleep 20.
So it's going to sleep for 20 seconds.
It was created 7 seconds ago.
It's been up for 6 seconds.
And it's it's got a funny name called Flamboyant Noise.
Now, we asked it to just sleep for 20 seconds, just to keep it alive for 20 seconds.
So if I run the Docker command now, probably it should should have gone.
Yes.
So it's gone because it slept for 20 seconds and then that was the end of that command.
And so since the command exited, the Docker container exited as well, because it didn't have anything
to run or any service running on it.
So that's a quick example of Docker Command.
Now, if you'd like to see all the containers you ran in the past and all the exited containers, especially
so you could do a
run, a Docker, PS Dash, a Docker piece command with the dash a option and you'll see all the, all
the containers that exited.
So the last one that we ran was the St OS with the sleep Command and it was created about a minute ago
and it exited about 54 seconds ago.
Similarly before that we ran the st OS with the bash the first time and I was on it for about 3 minutes,
checking the OS etc. and it was created about 4 minutes ago.
Similarly, you can see all the previous containers that we ran.
So when you run a container and it exits, the container actually lives in on the disk drive.
Now that we have seen how to list all the running containers, let's look at another example.
So I'm going to run the same command to.
Run as Santos.
But in this case, I'm going to sleep for around 2000 seconds.
And what this will mean is that my send, it'll run a Santos container, and then it'll sleep for 22000
seconds.
And so.
And after that, it's going to exit.
Now, if I run the Docker command now, I should be able to see that.
So it's up for 13 seconds and it's just going to be alive for 2000 seconds.
Now, for some reason, if I want to stop or kill this container right now, I could use the Docker
stop command.
So I do a Docker stop and then say serene pasture.
I could either provide the name of the container or I could give the container ID.
And when I do that, it takes a couple of seconds to stop or force kill that particular Docker container.
K Now, if I do a Docker piece, I can see that it's no longer there.
If I do a Docker piece Dash eh, I will be able to see that the container that I just ran at the top,
it was created about a minute ago and it exited about 9 seconds ago and you can see the exit code in
here.
So the exit code for the previous containers are all zero because they exited under normal conditions.
But since I killed it using the stop command, you can see the exit code, which is 137 right here.
So now I have a lot of containers that I ran previously and I kind of want to clean it up.
So what can I do to remove these containers?
For that I could use the Docker arm command.
So I do a Docker arm.
I'm going to start with the first one.
I'm going to provide this container ID so I could either refer to the containers with the container
ID or with the name right here.
So in this case, I'm going to select this one.
I'm going to provide the name.
And so I've removed two containers, and if I do a docker dash a, I will be able to see that those
are gone so that that's what you should do to reclaim disk space.
Similarly, I'm going to get rid of all of this.
Now, I don't need to provide the entire container ID.
I could actually provide just a few the first few letters.
So I say 345 and then I can provide multiple container IDs or names in the same command as well.
So this one is 345.
The next one is E.
Zero A.
The next one is seven, seven three.
So it's going to remove all of them at once.
Now, if I run the Docker command, I can see that all those three are gone.
So this this is a way to remove the Docker containers.
So I'm just going to clean.
Clean up all that.
Six, two and five.
B So I don't have any containers running or dead at the moment, so that's good.
So I've cleaned up all of that.
Now the image that I pulled, which is the I've actually pulled three images so far.
First the hello world, then the Ubuntu and then the CentOS.
Now to see the images that I currently have, I could run the Docker images command.
Then I can actually see the images.
I actually pulled another one called Busy Box, which is a really, really lightweight toolkit, as
you can call it.
It's just one around 1.13 and B in size.
So if you want to really test something really small, you could actually use this particular image.
So now what do I do to get rid of these images?
Let's say I pulled this for just to test them and I want to get rid of them.
I could do a Docker arm command followed by the name sorry, Docker RMI command.
So ARM is used for removing containers.
RMI is used for removing images.
So do a docker RMI and then say busy box that removes the busy box.
Then I do docker or I and remove the ubuntu that removes the ubuntu.
So now I have two left.
And just to demo something real quick, I'm going to run a container based off of CentOS.
And if I do a docker piece dash A now I can see that there's a container based on the center OS image.
Now the reason I did this is if I try to delete now I can see that if I try to delete the docker image
for send always using the RMI command, it'll actually fail.
Telling me that this particular image is being used by a particular container.
So we actually have a container dependent on this particular image that you can see here.
So we need to get rid of all the containers first before removing the image.
So we're going to do.
A doctor.
Erm.
And eight e to remove the container.
And we make sure the container no longer exists.
And then we remove the image using Docker, RMI, CentOS.
And now the image is gone.
Similarly, we're going to remove the Hello world image.
Okay, so we do not have any containers and we do not have any images running at the moment.
Um, okay, so that's some of the basic.
Docker commands.
Let me also show you one another command, which is pull.
So if you do the doctor pull earlier when we run the Docker run command with Ubuntu, it first looks
for an image locally.
If not, it's going to go out and pull the image and then it's going to pull the image and immediately
run that image and run a container with that image.
Now if we don't want Docker to run immediately and if we just want to pull an image and just to keep
it so that later on if we were planning to run it, we don't want to spend time pulling the image.
You could simply pull the image alone using the Docker pool command.
So you do a Docker pull and say Ubuntu and that goes out and pulls the Docker image and stores it locally
on the local system.
OC, so it's pulled the image.
Now, if I now run the Docker images command, I can see the Ubuntu image is there.
Okay, so there's one more thing to look at before we end this demo, and that's running a command on
a particular container.
So we're going to run a open to container, so we're going to do a Docker, run Ubuntu and we're going
to keep it alive for, let's say 1100 seconds and we want it to run in the background so we get back
to our prompt or console.
So we're going to do we run it in the background using the dash.
DD And so there it goes.
If you do a Docker command, you can see that it's running and it's sleeping for 100 seconds.
Now, while a Docker container is running like this, if you'd like to run a particular command on the
on the currently executing container, for example, if you'd like to see the contents of a particular
file which is inside the container, you might want to run a cat command on a particular file.
So to run a command inside a running container first, identify the container you want to work with
and then do a Docker run sorry Docker exec and provide the container ID.
In this case, this is a container ID and then followed by the command that you wish to run.
So I'm just going to run the cat slash Etsy slash star release file.
So I'm just going to look at the release file to understand what version of the OS is running.
So the exec command basically runs or executes and executes a command on a running container.
When I hit this, it actually runs this particular command inside the container and gives me an output.
So that's basically it for this demo.
We just looked at some of the basic commands and the some of the additional parameters we looked at.
We're going to look a look at them a little bit more in detail in the upcoming demos and lectures.
So this is it for now.
So these are some basic commands, so go ahead and play around with it.
Thank you for your time and see you in the next lecture.