Let me now walk you through the hands on lab practice environment.
The links to access the labs associated with this course are available at Code Cloud.
At Code cloud dot com slash P slash Docker Dash Labs.
This link is also given in the description of this video.
Once you're on this page, use the links given there to access the labs associated to your lecture.
Each lecture has its own lab, so remember to choose the right lab for your lecture.
The labs open up right in your browser.
I would recommend to use Google Chrome while working with the labs.
The interface consists of two parts a terminal on the left and a quiz portal on the right.
The quiz portal on the right gives you challenges to solve.
Follow the quiz and try and answer the questions asked and complete the tasks given to you.
Each scenario consists of anywhere from 10 to 20 questions that needs to be answered within 30 minutes
to an hour.
At the top.
You have the question numbers below.
That is the remaining time for your lab.
Below that is the question.
If you are not able to solve the challenge.
Look for hints in the hand section.
You may skip a question by hitting the skip button in the top right corner, but remember that you will
not be able to go back to a previous question once you have skipped.
If the Quest portal gets stuck for some reason, click on the quiz Portal tab at the top to open the
quiz portal in a separate window.
The terminal gives you access to a real system running docker.
You can run any Docker command here and run your own containers or applications.
You would typically be running commands to solve the task assigned in the quiz portal.
You may play around an experiment with this environment, but make sure you do that after you've gone
through the quiz so that your work does not interfere with the tasks provided by the quiz.
So let me walk you through a few questions.
There are two types of questions.
Each lab scenario starts with a set of exploratory, multiple choice questions where you're asked to
explore and find information in the given environment and select the right answer.
This is to get you familiarized with the setup.
You're then asked to perform task like run a container, stop them, delete them, build your own image,
etc..
Here.
The first question asks us to find the version of Docker server engine running on the host.
Run the Docker version command in the terminal and identify the right version.
Then select the appropriate option from the given choices.
Another example is the fourth question where it asks you to run a container using the radius image.
If you're not sure of the command, click on hints and it will show you a hint.
We now run a Redis container using the Docker run Redis command.
Wait for the container to run.
Once done, click on check to check your work.
We have now successfully completed the task.
Similarly, follow along and complete all tasks once the lab exercise is completed.
Remember to leave a feedback and let us know how it went.
A few things to note These are publicly accessible labs that anyone can access.
So if you catch yourself locked out during a peak hour, please wait for some time and try again.
Also remember to not store any private or confidential data on these systems.
Remember that this environment is for learning purposes only and is only alive for an hour, after which
the lab is destroyed.
So does all your work.
But you may start over and access these labs as many times as you want until you feel confident.
I will also post solutions to these lab quizzes.
So if you run into issues, you may refer to those.
That's it for now.
Head over to the first challenge and I will see you on the other side.