Hello and welcome to this course on TerraForm for Beginners.
My name is Vision Palese and I will be your instructor for this course.
In this course, we will get started with TerraForm.
But first we will take a look at infrastructure as code or IAC and the different types of tools available
in IAC and their purpose in managing the modern IT infrastructure.
We will then see the role of TerraForm in today's IT infrastructure.
Then we will learn how to install TerraForm.
This is followed by the basics of Hashicorp configuration language.
Next, we have our very first lab where you'll get your hands dirty working with the seal syntax.
Next, we will understand the basic software form, such as providers, input and output variables,
resource attributes and dependencies.
After this, we will take a look at state inter reform, what it is, why it is used, and the considerations
to follow when working with state.
We then dig deeper into the fundamentals, starting with different commands provided by TerraForm.
This is followed by a lecture where we understand the difference between mutable and immutable infrastructure.
Next, we'll take a look at lifecycle rules in TerraForm, where we'll learn how to manage the ways
in which resources are created.
After this.
We have lectures on basic topics such as data sources, meta arguments such as count and for each and
finally understand version constraints in TerraForm.
After this.
We have a dedicated section on AWS.
This section begins with optional lectures and demos where we learn the basics of AWS.
Such as setting up an account and learning about the basic services such as IAM SW three and Dynamo
DB.
We will then see how to provision and manage these using TerraForm.
Each of these topics, including the ones for us, are followed by hands on labs where we get to practice
the concepts that we have learned.
We will then learn concepts such as remote, state and state, locking with TerraForm and then see how
to store state in a remote SW three backend.
Next, we will see how to use their form state commands to manipulate the state file.
We then have a few lectures and demos where we get introduced to the easy to service and then learn
how to provision it using TerraForm.
Following this, we will learn about provisions in reform, what they are, the different types, the
behavior and considerations to follow when working with provisionals.
We then look at resource states, learn how to enable debugging, and then import other resources into
the management of TerraForm.
Next, we will learn about TerraForm modules, what they are, how to create them, and how to make
use of the modules which are available in the Public TerraForm Registry.
After this, we have a few lectures where we learn about functions and conditional expressions in TerraForm
and how to test them using the TerraForm console.
We will then learn about workspaces inter form what they are, how to create them and when to use them.
We will then wrap up this course with an introduction and high level overview of the features that are
provided by TerraForm Cloud.
In this course, we have video lectures that simplify complex concepts using animations.
In the section of this course, we have demonstration videos that are intended to help you get started
with us and make use of services such as IAM, Dynamo, DB and EC two with the AWS management console.
We have hands on labs where you will get to provision and manage infrastructure resources using TerraForm.
You don't need to set up your own labs or create any cloud accounts.
Our labs are embedded in the course and open right in your browser.
To optimize the user experience.
We have integrated Visual Studio code with the labs.
This will allow you to make use of the built in TerraForm extensions to write configuration files easily
and then run the commands from the integrated terminal.
You would also be developing configuration files that will work with the AWS infrastructure.
Well, I am very excited to begin this journey with you.
So let's get started.