Hello and welcome to this demo.
And this demo, I'd like to show how to create our own Docker image for an application that we have.
So first I'm going to explain a little bit about my application.
So I have a simple web application which is based on Python Flask.
It's on my GitHub page.
It's a really, really simple application that just, you know, gives prints a message onto the screen.
So how do you actually deploy this application?
So there are some dependencies.
First, for example, there are some Python dependencies and then and then you install the web application
dependencies like flask and the flask, MySQL, Python dependencies, and then you basically run your
application using the flask command.
And finally, just go to the once it's up and running, go to the website, go to the browser and access
the IP of the host where it's running on and go to the 5000 port and you'll see a welcome message.
So it's, it's a simple application.
If you if you ask how are you, it's going to come back saying, I'm good.
How about you?
I'm going to show the code.
It's just one single API file.
And if you look at this file, all you have is a simple route, which is the default route that returns
welcome message and then another URL.
How are you that returns another message?
So it's a really simple web application.
So first I'm just going to show how to deploy it manually.
So what I would like to do is I don't want to install anything on my Docker host, just so I don't want
I just want to keep it clean.
I don't want to install some dependencies now and then remove it later.
So since I have Docker already, the easiest way to go about this is to start with some kind of a base
operating system.
So I'd like to start with a base operating system like Ubuntu since I already have it.
The image pulled so I could run a docker run ubuntu.
But what I want to do is I want it to stay alive and I want to work on it.
Work on that particular container.
So I'm going to append a bash command.
So it runs the bash bash command when it starts the container and I'm going to map the standard input
using the dash parameter and the terminal using the T.
So this way as soon as the Ubuntu image starts and it runs the bash command and it takes or it attaches
my input and terminal to that particular container.
So that basically runs the command, runs the container and connects me onto that particular container,
which is all I want for now.
And as soon as I exit the container the, the image is going to stop.
So this is all I want for now just to play around and test my application.
So I have my one two image running and what I'm going to do is I'm going to follow instructions in my
in setting up my simple web application.
So the first thing to do is install Python.
So I'm not going to install the remaining dependencies there, I'm just going to install Python.
So I'm going to run apt get install python.
It cannot locate the package python.
That's because we have to run.
We have it run the apt get update to update the package index.
So I've run that and now I'm going to run and try and install Python.
Okay, so it's installed python, and if I run Python command, I can see that Python 2.7 is installed,
which is good.
So I'm good with that.
So the next step is to install flask.
So I'm going to use PIP install flask so PIP is not found, so I need to install PIP first.
So I'm going to do apt get install python pip.
Okay, so Pip is installed and I'm now going to install the flask dependency from my web application
using PIP.
Okay.
So that's that's installed and it's successful.
So I can now run my web server using the flask Flask run command, but for that I need the source code,
of course.
So I go to my source code and all I'm going to do is I'm just going to copy the source code of the application
and create it here.
So I'm going to put the source code in for Slash opt for slash API, and I'm going to paste the source
code there.
I'm going to follow the instructions.
Here to run the application, which is this.
I'm just going to copy that.
You're on it.
Okay, so it's inside OPPT folder.
So I'm going to go there and I'm going to run that again.
So as you can see, my my Flask application is currently running.
Now how do I access my web server?
So if you remember when I ran the Docker container using the Docker run command, I haven't actually
mapped a port to my Docker host.
And so the only way to access my application is to go in to the host and access it from a web browser
inside my host.
So I'm going to go here and I'm going to go into the one 7217 .0.2 IP, and I'm going to access the
port 5000 because it's 5000 on which my web server is listening.
And when I run that, I can actually see the welcome message come right here and you can actually see
some output here as well.
Another URL that we talked about was how we're used.
I'm just going to say, how are you in the URL?
And it's come back with the message.
I'm good.
How about you?
So.
So that's working.
So my application is working.
So this is how I set up my simple web application.
Now, how do I do?
Authorize it?
Let's go back.
I'm going to quit the application.
I'm going to I've actually got the instructions ready.
So the first thing to do is whatever you need to containerized first, go over the basic install step.
So try to do it once manually and then note down the steps required.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to open a notepad and write down the steps that I followed.
For example, the first thing that I did is apt get update So I'm just going to run the history command
and pull down all the instructions from that and then I run the apt get install python.
And then.
I ran PIPP install flask, but I had to have python pip for that, so I'm going to copy Pip from here.
So this is going to be my next command.
And then followed by PIP install flask.
And then I created my app application file at App Pie.
So I'm just going to write it down here, create or copy application code to Output API.
And then finally I run my flask application.
Using this command.
And this should actually be opt AP vi.
So this is all that I need to install and set up and run my application on a new host on a on a on an
Ubuntu host.
So I have the instructions ready.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to exit out of this container and back to my Docker container.
I'm going to run Docker PS and I see there are no containers running.
So as we saw in the lecture, the first thing to do is to create a docker file.
So I'm just before that, I'm going to create a directory called my custom app.
All right, I'll say my simple web app.
And I'll create all the files, all the all the Docker files inside this particular directory.
So the first thing that I need to create is a docker file.
So I call it Docker file.
And what I did here is if I look at my instructions.
The first thing is before I run the update command as we saw in the instructions in the lecture.
The first instruction should always be from.
So I'm going to start from an Ubuntu based operating system.
So I have the instructions here and I might have my Docker file here.
So I'm going to start with Ubuntu and then I'm going to install, I'm going to run the apt get update
command, apt get update.
Then I'm going to run apt get install dash.
Why that's why is required.
So it doesn't actually wait there waiting for your prompt.
Um, and then I could do both in this command.
I could install Python and Python pip in the same command.
And then I need to run the flask installing the flask dependency.
So I do.
PIPP install flask.
And then this is where I need to copy my source code of the application from my local directory to the
Docker container.
So I use the copy instruction and then I say copy app dot py.
So this, this would mean I, this is assuming that I have my API in my local directory, which I don't
have for now, but as soon as I finish creating the docker file, that's what I would do next.
So I have my API and then I want it to be copied to opt API inside the Docker container.
And then finally the application, the code to run the application that would go in entry point.
So it's the entry point is I just copy.
The command to run my application.
So that's basically it.
And before I run, try to build it, I need my application code in the same directory.
So I'm going to create an AB dot P here and copy the application source code.
So I'm all set.
I could now run the Docker build commands, so I do a Docker build.
Dot and it's going to start building the image.
So I already have Ubuntu.
So the step one out of six was completed immediately because it didn't have to go out and pull the image.
Step two is running apt get update and that's you can see the output of that particular step right here.
Similarly, you will be able to see output of all the instructions on the screen.
Okay, so it's finished building my image.
And as you can see, all the steps are complete.
Step five out of six, six out of six is complete.
And finally, it's successfully built my image.
So if you look at the command, I haven't actually specified a name for the image, so I'm just going
to run it again and I'm going to give a tag.
I'm going to say my symbol web app.
And now, since it's already built, it's just going to go through that real quick because it doesn't
have to rebuild the whole image.
Again, as we discussed in the lecture, whenever Docker builds an image, it builds and caches each
layer.
So all the layers are cached and I don't really have to.
Even if I rebuild the image without any changes, it's just going to build real quick and it's not actually
going to go through the whole build process.
So now I have my new image.
So if I run, if I just clear my screen and run a Docker image, sorry, Docker Docker images.
I can see my new image right here.
And so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to run that by running the Docker run and providing my
symbol web app.
And as you can see, it started and it's listening on 5000.
So if I go inside my host
and if I go to that particular URL, I should be able to see that it's listening and it's working.
Okay, so that's good.
And I could also map it, map a port and access it from my Docker host.
So I have my simple web app image.
Now how do I push it to the Docker hub and make it available to the public?
So once I have my application ready, I could push it to the Docker hub by running the Docker push command.
Now, before that, you should have tagged your application with your repositories.
So if you do a Docker, push my simple web app.
Um, it says requested access to the resource is denied.
The reason is, by default, if you didn't specify an organization in your name is going to try and
push it to the default organization, which is called Library or the default account, which is the
library, and not everybody has the permission to push it to that account.
That's only for default.
Docker supported official repositories, so you can only push to repositories under your own account.
So first what we need to do is we need to build the image and tag it with our not just the name directly,
but you need to tag it with your account name.
So you're going to do a Docker build once again and in this time you're going to tag it with your account
name.
In this case, my name is Mom Shad, and you're going to tag it with your application name.
Okay.
So if we if I do a Docker images, I can see that that I've created a new image and then now I do a
Docker push and provide that repository.
Name the image name.
It says request access requested.
Access to the resource is denied if you haven't logged in.
So there's a prerequisite which is to log in.
So you do a Docker login first, provide your user account.
So my user account is this and I'm going to type in my password.
And log in succeeded.
So that's good.
Now, if I run the push command again.
It will push my image to the darker hub.
Okay, so my application is now pushed to the Docker hub.
So if I go to.
And Docker hub.
And if I go to my dashboard, if I'm logged in with the user, I will now be able to see my application
right there.
So if I look at at the bottom, I see my symbol web app, and if you go inside it, you should be able
to see and you have the command here on how to pull and run this particular application.
That's about it.
That's available now on public.
And if you actually want to make it private, you can actually do that.
But with your free account on Docker Hub, you can only have one of private repositories.
Okay, So once it's there, any user anywhere in the world can actually pull down your image and your
container and run your application with a simple Docker run command.
So that's about it.
In this demo, we looked at how to create our own simple Docker image.
So go ahead and practice for yourself, create your own images, containerized your applications and
push them to Docker Hub.
Thank you very much for your time and we will meet in the next lecture.