Let us start with a simple web application written in Python.
This piece of code is used to create a web application that displays a web page with a background color.
If you look closely into the application code, you will see a line that sets the background color to
red.
Now, that works just fine.
However, if you decide to change the color in the future, you will have to change the application
code.
It is a best practice to move such information out of the application code and into, say, an environment
variable called app color.
The next time you run the application, set an environment variable called add color to a desired value,
and the application now has a new color.
Once your application gets packaged into a Docker image, you will then run it with the Docker run command,
followed by the name of the image.
However, if you wish to pass the environment variable as we did before, you would now use the Docker
run commands option to set an environment variable within the container to deploy multiple containers
with different colours.
You would run the Docker command multiple times and set a different value for the environment variable
each time.
So how do you find the environment variable set on a container that's already running?
Use the Docker, inspect command to inspect the properties of a running container.
Under the config section you will find the list of environment variables set on the container.
Well, that's it for this lecture on configuring Environment Variables in Docker.