In this lecture, we will look at commands, arguments and entry points in Docker.
Let's start with a simple scenario.
Say you were to run a docker container from an Ubuntu image.
When you run the Docker run Ubuntu command, it runs an instance of Ubuntu image and exits immediately.
If you were to list the running containers, you wouldn't see the container running.
If you list all containers, including those that are stopped, you will see that the new container
you ran is in an excited state.
Now why is that?
Unlike virtual machines, containers are not meant to host an operating system.
Containers are meant to run a specific task or process, such as to host an instance of a web server
or application server or a database, or simply to carry out some kind of computation or analysis.
Once the task is complete, the container exits.
A container only leaves as long as the process inside it is alive.
If the web service inside the container is stopped or crashes, the container exits.
So who defines what process is run within the container?
If you look at the Docker file for popular Docker images like Engine X, you will see an instruction
called CMD, which stands for Command that defines the program that will be run within the container
when it starts.
For the engine X image, it is the engine X command for the MySQL image, it is the MySQL D command.
What we tried to do earlier was to run a container with a plain Ubuntu operating system.
Let us look at the docker file for this image.
You will see that it uses bash as the default command.
Now, bash is not really a process like a web server or database server.
It is a shell that listens for inputs from a terminal.
If it cannot find a terminal, it exits.
When we ran the Ubuntu container earlier, Docker created a container from the Ubuntu image and launched
the bash program.
By default, Docker does not attach a terminal to a container when it is run, and so the bash program
does not find the terminal and so it exits.
Since the process that was started when the container was created finished, the container exits as
well.
So how do you specify a different command to start the container?
One option is to append a command to the Docker run command, and that way it overrides the default
command specified within the image.
In this case I run the Docker run Ubuntu command with the sleep five command as the added option.
This way when the container starts it runs.
The sleep program, waits for 5 seconds and then exits.
But how do you make that change permanent?
Say you want the image to always run the sleep command when it starts.
You would then create your own image from the base ubuntu image and specify a new command.
There are different ways of specifying the command, either the command simply as is in a shell form
or in a JSON array format like this.
But remember when you specify in a JSON array format, the first element in the array should be the
executable.
In this case, the sleep program do not specify the command and parameters together like this.
The command and its parameters should be separate elements in the list.
So I now build my new image using the Docker, build command and name it as Ubuntu Sleeper.
I could now simply run the Docker Ubuntu Sleeper command and get the same results.
It always sleeps for 5 seconds and exits.
But what if I wish to change the number of seconds it sleeps?
Currently it is hardcoded to 5 seconds as we learned before.
One option is to run the Docker run command with the new command appended to it.
In this case sleep ten.
And so the command that will be run at startup will be sleep ten, but it doesn't look very good.
The name of the image Ubuntu Sleeper in itself implies that the container will sleep, so we shouldn't
have to specify the sleep command again.
Instead, we would like it to be something like this.
Docker run Ubuntu sleeper ten.
We only want to pass in the number of seconds.
The container should sleep and the sleep command should be invoked automatically.
And that is where the entry point instruction comes into play.
The entry point instruction is like the command instruction, as you can specify the program that will
be run when the container starts.
And whatever you specify on the command line in this case, ten will get appended to the entry point.
So the command that will be run when the container starts is sleep ten.
So that's the difference between the two.
In case of the CMD instruction, the command line parameters passed will get replaced entirely, whereas
in case of entry point, the command line parameters will get appended.
Now, in the second case, what if I run the Ubuntu Sleeper image command without appending the number
of seconds?
Then the command at startup will be just sleep and you get the error that the operand is missing.
So how do you configure a default value for the command if one was not specified in the command line?
That's where you would use both entry point as well as the command instruction.
In this case, the command instruction will be appended to the entry point instruction.
So at startup, the command would be sleep five.
If you didn't specify any parameters in the command line, if you did, then that will override the
command instruction.
And remember, for this to happen, you should always specify the entry point and command instructions
in a JSON format.
Finally, what if you really, really want to modify the entry point during runtime, say, from sleep
to an imaginary sleep 2.0 command?
Well, in that case, you can override it by using the entry point option in the Docker run command.
The final command at startup will then be sleep 2.0 ten.
Well, that's it for this lecture, and I will see you in the next.