Hello and welcome to this lecture.
Before we head into setting up a Kubernetes cluster, it is important to understand some of the basic
concepts.
This is to make sense of the terms that we will come across while setting up a Kubernetes cluster.
Let us start with nodes.
A node is a machine, physical or virtual, on which Kubernetes is installed.
A node is a worker machine, and that is where containers will be launched by Kubernetes.
It was also known as Minions in the past, so you might hear these terms used interchangeably.
But what if the node on which your application is running fails?
Well, obviously our application goes down.
So you need to have more than one nodes.
A cluster is a set of nodes grouped together.
This way.
Even if one node fails, you have your application still accessible from the other nodes.
Moreover, having multiple nodes helps in sharing load as well.
Now we have a cluster.
But who is responsible for managing the cluster?
Where is the information about the members of the cluster stored?
How are the nodes monitored?
When a node fails, how do you move the workload of the failed node to another worker node?
That's where the master comes in.
The master is another node with Kubernetes installed in it and is configured as a master.
The master watches over the nodes in the cluster and is responsible for the actual orchestration of
containers on the worker nodes.
When you install Kubernetes on a system, you're actually installing the following components an API
server and CD service, a cube that service a container, runtime controllers and schedulers.
The API server acts as the front end for Kubernetes.
The users management devices, command line interfaces all talk to the API server to interact with the
Kubernetes cluster.
Next is the Etsy Keystore.
Etsy ID is a distributed reliable key value store used by Kubernetes to store all data used to manage
the cluster.
Think of it this way When you have multiple nodes and multiple masters in your cluster, Etsy D stores,
all that information on all the nodes in the cluster in a distributed manner.
Etsy is responsible for implementing locks within the cluster to ensure that there are no conflicts
between the masters.
The scheduler is responsible for distributing work or containers across multiple nodes.
It looks for newly created containers and assigns them to nodes.
The controllers are the brain behind orchestration.
They are responsible for noticing and responding when nodes, containers or endpoints goes down.
The controllers make decisions to bring up new containers in such cases.
The container runtime is the underlying software that is used to run containers.
In our case, it happens to be Docker, but there are other options as well.
And finally, Cube LED is the agent that runs on each node in the cluster.
The agent is responsible for making sure that the containers are running on the nodes as expected.
So far we saw two types of servers master and worker and a set of components that make up Kubernetes.
But how are these components distributed across different types of servers?
In other words, how does one server become a master and the other the slave, The worker node or minion,
as it is also known, is where the containers are hosted, for example, Docker containers.
And to run Docker containers on a system, we need container runtime installed and that's where the
container runtime falls.
In this case it happens to be Docker.
This doesn't have to be Docker.
There are other container runtime alternatives available such as Rocket or cryo, but throughout this
course we are going to use Docker as our container runtime engine.
The master server has the Cube API server and that is what makes it a master.
Similarly, the worker nodes have the cube let agent that is responsible for interacting with the master
to provide health information of the worker node and carry out actions requested by the master on the
worker nodes.
All the information gathered are stored in a key value store on the Master.
The key value store is based on the popular ID framework, as we just discussed.
The Master also has the control manager and the scheduler.
There are other components as well, but we will stop there for now.
The reason we went through this is to understand what components constitute the master and worker nodes.
This will help us install and configure the right components on different systems when we set up our
infrastructure.
And finally, we also need to learn a little bit about one of the command line utilities known as the
Cube Command Line Tool or Cube CTL or Cube Control, as it is also called.
The Cube Control tool is used to deploy and manage applications on a Kubernetes cluster to get cluster
information, to get the status of other nodes in the cluster and to manage many other things.
The Cube CTL run command is used to deploy an application on the cluster.
The Cube Cluster Info command is used to view information about the cluster and the cube CTL get nodes.
Command is used to list all the nodes part of the cluster.
That's all we need to know for now, and we will keep learning more commands throughout this course.
We will explore more commands with Cube CTL when we learn the associated concepts.
For now, just remember to run cluster info and get nodes commands and that will help us get through
the first few labs.
That's it for this lecture.
I will see you in the next lecture.