In this section, we're going to talk about what it looks like to install Jenkins.
Now, you're going to be pretty pleasantly surprised that it doesn't take all that much to get Jenkins
up and running.
It's a few lines on the terminal.
Open up a port and that's pretty much it.
So our environment is we're going to be installing Jenkins on a boon to 20.4.
Now I will be running that virtual machine inside of Azure.
Don't worry.
You don't need Azure.
You could use AWS, you could use GCP, you could use a virtual machine running locally on your desktop
or your laptop.
It totally doesn't matter.
I'm just running it in Azure because it's easy.
So we're going to install Jenkins fully on a boon to and we're going to install all of the dependencies
that are needed to get Jenkins up and running.
And then once we do that, we'll be able to log into the Jenkins portal, see all the visuals and start
to play around and get on our journey.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.