All right, everybody, let's go ahead and dive into what it's going to look like to install Jenkins
on a beam.
Now, we will be using a boon to and again, I'm going to be using Azure, But you could use anything
like you could use Hyper-V locally.
You could use an A boon to server ISO that you download from a website.
You could really use anything.
But for me it's just easier to just spin up a quick VM in Azure.
So that's what we're going to be doing today.
So first things first, I'm just going to go to virtual machines and I'm going to click Create Virtual
Machine.
Now you can skip this step if you want to, although it may actually be helpful for you to see the resources
that I'm using like RAM and CPU and stuff like that.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to just choose my Code Cloud Resource group.
I'm going to give it a name, I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to choose a boon to 24.
And go ahead.
And I'm going to choose the size that I want.
So it's going to be one CPU and two gigs of memory.
Fairly small, fairly cheap.
Next, I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to set up a password here, and that's just going to be the
username and password to SSH into the server.
I'm going to allow Port 22 to be open.
Definitely don't do this in production.
I'm just doing this because it's a demo environment.
But really what this is saying is I'm going to be able to hit the server from any IP, no firewall rules
or security groups or anything or present.
For discs.
It's going to be a premium SSD.
I'm going to go ahead and put it into this code Cloud V Net and click next review.
I just had to redo the password there.
Now I can go ahead and create my VM.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to create this VM.
And then once it's done, I'll go ahead and open it up in a terminal.
So I have my terminal here and what I'm going to do is I'm going to type SSH mike at IP address.
This is the public IP address of my virtual machine.
Let me go ahead and I'm going to click.
Yes.
I'm going to type in my password.
Okay.
And now we are officially inside of the server.
So I'm going go ahead and I'm going to clear this.
First thing that I'm going to do is run sudo apt update minus y.
This is just to update the server here.
And then next, I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to run my prerequisite.
Now, really, the only prerequisite that I need is to install Java.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to install Java.
And now that our prerequisite is installed, we are ready to start installing Jenkins.
First things first, we're going to go ahead and we're going to add the repository key to the system.
Next, we're going to go ahead and we're going to append the package repository to the server source
list.
Essentially, what that means is we are taking the Jenkins repo and we're adding it to our aptitude
package manager.
Next, we're going to go ahead and we're going to run sudo apt update minus y.
And the reason why is because it's now embedding that jenkins repo or package inside of our package
manager and then we'll be ready to actually install Jenkins.
So let's go ahead and do that.
And just like that, Jenkins is installed very straightforward.
Now all we have to really do is start Jenkins and ensure that we can reach the server.
So let's go ahead and do that by running our start command.
You got to put the s in front of that.
And what this is going to do is it's going to actually start the service.
Next, we're going to go ahead and we're going to run system CTL status.
Jenkins We can see that it is, in fact active and running.
And then now we're going to go ahead and we're going to open up the firewall.
So what that's going to do is it's going to allow us to interact with Jenkins from the UI and it needs
port 80, 80 open.
So we're going to go ahead and we're going to allow that.
We can go ahead and we can run the firewall status here.
And we can see that it is in fact inactive, which is perfectly fine.
So next I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to hit exit there.
I'm going to copy this IP address.
And then I'm going to go ahead.
I'm going to open up our Web browser.
We're going to type this in.
And we should be able to access Jenkins.
And if we can, I'll tell you exactly why.
If we go to the Azure portal and we go to networking, the port may not be open.
So let's go ahead and add the source port range of any.
The destination is any.
The destination port range is four 8080.
Then we're going to go ahead and we're going to give this a name port 8080 there.
So now it's creating our security rule here.
That way we can access our server on Port 8080.
And now we are officially good to go here.
Now to actually unlock Jenkins, we have a password that we need to hit and that password is on our
server.
And the way that we do that is we run sudo cat var lib jenkins.
This is where our Jenkins application or package lives secrets.
And then there's an initial admin password.
That's going to be this password right here.
I'm going to go ahead and copy that.
Go back to Jenkins.
I run that.
And then as we can see, our server is officially up and running.
And what we can do is we can install the suggested plugins and we'll go ahead and we'll wait for this
to finish.
And then once it's finished, it'll come up to our Jenkins UI.
Now we're going to go ahead and we're going to create our first admin user.
So I'll just say, Mike, give it a password here.
Give it.
And full name.
We have our Jenkins Earl here.
Now, if we had a dense address, we could obviously pass that in here, but we don't at the moment.
So we'll just go ahead and we'll keep it as the IP address.
We'll go ahead and click, save and finish start using Jenkins.
And we are officially at the portal.
All right, everybody.
That's it for this lecture.
Head over to the labs and start practicing what you've just learned.