When you first install Jenkins, you're going to have a bunch of different things that you can do in
the UI, and we're definitely going to go over all of that good stuff.
But there is also a CLI.
So if you prefer to work out of the terminal instead of clicking around a UI, Jenkins does have a built
in command line interface that we can use and we can connect to it via curl.
And if we scroll down here we can actually see that there is an authentication method here that we can
use to get into the server.
So from the portal here, if I click on my name and I go to configure.
And I scroll down here, I have a few different options, like an API token, for example, credentials,
email.
This is just a fake email here, but if I keep going down, I have ssh keys.
So if I wanted to, I could take an SSH key, a public one, and pop it in here.
So for example, if I type cat ID RSA dot pub, this is my public ssh key on my Mac.
So if I go ahead and if I copy that, then I paste that in here, I click Save and I go back to configure,
scroll down.
I now have a public ssh key associated with my user Mike, and now I can work on the terminal via the
Jenkins CLI.
Now I will admit that you probably won't see people working on the CLI all that much.
It's going to be more or less throughout the UI and a lot of the courses that you see as well.
But if you want to now that you're authenticated, you can start working with the Jenkins CLI and using
the different common commands and all that good stuff.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.