All right, everybody, now that we understand a little bit about the Jenkins clay, what it does,
let's go ahead and learn how to use it.
So I'm at my Jenkins portal right now.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to click on Manage Jenkins.
Now, if I scroll all the way down here, notice how under tools and actions I have Jenkins CLI.
Let's go ahead and click on that.
Now, this does show a little bit of a piece of documentation stating what you can do to get up and
running and all of that.
But let's go through from an authentication perspective.
So first things first, let's go ahead and install the Jenkins cloud.
So I'm going to open up my terminal here and I'm on my Jenkins host.
Notice I'm going to run a command against the Jenkins Cloud jar.
Now, if I lose here, we'll see that I have my Jenkins Clyde dot jar.
Now we have to authenticate to Jenkins from here.
Even though yes, we are on the Jenkins host, we still have to authenticate to Jenkins.
Now, the way that we can do that is if I go ahead and I open up another Jenkins portal here, I'm going
to go to manage actually, rather under my name here, I'm going to click on configure.
And then I'm going to go to API tokens.
Now, under here, as you can see, I already have an API token created.
You may not, which is okay, all you have to do is just click add new token and the new token will
pop up when I click generate here.
And as you can see, I have a new token right here.
So now that I have the token, I can authenticate to Jenkins.
And how do we do that?
Well, let's go ahead and open up our terminal here again.
And as you can see, I'm running the Java Jar Jenkins command.
I'm specifying my URL here.
And now I have this auth argument.
And what the auth argument does is I pass in my username.
Colon, then my API token.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to run that.
And boom, as we can see, we get a whole bunch of these commands that are available for us because
we're authenticated.
So now let's actually run through maybe, I don't know, showing some jobs, for example.
Well, go ahead.
And I'm going to run this command.
And what this is doing is it's pretty much the same exact command that we had before, except now I'm
specifying the web socket argument with list jobs.
And as we can see, we have one job here called Test one.
Let's actually create a new job.
And what that means is where it's going to create a new pipeline.
And we're just going to create a template, one just to getting started one.
So I'm going to call this test two.
I'm going to click on Pipeline, then I'm going to click okay here.
I scroll all the way down and then you're going to see this try sample pipeline.
We'll click on Hello World.
This is just going to literally Echo Hello World here.
So I'm going to click Save.
Then.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to go back to my terminal to clear my screen and I'm going to
run the command to list jobs one more time.
Now notice here I now have two jobs listed.
Before we only had test one.
Now we have test one and test two.
So I'm going to run a new command again.
This is always the same here, folks.
So the Java jar specifying the Jenkins jar, specifying the server URL specifying the auth.
This is always the same.
Really, the only thing that actually changes is the command itself.
So as you can see, we had the list Jobs command.
Now we're going to do the build command.
So we're going to do this build against test two.
So really quick, as you can see, we have no builds here currently literally nothing.
You go, and I'm going to run this command.
You go back to the Jenkins portal here, and as you can see, we now have a build that ran successfully.
So if you want to get started with the Jenkins CLI, this is typically the best way.
Go through, learn about the authentication methods, learn how to list jobs, how to build jobs, etc..
Well, that's all for now.
Let's get some hands on practice.