In this section, we'll go through some of the basics of Linux command line.
If you're already a Linux maestro, then feel free to skip this section or simply go through the labs
and try to complete the challenges and make sure you're comfortable with all of them.
While designing this course, we used Stack Overflow insights along with the data from surveys we conducted
from our student base and which you might have seen in our other courses to identify the most commonly
used and most demanding technologies that we will cover in this course.
That way we can make this course relevant to most of you.
So you'll see me referring to these often, and I hope learning the most loved and wanted technologies
will motivate you.
As for Stack Overflow insights, the most common and the most loved platform used for development work
happens to be Linux.
If you're from a Windows background, I'd highly recommend learning some Linux basics as most DevOps
tools have a requirement for Linux.
The reason I say that is because many of the new DevOps tools are developed and used in Linux environments
first before they are made available on Windows.
For example, Containerization tools like Docker was only available on Linux based systems for many
years before being supported on Windows platforms.
Similarly, automation tools like Ansible requires it to be installed in a Linux environment.
Even though Ansible can manage Windows systems as target machines.
A Linux system is required to be the Ansible controller in case of container orchestration tools like
Kubernetes Cluster.
The master nodes can only be Linux systems.
As the documentation says, there are no plans to have a Windows only Kubernetes cluster as of this
recording.
So when you go through our Kubernetes series of courses and setting up a Kubernetes cluster is all done
in Linux.
The same is true for certification exams.
The Kubernetes and Red Hat, Ansible certification exams are all to be done on Linux systems.
So if you plan to learn these technologies and get yourself certified, then it's important to have
knowledge of basic Linux operating system.
And if you've always thought Linux is not for you, you might want to go through our courses and think
again.
As part of this course, we cover basics of Linux OS such as how to work with the command line interface,
how to work with text editors like V Editor.
We discuss package management and services, etc..
There are different flavors of Linux such as Ubuntu, RedHat, Enterprise, Linux, CentOS, etc..
We conducted a survey of our students and a good percentage of them requested their preferred OS to
be CentOS followed by Ubuntu and Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
CentOS is a free community edition of Red Hat Enterprise Linux, so learning CentOS also helps you cover
the basics of RCL.
Learning Centers will also help you prepare for Linux certifications like Linux Essentials or Linux
Foundation's Certified Systems Administrator Certification.
Now, since you also cover basics of Red Hat Enterprise Linux by going through this, it also helps
you prepare for any Red Hat exams.
So you kind of cover two versions of operating systems, CentOS and a Red Hat Enterprise Linux in one
shot.
And that's why we decided that CentOS is going to be the OSS of our choice for this course.
Note that this course covers a variety of topics from Linux to applications to databases and web servers,
etc. And so this section is only meant to be a crash course in Linux.
If you'd like to learn more about Linux, then what is covered in this course?
I recommend going through the full fledged Linux basics course available at Code Cloud.
It's a completely new concept, a new way of learning.
It's in a story or a comic format and has a lot of lab exercises that you can practice with and I'm
sure you'll love it.
So check it out after you're done with this course.
So let us begin our Linux crash course.
In this section.
You're going to work with Linux systems in our lab.
This is so you get very familiar with the Linux CLI and some basic commands before you actually deploy
a Linux system by yourself.
The next section is about deploying a Linux system on your Linux laptop using tools like VirtualBox.
When you do that, the CLI and commands you'll learn in this section will be handy.
So I recommend not deploying your own Linux system for now.
Instead, just rely on our labs and get some good hands on practice and then in the next section deploy
your own VMs.
So we will start assuming Linux system has already been provisioned.
Let's start with Shell.
Linux systems have both CLI and die interfaces.
When you work with Linux, especially in I.T., you work with the CLI and you must get really comfortable
with it because most servers that you work with in your work environment won't really have a graphical
user interface.
So we will just focus on the command line, the text based command line interface that helps you run
commands to interact with the operating system is called the Linux shell.
If you have ever worked on a Linux system before, you might have noticed that sometimes the CLI interface
behaves differently, as in sometimes you press the backspace button to delete a command and it doesn't
work.
Or when you press the tab button to autocomplete, it doesn't autocomplete.
And that's because there are different kinds of shells such as The Bourne Shell, the C Shell, Z Shell,
born again Shell, which is known as Bash.
And each of these shells behave differently.
The older shell, which is the Bourne Shell, or simply known as Shell, had limitations in the way
we interact with it.
The newer Bash Shell supports many advanced features, such as arithmetic operations, conditionals,
arrays, etc..
You can see which shell you are on by printing the environment variable named Shell using the echo dot
shell command.
The echo command helps you print on the screen and the dollar symbol helps you specify an environment
variable.
Let's not get introduced to some basic Linux commands.
We will first look at the commands and you will then work on labs where you will use these commands.
Echo, as we just discussed, is the command used to print a line of text.
The word you enter after the echo command will be printed on your screen, as simple as that.
The echo command is usually used when you want to print out an environment variable as we just saw.
We will discuss about environment variables later.
The echo command is also used in scripts where you want to print out information onto screen.
The LS command is used to list all the contents of a directory.
Here we see that we have two files, files, txt and file two conf and a directory named my underscore
dir one.
The CD command stands for Change Directory and it is used to navigate to new directories in the system.
For example, to get into the my underscore da one directory run the command c d followed by the directory
name.
The P.W. de Command or the present working Directory Command is used to print the directory you are
currently in.
The McDeere or the make directory.
Command is used to create a new directory.
In this example, we've created a new directory called new underscore directory.
To run multiple commands, one after the other, separate them by semicolon.
In this case, it first changes into the new directory, then makes a directory by the name w w w and
then prints the current working directory.
Now, even though it's a single execution, remember there are three separate commands and executed
one after the other.
At times you might want to create a directory tree.
For example, we want to create a directory slash tmp slash azure slash India slash Bangalore.
One way to do that is to run the make directory command three times, specifying one directory each
time.
For example, first we create the first directory and then we create the India directory inside Asia
and then we create the Bangalore directory inside India.
A better way to do that would be to run a single command using the dash P option like this.
This way, it creates the entire directory tree in one shot and does not complain if a particular directory
is not available to remove a directory and all of its contents run the arm minus our command and specify
the directory name.
To copy one directory to another location, use the CP command.
But with the AR option, this copy is the directory and all of its contents from one location to another.
Let's see some commands to work with files to create a new file, run the touch command and provide
the file name.
This creates a new file, but with no contents.
To add some contents to the file, use the CAT command and the redirection symbol, which looks like
a forward arrow followed by the file name.
Once this command is issued, the prompt will wait for your user input.
You would be able to add lines of text.
Hit the return key to typing into a new line of text and press the control dx combination to exit out
of this prompt and save the data to the file to view the contents of a file.
Run the cat command followed by the file name this time without the redirection symbol.
These are some basic commands to work with files in the CLI.
For editing contents of a file.
You may need a text editor like VI or VIM.
We also take a look at the basics of VI editor later in this course.
Now, while working with DevOps tools, you'll often come across situations where you will have to modify
configuration files on Linux.
And these editors will come handy then.
But to get through this lecture and the following labs, you don't really need a text editor.
So let's continue to copy a file, use the CP command and specify the source file path and name and
the target path and name to move a file, which is similar to cutting and pasting a file to a different
location.
Use the MV command, specify the old name and the new path and the file name.
If the file is moved to the same path but with a different name, then it's essentially like renaming
the file.
So you're cutting the file, which has one name and then pasting it in the same directory with another
name.
So that kind of works like a rename and that is how you rename a file in Linux.
Now there's no separate command for that.
Run the command to remove or delete a file.
So that's about it for this section.
Head over to the labs and practice working with these basic Linux commands.