I wanted to share a quick tip about how I think you can maximize the hands on experience and results
you gain from this course.
So think of this like learning how to build a car.
Now, if you start building the car without ever having driven or being in one, you will find it especially
difficult.
Now, you would have no idea what the wheels, the transmission or electronics are for and how the brakes
work or why you need a hand brake and so on.
But once you have driven a car for some time, then you'll know the role that all these vital elements
play in the function of the car.
And then when you learn how to build the car, it will be with a feel for the machine that you are aspiring
to build, and you will build it with an actual understanding of the parts that you are putting together.
Now, typically most courses out there ask you to set up virtual machines on virtual box or cloud environments
at this stage of the course.
However, this takes a lot of time and not to mention the extra time troubleshooting so you can get
everything working correctly and even then you may not have access to enough resources on your system
or on access to cloud platforms.
And often you will have to clean up your work before you can even begin working on the next course topic.
And all of these take away a lot of time when it comes to focusing on the things that actually matter.
Now, of course, it's important to learn how to set this up, and you'll learn a lot by troubleshooting
and figuring things out for yourself.
But repeated issues will discourage some of you, and others will even give up and everyone will miss
out on the new skills that they were about to gain.
At the end of the day, all this teaches you is how to provision VMs on your laptop and figure out networking
functions.
And we have specific courses for this that can be taken separately.
And you should, if you want to learn how to set up your own local environments.
However, if your main goal is to learn about the topic that's taught in this course, the best approach
is to spend maximum time gaining hands on experience in this specific topic.
And that's exactly why we build our dedicated labs.
So my recommendation to you is to go through and aim to complete this course as soon as possible and
to complete it using our labs for the best possible experience and results.
Each lab is specifically crafted for the lecture that you learned before, so there is no cleanup needed,
no messed up environments, no missing prerequisites.
You go from learning something to actually gaining experience in about less than 20 seconds.
So protect yourself and your learning journey from distracting issues that are out of your control For
now.
Contain that urge to set up your own local environments and build your own local system.
Once you complete the entire course, you can dedicate your time and focus to setting up your own environments
and working on your own research and projects.
And we have a lot of resources to help with that too.
And by then you will have all the prerequisite knowledge to build your own environment.
And if you do run into issues, you will be in a far better position to resolve them.