Hey, so here is a quick reminder and I hope you don't mind me jumping in like this.
I wanted to take a moment to remind you about the importance of staying focused on the labs and videos
that are provided in this course.
Now, I understand that you may be eager to create your own local setup to practice, but I recommend
that you resist that urge until you have completed the course.
Our labs and videos are designed to give you a seamless learning experience that will help you gain
the most out of the course in the time that you have available.
By sticking to the labs and videos provided in the course, you can minimize distractions and interruptions
and ensure that you have a clear path from start to finish.
And this will help you stay focused on your learning goals and make the most of your time with us.
Rest assured, we will provide you with resources to create your own local setup at the appropriate
time in the course.
For now, let's focus on the labs so you can gain the knowledge and skills you need to succeed.
Thank you for choosing our course.
Thank you for choosing Code Cloud and we look forward to helping you achieve your learning goals.