Hello.
In this video, I will explain how to access labs part of this course.
This course comes with real hands on labs that you can access right in your browser.
Unfortunately, Udemy does not have native support for embedding real hands on labs in the course.
And that's why these labs are hosted on Code Cloud.
Students who purchased this course on Udemy can get access to the labs for free on Code Cloud.
You don't have to make any extra payments to access the labs.
There is a lecture named Access Labs in your course.
Right before the first lab starts.
In the lecture, there is a link to enroll in the labs.
Use the link to go to the checkout page on Code Cloud to gain access to the labs for free.
If you haven't signed up on the Code Cloud website before, you will need to provide your email address.
A temporary password will be emailed to you so that you can log in.
Code Cloud and Udemy are different platforms and unfortunately there is no option available yet to share
the same user accounts between the two.
So you must create an account and sign up on Code Cloud to access the labs.
Remember your Udemy credentials won't work on code Cloud.
If you are accessing through Udemy for business, then your company credentials won't work either.
You must create a new account on Code Cloud.
This is something we hope to improve in the future.
Once logged in, you can find your course under the courses page.
Lab courses start with the term labs in their name.
Once the labs are open, use the maximize button to hide the course curriculum to get more space for
your labs.
And if you want to see the course curriculum again, click on the same button.
And to turn on dark mode, click the theme toggle button in the top right corner of your screen.
Once you're done working on a lab market, complete, using the complete button.
As you can see, there are multiple lab scenarios for each course and when to access which lab.
The detail of that will be given within the course.
AS and when you progress through the course on Udemy, you will know when to access what lab.
Well, that's it for now.
I wish you all the best.
And if you run into issues with accessing labs, please write to support and support at icloud.com.
I hope you have a great learning experience from us.