In this section, we will learn more about console based text editors and Linux.
Earlier in this course, we saw the usage of the CAT command to write and redirect data into a file.
While this works well and has its uses, it is a very basic form and offers no additional features and
is not feasible when dealing with adding or manipulating large amount of texts or for writing code.
In the DevOps and cloud world, you'll be working with a number of Linux servers and most of the time
you'll be accessing them remotely using terminal tools and you'll be modifying content in a number of
files, configuration files mostly.
So getting the basics of VI editor comes in really handy in such cases.
There are a number of text editors available in Linux such as VI, Vim, Nano, etc. and in this course
we will look at VI editor, which happens to be the most popular one.
VI ed comes installed by default with most operating systems.
Run the VI command and specify the file name to open it.
The terminal opens the file and you're now inside the VI editor.
VII.
Ed has two modes of operation the command mode and the insert mode.
When you open a file in VI editor, you are by default in the command mode.
In this mode you can issue commands to the editor, such as to copy and paste lines or delete a line
or a word, or to navigate between lines, etc..
But you cannot write contents to the file.
To write contents to the file, you must switch to the insert mode to switch to the insert mode.
Type lowercase i.
Once you are in insert mode, you may modify the file contents as you would normally to switch back
from insert mode to the command mode.
Press the escape key.
Let's see what operations are available in the command mode.
You may move around through the editor using the arrow keys or the keys cage on your keyboard.
K to go up H to left J two down and L to the right.
To delete a character, press X.
Typing D deletes the entire line to copy a line type y y.
And to paste it.
Type in P.
To scroll the page up or down, press the control plus you or DD buttons.
Typing in colon takes you to the prompt where you can type in commands to save the changes made to the
file and write the file to disk.
Use the colon w command.
You can optionally specify a file name as well.
To discard any unsaved changes made to the file and quit whim type in colon Q command to save changes
and quit type in colon WQ command.
So how do you find stuff?
For example, I want to find the word off in this file for this type in the command slash off.
When you do that, all occurrences of the word off is highlighted and the cursor is positioned at that
location to move your cursor to the rest of the occurrences.
Press the key and you can continue to press the end key to move the cursor to all future occurrences.
Well, that's it for the basics of VI editor.
For now, head over to the labs and practice working with VI Editor.