Let us now look at some more Linux commands that will help you get through this course.
We will start with user accounts to know which user you are.
Run the Who am I command.
In this case it says you are user Matthew.
The ID command gives you more information about the user, such as the user's ID, which happens to
be 1001 and the group ID and the groups that the user is part of.
To switch from one user to another, you may use the su command su stands for switch user to switch
to user.
Say Aparna run the su command followed by the user's name.
You will then be prompted for the user's password.
If you're accessing one system from another system using say, ssh and you want to log in to the other
system using a different user than your current user, specify the username before the host name followed
by an add symbol.
When it comes to performing tasks.
Not all users can do all tasks in Linux.
Matthew is a regular user and so his access on the system is restricted.
Every Linux system has a super user known as the root user.
The root user has no restrictions on the system and can perform any task, which is why in most production
environments or enterprise environments, access to the root user is restricted and you will almost
never log in to the systems as a root user.
Now, as a normal user, what if you wish to perform actions that can only be performed by a root user
such as installing and configuring software and services on the system, or viewing certain paths such
as the root directory?
A root user can make that possible for a regular user by granting them pseudo privileges, by making
an entry into the ETSI pseudo ers file.
So the user is still a regular user but with root privileges.
When a regular user is granted pseudo privilege, they can now elevate their permission level and perform
tasks that they otherwise couldn't by simply pre fixing a command with the keyword pseudo.
They'll be asked for their password and on entering the password the command is executed.
When you look through the labs in the rest of this course, you'll work in an environment where you
will not have root access.
Instead, you will be a regular user with pseudo privileges.
So while making changes to the system, you must remember to use the pseudo prefix.
If not, you will get permission denied errors.
So whenever you hit permission denied errors, remember that it could be because you haven't used the
pseudo prefix.
We will be discussing about a lot of commands through the rest of this course.
And for the sake of brevity we won't be specifying the pseudo prefix each time on all our slides.
So it is assumed that you will use this prefix while working in the labs.
Let us now look at some commands that will help us download files from the internet.
At times you will have to download files from the internet such as RPM packages or binary files or images,
and you can use use the call command and provide the URL of the file to download the file.
Add the dash capital option to save the result to a file.
Otherwise it'll just print the file on screen.
Another tool that can be used to download files is the W get command.
Again, specify the full URL and with the capital O options, specify the name of the file that you
wanted to store locally as.
At times you may be on a Linux system and may not know what operating system you are on.
To know the current OS.
Inspect the release files under the C directory.
The release files may be named differently based on the operating system, so use a wild card like this
to see more details about the OS.
View these files by running the CAT command and you can see that in this case it's CentOS version seven.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
Head over to the labs and practice working with some more commands on the net.