Let's now talk about package managers in Linux.
Package managers help you install various software on the Linux system, and when you go through DevOps
and cloud courses, you will install various software such as Web servers, database servers and DevOps
tools or dependent softwares.
And most of these are installed using package managers.
Santos uses an RPM based package manager just like RedHat Enterprise Linux or Fedora.
RPM stands for Red Hat Package Manager.
A software is packaged into a bundle with the extension RPM to install the package, use the RPM command
and the IE option for install and specify the package name.
To uninstall a package, use the dash E option and to query the database and get details about an installed
package.
Use the dash queue option.
So RPM requires you to point it to the exact location where the RPM package is available.
You then install that package on the system.
It does not care about any dependencies that this package may have.
For example, say you were installing another software like Ansible and it requires Python and other
other dependent software.
So simply installing ansible with the RPM command would not take care of installing python and other
dependent libraries if they are not already installed.
And that's why you need a solution that can make these easy for you.
A single command that can query the package, find its location and install all dependencies as well
as the package itself.
That's where package managers like Yum come into play.
Yum is a high level package manager that uses RPM underneath running a simple yum install, Ansible
command installs ansible and all of its dependent packages.
Yum.
Searches software repositories that act as warehouses containing hundreds and thousands of RPM package
files.
These repositories can be local that is installed on your laptop, for example, or on a remote location,
either a secure server in your enterprise or available publicly in the internet under the hood.
Yum.
Still makes use of the RPM package manager.
So when you try to install a package using yum yum searches, these repositories finds the required
packages and dependencies and installs all of them in the right order.
So what is this remote repository and how are packages stored there?
Like how does yum find where a particular package is located?
The information about the repository in a configuration file at PATH slash etsy slash yum repos dot
dd directory.
Every operating system comes bundled with its own set of repositories from which you can install a lot
of commonly used software and tools.
So you might not need to edit the list of repositories, but at times the default set of repositories
may not have the software you need or may not have the latest version of software that you need to install.
So in that case, you will need to configure additional repositories so that you can find those packages.
Instructions to configure additional repositories are usually made available along with the software
itself, and we'll see an example of that.
So to see the list of repositories available on a system, run the Yum Repo List command.
And here we see that there are a set of CentOS repositories such as the base and extra repository as
well as MongoDB and MySQL ones.
So listing the files under the Etsy Repository directory shows the files where these repositories are
configured.
And if you look inside one of these files, you will see the URL of the location where all packages
are stored.
Now, if you visit this URL, you can see the RPM files that YUM will eventually download and install
on your local system with the RPM utility.
So that's kind of how Yum finds a package in this case since we are relying on an existing yum repo
on CentOS.
It takes us to an older version of Ansible, which happens to be version 2.4.
Although the latest version as of this recording is 2.9.
So as I just mentioned, the instructions to configure the repo to install the latest version of Ansible
is available in the Ansible documentation page itself.
So you can configure a new repo using the install command itself and running this command adds a new
repository to your system, which points to the latest version of Ansible.
To see a list of installed or available packages run the Yum List command and followed by the package
name.
If you want to search for a particular package, it provides the package name and version, and if it's
an installed package or just an available package to remove and install package, run the yum remove
command followed by the package name and to list all available versions of a package.
Run the Yum List command, but this time with the show duplicates option.
So here we see two versions of packages for Ansible and we can see that each of these are from two separate
repositories.
One is from the extras repository and the other is from the APL repository to install a specific version
of a package.
Run the Yum install command with the package name followed by a hyphen and the version of the package.
Well, that's it for now.
Head over to the labs and practice working with packages, and I will see you in the next lecture.