Let's now talk about services in Linux.
Once you install a software on servers, especially those that run in the background, such as web servers
or database servers, you would need to make sure that those servers or services are running and that
they stay running even after the servers are rebooted.
And also you want to make sure that these servers are started in the right order, especially if there
are multiple services available on the server and if they are kind of dependent on each other, you
want to make sure that they all kind of start in the right order.
So services in Linux help you configure software to run in the background and make sure that they run
all the time automatically when servers are rebooted as well as they follow the right order of startup.
When any software that runs as a service in the background is installed, such as a web server or database
server or DevOps tools like Docker, they are automatically configured as a service on the system.
To start that service, you run the service, start command and providing the service name, which happens
to be in this case http ID.
So HTTP in this example is an Apache web server.
Later on we have a section just for http D, but here we're just going to look at it as a service.
The newer method to start a service is to use the system kernel command and run the system kernel start
command and provide the service name.
So in this case system or system, CTL start http d.
System is the command used to manage services on a system de managed server.
Both the commands, the service command and the system command serve the same purpose.
The service command uses the system cuddle utility underneath.
So we will just focus on using the system command for the remainder of this lecture.
To stop a running service, run the system all stop command, followed by the service name to check
the status of a service.
Run the system Call status Command.
To configure a service to start automatically when the system boots up, run the system called Enable
Command and to disable the service at boot up.
Run the system.
Call disable command.
Once services are configured, it is so convenient for administrators to start, stop or enable these
services.
You don't have to go looking for the executables to start these services.
So how do you configure a program or software as a service?
Say, for example, you have a simple Python program and it could be a simple web server that's developed
in Python.
And the code is available at opt code.
My API.
You can run this server with the python interpreter.
Once it's running, if you call the local host for port 5000, you see it return Hello World, which
happens to be the response of the web server.
So it's a very simple web server.
You don't have to worry about Python or the code as of now.
And just know that if you run this command, it's going to start as simple web server that listens on
Port 5000.
And to access that web server, you use the code command to test it, Right?
Later in this course we have sections on Python and where we look at how to work with Python, etc.
But for now we'll just assume that Python is all set up and configured and we can run a simple web server
using this command.
So I have this application and now I want to configure this as a service.
You know, so you want your program to run as a service so that when you run this system, cuddle,
start, command, it starts.
And when you run the system called Stop Command, it stops as simple as that.
So the administrator, when this application is finally configured on a server, the administrator does
not really have to bother about this, the path of this file or the options and arguments that you pass
to it or the path to the python file.
Right.
You want to be able to configure it and to to start the service.
All that you need to do is run the system, call, start command and to stop it, run the stop command
and that's it.
So that's our goal here.
And similarly, you want to configure your application to automatically start when the system boots
up and even automatically restart in case the application crashes.
So how do you how do you do that?
As we just saw, the system called command line utility is used to manage the system services, so we
must configure our program as a systemd service.
So how do we do that?
A system The service is configured using a system, the unit file.
These files may be located at ETSI System rd slash system path.
So let's create a unit file at Etsy.
System.
The system path.
The file must be named with the name that you eventually want the service to be known as.
In this case, we'll name it my app and with an extension service.
Define a section called service using the square brackets inside the file and provide a directive named
exec.
Start under it.
This is where you specify the command that you will be using to run your application.
So the same command that we run here, we're going to put it over here.
And that's it.
That's enough to configure your application as a service.
Run the system, call daemon reload command to let system D know that there is a new service configured
and then run the system called START Command and provide the name of the service.
In this case my underscore app.
Let's check the status of the new service using the system called Status Command.
It lists that the service is in an active and running state.
You can now test by performing a call operation on port 5000 of local host to stop the application.
Run the system call stop command.
Okay, So we have configured our application to run as a service and we are now able to start and stop
it as required.
So how do we configure it to automatically run when the system boots up?
We configure that in the unit file and the unit configuration file has many other options.
The service section is only one of the many sections.
Another section is the install section.
So in this section we basically need to configure this service to run after a particular service that
runs at boot up.
So one way to specify that is using the wanted by directive.
We can configure this service to run after the multi user target run level is started.
Once this is done, you can configure the service to start during boot up using the system.
Call Enable command.
You can also provide additional metadata information about the service, such as description that would
allow others to understand what this service is about.
Now, for that, add a new section in the file called Unit and use the description directive.
If your application has other dependencies such as commands or scripts that are to be run before starting
the application or after starting the application, then add the exec start pre and exec start post
directives and specify the scripts or commands to be run.
If you'd like the application to automatically restart in case it crashes, specify the Restart directive
and set its value to always.
So this is a simple form of a unit configuration file that we've used to configure a simple Python application.
But when it comes to real systems and servers and softwares, this file can be a lot more larger and
with a lot more options.
So let's take an example of a real software, say Docker, right?
But we're not going to talk about Docker itself.
So we have multiple courses on Docker where we talk a lot about Docker.
In this context, Docker is just an example of a software.
So and it's the same with any software, so you don't really need to know anything about Docker to understand
this lecture.
So once Docker is installed, Docker Daemon runs as a background process that listens for Docker commands.
When Docker is installed and executable named Docker DD is made available on the system at PATH slash
user slash bin slash Docker RD.
This is configured as a service using the system unit file at path lib a system, the system Docker
Service.
Now this file has three sections the unit service and install section as we just learned, and you can
see the description as well as some of the other details such as link to documentation, etc. And the
service section has the command that is run to start the docker daemon which is specified under the
exec start section.
Well, the search for now.
I head over to the labs and practice working with services.