So far, we've simply added and committed all our changes.
However, we've actually committed those changes to something called a branch.
As mentioned before, this branch is called master by default.
Now, let's say that a new developer joins the project and wants to add a new story.
We don't want developers to directly make changes to our production code, but instead give them a separate
version where they can change code and commit to until their work is done.
In the meantime, we can keep on working on our own branch only after their entire work is done and
tested.
We want to get the new code into the production code.
What we're actually saying here is that we don't want to always work on the master branch but keep our
project versioned using branches.
A branch is basically a pointer to the last commit.
If you're working on a new feature, you might work on a branch called feature forward slash sign up.
And only once that feature has been finished and entirely tested.
We want to get all those changes into the master branch.
First, let's create a new branch.
We can do so by running the JIT.
Check out Dash B Command with a name of the branch.
Say that the developer is called Sarah and we just create a Sarah branch to see a list of all our branches
and the branch that we're currently on.
We execute the Git branch command.
Currently we have two branches, Master and Sara.
In total we've made one commit initial commit.
They both point to that commit.
As stated before, branches are actually nothing more than pointers to a certain commit.
Now, let's say that Sarah adds a new story and commits this to the Sarah branch.
This commit gets added to the Sarah branch, but not to the master branch.
The master branch is now one commit behind the Sarah branch.
Let's say that the team is growing and you just hired a new developer.
This developer called Max.
Once you write the third story, Max is currently still checked out on the master branch.
But to keep things clean, Max also creates his own branch called Max.
Max writes the third story and commits this to his Max branch.
The Sara and Master branch don't have this change yet.
Only Max Branch has this change.
Here are some useful commands that you can use when you're working with branches in order to create
a new branch.
You can run the get branch command with the name of the new branch.
You can switch branches with the git checkout command followed by the name of the branch to which you
want to switch to create a new branch and immediately switch to this new branch.
You can run the Git checkout B command.
This command combines the git branch and get checkout commands together and to delete a branch run the
git branch.
Dash d command The dash d flag stands for delete and to list all the branches that you currently have.
You can run the git branch command.
Now that we've talked about branches, it's important to know what a head is.
You might see the reference to head in quite a few places.
A head is where you are right now in the git repository.
The head points to the last commit in the branch that you're currently on.
When you switch branches, the head moves with you.