If you're working on a new feature, you might work on a branch called feature forward slash sign up.
And only once that feature has been finished and entirely tested.
We want to get all those changes into the master branch.
We can merge a branch with a git merge command.
The git merge command receives the name of the branch that we want to merge into our current branch.
In this case we first have to check out to the master branch in order to merge feature forward slash
sign up into master.
We can now merge by typing git merge feature forward slash sign up.
There are two types of merges that git can perform a fast forward merge or a no.
Fast forward merge.
A fast forward merge can happen when the current branch has no extra commits compared to the branch
that we're merging.
Git is lazy and will first try to perform the easiest option.
The fast forward.
This type of merge doesn't create a new commit, but rather merges the commits on the branch that we're
merging right into the current branch.
Since the master branch doesn't contain any extra commits, we can merge branch directly into master.
Perfect.
We now have all the changes that were made on the branch available on the master branch.
So what's to know?
Fast forward all about.
It's great if your current branch doesn't have any extra commits compared to the branch that you want
to merge, but unfortunately that's rarely the case.
If we commit a changes on the current branch that the branch we want to merge doesn't have, git will
perform a no.
Fast forward merge with a no fast forward merge get creates a new merging commit on the active branch.
The commits parent commit point to both the active branch and the branch that we want to merge.
No big deal.
A perfect merge.
The master branch now contains all the changes that we've made.
That's it for this lecture.
Head over to the labs and start practicing what you've just learned.