Previously we saw it's possible to have a remote repository with Git.
We can push code to this remote repository that is hosted somewhere else and get this code again on
our local machines by pooling this information.
There are several platforms on which we can host our remote repository.
The most commonly used platforms are GitHub, Get Lab and Bitbucket, but there are also many more out
there.
Once we've successfully initialized a repository on one of those platforms, we get access to something
called a connection string.
A connection string is a URL that we can use in order to let Git know where the remote repository is
located.
We can add the remote repository to a local project with a git remote ad command.
We want to add a remote repository and give it the alias origin to make sure that we always know which
remote repository we're pushing to.
Without having to memorize the entire connection string.
In order to do so, we can type git remote add origin followed by the connection string.
After initializing the remote repository.
We have access to this remote repository that is hosted at the location of the connection string.
You can list all your remote repositories with a git remote v command.
In order to work with this remote repository, we can fetch and push the necessary data from our local
project to the hosted repo.
In this case, we're both pushing and fetching data from the same remote repository, which gets shows
us first.
Let's see how we can push data to this remote repository.