In order to keep our local and remote repo in sync, we have to push the data from our local repo to
the remote repo.
We can push data to a remote repo with a git push command.
This command expects two more arguments.
The alias of a remote repo which we called origin in this case and the current branch that we're on.
We haven't made any GID branches yet, so we're just on a default branch named master.
It can happen that we've made some new commits locally that we haven't pushed to the remote repository
yet.
In this case, the remote repository is not in sync with the local repo by using the git push command.
We can push the newly committed files to the remote repository.
Now that we've pushed a new data, any developer that has access to our remote repository can fetch
the latest changes that we just pushed.