When a new team member gets added to the project and should get access to all the data that's currently
hosted on the remote repository, that person can clone the repository in order to get all this data
on their local machines.
You can clone a repository with a git clone command followed by the SSH link of the remote repository.
So let's see how we can get that SSH link.
Each forum has a different UI and a different way to access the SSH link in order to clone the repository.
But in this case, let's just focus on the most popular platform GitHub.
When visiting the remote repository, you see a big green button with a text clone.
Once you click on that button, you see a flyout with the s h link that we need in order to clone the
repository.
We can now clone it locally on our machine with a git clone command followed by the ssh link that we
just copied.
By default, it will create a folder locally with the same name as the remote repository, which you
can see here.
Let's go into the folder that was just cloned with the CD command.
When we type get log, you can see that we have the entire Jets history of the project that we just
cloned.
We can now get started to work on this project locally and interact with the remote repository when
we've made changes in order for the entire team to stay up to date.