In the previous examples, we saw that we could merge branches directly into the master branch by first
checking out to master and then merging them.
When you're working with a team, however, you usually don't want to do this.
Instead, we can do all of this on a platform like GitHub.
In order to push the latest change to GitHub will push to the Origin Sierra branch by typing git push
origin Sierra.
After pushing to the Sarah branch and checking out the GitHub repo, you'll see a pop up that shows
that the master branch is now one commit behind the Sarah branch.
In order to merge Sara into master will have to open something called a pull request.
We can do that by clicking the pull request button in the top bar or the pull request button shown in
this pop up.
Once we've clicked on that button, you'll see the changes that were made to the Sarah branch compared
to the master branch and a button to create a pool request.
Let's create a pull request also called a PR.
We can add additional information about the changes that we've made, such as a title and a description,
maybe some important labels, or add specific reviewers for this pull request.
Now that the pool request has been opened, other team members can see the changes that you've made
and comment on them.
If everything has been approved, you can merge your changes into master by clicking the merge pull
request button.
Perfect.
Instead of checking out to master locally emerging it that way, we've just merged our changes into
master by creating a pull request emerging it on GitHub.
The origin Sara branch has now been merged into the Origin Master branch to make sure that not anyone
can just merge changes into the master branch.
You need to have the right privileges to do so.
This is the default if it's your own repo, but if you're working in a larger team, you may need to
ask other team members to merge the PR for you.