We just updated the Origin Master branch by merging Origin Sara into it.
Our local repository isn't automatically aware of these changes, so we'd have to get these changes
into a local repository.
We can do so with the git fetch command.
We can type git fetch master in order to update the origin master branch in our local repo.
Now that we fetched the origin master, we can update our local master branch to point to the latest
changes made on Origin Master.
To do that we can merge Origin Master into the local master branch.
Awesome.
We now have all the latest changes available locally.
Instead of individually fetching and then merging, we can also pool the Origin master branch with the
git pool command.
Git pool is actually two commands in one git fetch and get merge by typing git pool origin master.
We can fetch and merge the remote changes directly into our local master branch.
That's it.
For now.
It's time to gain some hands on practice.