In most cases get is smart enough to know how files should be modified when we're merging branches.
However, that's not always the case.
Imagine that Sarah started working on a fourth story.
But she didn't communicate this with Max.
So Max also started working on the fourth story.
Sarah was a bit quicker though, and Mercer changes back into Master.
Max now wants to go ahead and merge his change into Master as well.
But the master branch contains changes compared to the Max branch in a file that we're currently trying
to merge.
However, the file within Master says this is Sarah's version, whereas Max's version says this is Max's
version.
Get doesn't know which which version you want to keep and we just ended up in a merge conflict.
There are several ways to resolve those conflicts.
For example in get these or simply in the code editor during a conflict get add some extra characters
to the file.
That's conflicting.
Git shows the current context of the conflicting files as well as the contents that we're trying to
merge.
We can simply remove the lines that we don't want to keep and leave the lines that we do want to keep
and then save the file again.
During the conflict, we made some changes to the four storied TXT file which will have to add to get
again.
After adding it, we can finally merge the match branch without any conflicts.
Master now contains a combination of Max's and Sarah's changes.