So far, our examples used a small team of individuals working together.
Since it's a small team.
All members of the remote Git repository had the right permissions to push their changes right in.
However, this isn't always the case.
There are thousands of open source projects on GitHub with millions of contributors contributing to
them.
All of these contributors are not members of these projects with write permissions.
We don't want just anyone to be able to modify our code, of course.
So how do you create a pool request if you're not part of the get project and therefore not allowed
to create branches or push your changes right in?
One way to contribute to such projects is to first fork the main project.
After forking the project, you can add your changes to a branch on the fourth copy and send a pull
request to the original project to merge your changes right in.
When you forge a git repository, you're creating your own copy of the original project.
You're free to experiment with it and do whatever you want to do with the repository without impacting
the original project.
Once you think that you have something to contribute to the original project, you can create a pool
request safely.
The reviewers of the original project can now review the changes submitted by you and give feedback
to you if required.
Once your PR has been approved by the maintainers, they can merge your changes into the original repository.
You've now successfully contributed to an open source project.