All right, everybody, now that we understand what Jenkins files are, let's actually dive into some
hands on goodness and start to play around with some Jenkins files.
So first things first.
If you want to create a Jenkins file, at least in V's code, it's pretty straightforward.
Just create a new file and literally just type Jenkins file.
And as you can see, V's code knows that this is a Jenkins file, which is awesome.
So let me go ahead and I'm going to delete that.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to look at three separate Jenkins files.
Now, we will not be deploying them right now.
I just want to show you the structure and the overall basics.
And then in the next few videos, we're going to actually look at deploying these Jenkins files.
So first things first, I'm going to click on the Jenkins file test.
I'm going to open up this Jenkins file.
Now, this is a very straightforward Helloworld Jenkins file.
As we can see, we're first set up with our pipeline structure.
And our pipeline structure has an opening bracket and it has a closing bracket.
And inside of that opening and closing bracket, like, for example, if I just take this out really
quick, we can see that I'm specifying the agent and the agent.
Again, we're going to talk about build agents in the next section.
But this could be anything, any type of system that's running Java.
I'm saying any here at this point.
And what that's going to do is it's actually going to run the current Jenkins server as the build agent.
Next, we have our stages that are set up now, our stage.
We could have any type of stage that we want.
Dev, UAT, prod, we can name it whatever we want.
If we want to be a little bit more flush with our names here, we can go out and we can name this dev
and then the dev stage is going to deploy some steps.
Now the steps are inside of these brackets here and what this step is doing, it's very straightforward.
It's running an echo, which just means it's just going to say something back to us, say something
to the terminal that's going to say Hello world.
And just like that, you could have your first pipeline set up very, very straightforward.
Next, let's break into something a little bit more complicated here.
Go ahead.
I'm going to close out of this Jenkins file and then I'm going to open up go app one stage, this directory
here.
Then I'm going to click on this Jenkins file.
Now, notice it's pretty much set up the same.
We have our pipeline structure.
We have our agent that we're calling upon.
We have our stages and then we have our step.
Now, here's the thing that's actually happening.
We're pulling code from GitHub now.
So now what this is doing is this is taking code from GitHub and it's building it for us inside of this
pipeline.
It's taking this code, it's pulling it from GitHub, and now we'll have that code readily available
to start working on to be able to do things like run tests, for example.
And then finally, if we just look into one more thing here, we looked at one stage, let's look at
multi stage.
Remember we talked about multi stage a little bit already.
So as you can see, again, same thing.
We have our pipeline structure set up where designing this to say use any agent and then we have two
stages.
Now this is where things are a little bit different inside of our stages.
BLOCK We have two stage keywords, and then within those two stage keywords, we have two different
stages.
We have one called dev on line five, and then we have one called UAT on line 12.
Now within each of those stages, within the dev stage and then within the UAT stage, we have steps.
And both of these steps are doing the same thing.
This isn't meant to be, you know, a crazy, hardcore advanced example here.
This is really just a show how a multi stage pipeline would work.
And realistically, this actually does make sense because remember, when you're running multi stage
pipelines, you're not necessarily looking to do different things at each stage.
You're really looking to do practically the same thing.
You want to be able to build the code and you want to be able to test the code and push that code out
and all of that good stuff.
So if you're looking to set up multi stage pipelines, this is the way that it would look.
You would have inside of your stages bracket, you would have two or three or however many stage keywords.
Within those stage keywords you would have what stage like Dev or UAT.
And then within there you would have your steps.
Now remember, just going back one more time, if you want one stage, this is what it looks like.
Again, you have your stages bracket, you have your stage keyword, but you're just setting up one
stage.
So with that, now let's head over to the Jenkins portal and we can actually start building out some
code.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.