Before we build out our pipeline, like our actual one that's going to go ahead and push out our go
app and build it and all that good stuff.
I do want to just show you how to set up a sample pipeline.
I think that this definitely helps if you understand the process and just do a sample versus going full
fledged 100% into a brand new pipeline that you're not really aware of.
So what I want to do is let's just go ahead and just set up what a pipeline typically looks like.
So I'm in the dashboard here for Jenkins, and what I'm going to do is I'm going to click on new item
and I'm going to give this a name.
I'm just going to call it test for.
Then at this point, I have a few different options here and let's kind of look at these and see what
these actually mean.
So first is a freestyle project and this is a central feature of Jenkins, so it will build the project,
it'll combine any scheme, any build system, and it could even be used for something other than building
software.
He doesn't have to be an application.
Now pipeline, which is probably what we'll be living in, more or less.
This is actually to create a pipeline.
And we're going to see that in just a second.
That's the one we're going to use.
Then we have a multi configuration project, which is great if you need a large number of Jenkins configurations,
if you're setting up on multiple environments, for example, this might even be good for multi stage
pipelines.
So let's say you got a dev on stage and maybe your dev stage, you're deploying it to some really cheap
environment and then your UAT stage, you're deploying it to more of what it's going to look like in
production.
Next you have a folder option and this creates a container and then stores nested items inside of it.
And it's great if you want to group different projects together, filter those, all of that good stuff.
Next you have Multi branch Pipeline, which we're going to see a little bit in this section as well.
And what that does is it sets up a pipeline project for different repository, so like different GitHub
repositories and stuff like that.
And then you have an organization folder and that just creates a multi branch project for all of your
different sub folders that are available.
So let's go ahead and choose Pipeline.
We'll click okay here.
Okay, so now we have a bunch of different options.
Let's just go ahead and go over these options.
So all these times here, you could just see if I click on them, it just goes down.
So what I'm going to do is I'm just going to start at the top and we'll work our way down here.
So first things first, we have a description and we can give this description here, for example.
Deploy our sample pipeline to test out Jenkins.
And this could be really anything you want, but obviously you want the description to make sense to
what you're doing.
So now we have a few different options here.
First, discard old builds.
What that really means is it's not going to hold on to the build for like a year, for example.
There's really no reason for that unless you absolutely need it.
I typically say to hold on to builds for like.
You know, a few weeks.
I think that makes the most sense.
But really, other than that, you're never going to actually come and look at them unless you're troubleshooting
something.
But if you're troubleshooting something, you're looking at the bills anyways.
And then we have another option to not allow concurrent builds, which means builds wouldn't be able
to run at the same time.
Now, this option doesn't make sense really, because depending on how large your environment is, you're
probably going to have multiple teams using Jenkins.
And because of that, you're definitely going to want to be able to build multiple times or at the same
time, rather.
The next option here is do not allow the pipeline to resume if the controller restarts.
So if the controller like the Jenkins server restarts, this is saying don't resume the pipeline that
was running while the restart occurred.
Next you have GitHub project here, which if you click on that, it allows you to put in the project
URL, pipeline speed, durability override preserve stashes from completed builds.
This project is parameterized, so it allows you to prompt users for one or more inputs.
Think of it like if you have to pass in a variable or something like that, this is a great way to do
that.
And then throttle builds.
And what this does is this for enforces a minimum time between builds based on the desired rate.
So this is really good.
If you have some slow systems, for example, or you're maybe working on scaling out at the moment,
but you don't exactly like have that set up just yet.
This would be good for that.
It just kind of just slows down the workload.
But the good thing is this is not the same as do not allow concurrent builds the throttle build.
It'll allow concurrent build so you can run as many as you want, but it'll just kind of slow it down
a little bit.
And again, this is good if you don't have the proper resource or the proper build agents to be able
to run all of your builds whenever you feel like it.
He next scrolling down, we have a few build triggers, so build after the other projects are built.
This is kind of like throttling.
Throttling builds almost build periodically.
Which is like a cron job almost.
So, like, you know, run my build every day at 2 a.m., for example.
GitHub hook trigger for get SQM polling.
Which is just a GitHub push hook.
Pull scheme, disable this project so if you don't want it to run at all.
Quiet period.
So what this means is the builds will be triggered, but it will be added to a queue and then trigger
builds remotely.
If you want to be able to trigger this from a predefined URL from another location.
He then we have some advanced project options, which it's actually nothing in here by default, really,
it's just the display name.
And then you have the actual pipeline.
So for example, we can click on Hello World and it'll go out.
Hello World, There is a GitHub plus Maven example here and then there is a scripted pipeline example.
This is actually pretty interesting, this build stage here.
It's actually just running a whole bunch of batch code.
So we'll just go ahead and we'll choose.
Hello world.
Let's keep it real basic for our first one and then use groovy sandbox.
And if you're not familiar with Groovy, essentially what it is is kind of like a scripting language,
like a programming language almost.
I think it actually defines itself as a programming language.
So if we just go back here, we can see Groovy is a very powerful language which offers the ability
to do practically anything Java can do.
So kind of think about it like an extension of Java almost.
But if you want to dive into Groovy a little bit more, definitely recommend this page right here.
But really think about it like a Java extender almost for Jenkins.
So now I'm going to click Save.
And then we are at the point where we can build our code if we want to.
So what I can do is I can click build now.
And then it says build scheduled.
So as we can see here, the build ran successfully and ran for about a second here and we can see that
the build was hello, That was the stage view.
Now let's say we want to change something up a little bit here.
If I go to configure, I'm now back at that location where I had all these options and if I scroll down
here, I can go to stage and maybe we want to name this Dev.
Let's go ahead and let's save that.
Let's do build now.
And then as you can see, the build now ran again.
But the stage is different.
It's called dev.
And then we can see here, Ock, our stage name has changed.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.