Going off of where we just were.
Let's go ahead and go back to configure.
Now, I'm going to scroll down here and what I want to do is I want to create a new stage.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to copy this.
And then I'm actually going to just paste that in here.
And then we'll do is we'll change this to UAT.
So if you've guessed it by now, you are correct.
Yes.
We just created a multi stage pipeline.
Very straightforward.
Of course, the step is just echoing Hello World.
But I do just want to show this in action here.
So if I click on Save and then I click on Build now.
We can see that we have now two stages here.
We have one stage called Dev, and then we have another stage called UAT.
So when we build our multi stage pipelines, we'll have the ability to see both right here.
And we could also even see that this was the third build that was run.
But if we look at the second one, there was no UAT stage yet.
However, the history of the one just dev running is still here, which is great.
So we can see the history of even when it changed from single to multi stage.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.