All right, everybody.
Now that we know how to build a sample pipeline, we know all of the options available.
Let's actually dive in and build our code and test it for the first time.
So the first thing that we're going to do is we're going to go to manage Jenkins.
And then I'm going to go to manage plugins.
Now, I actually already have this plugin installed, but you will need to go ahead and you will need
to install it yourself.
So search for go.
And as you can see, I have this go plug in here, but you can just go to available search for go and
you should see a pop up.
You're just not seeing it here because I already have it installed.
Now, once you have that, you're going to have to restart Jenkins.
So go ahead, restart Jenkins and then come on back.
All right.
Now, once you're back, let's go ahead and start configuring our pipeline.
So first things first, we're going to type pipeline and we're going to go in and we're going to use
our brackets here.
Now we're going to use Agent Annie because we haven't set up our new build agent yet, which is again,
is perfectly fine.
We will get there, I promise.
And then we're going to type tools, new opening, closing bracket, and then we're going to type go
for go line, and then we'll do go hyphen 1.17.
Now, this is the latest in terms of when I'm recording this course right here, but it may be different
for you.
If you have a newer version, feel free to pop that one in.
Okay.
Next, what we're going to do is we're going to set up our environment.
So we're going to type environment.
Now we're going to type go 111 module equals on.
Now, if you're not familiar with this, essentially what this means is you can install the latest version
of some code base from, say, GitHub, for example.
Okay.
Now, next, we're going to set up our stages.
So let's go ahead and set up our stages here.
We're going to type stage and we're going to type test in here because our first stage will be our tests.
And what do I mean by that?
What I mean is we're going to be running some unit tests on our code.
So I'm going to type in steps.
And then our first step is going to be to bring down the code very much like we did right here.
We're going to literally paste that same thing in there, and then we're going to run a shell command
and we're going to say, Go test, dot, dot, dot, dot.
What this means is it looks at the current directory and all of the subdirectories and runs every test
that's available.
So with that, I'm going to go ahead and copy this.
We're going to head back over to Jenkins.
And then now let's go to Dashboard new item.
We'll call this go three.
We'll click on Pipeline, Click select here.
And then we'll go ahead, we'll scroll down to Pipeline and we'll pop our pipeline in.
So again, what this is doing is it's using GO version 1.17.
We're ensuring that the go 111 module is on.
We are setting up a one stage for running our unit test.
So let's go ahead and let's save that.
Let's click build now.
And hopefully our code will build successfully.
Okay.
And as we can see, our code finish testing successfully.
We can go ahead and we can take a look at the logs here.
We can see our shell script and we can see that there are no test files in these repositories.
But in the controller repository here, we can see that there were tests and they all pass successfully.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.