All right, everybody, now that we know the proper PSI process and how to build our code using Jenkins,
let's go ahead and learn the CI CD process, as in let's go ahead and build our code.
Bring it down from GitHub and create a Docker image.
So you're going to notice here that our Jenkins file is pretty similar.
How is the same pipeline structure using the same tools, the same environment variable?
Even that development stage is still the same where we're bringing down the go code.
Now really the biggest difference is on line 19 here where we have a new stage called Building Our Image.
Now we're using this command from the Docker plugin and I'm going to show you how to get that in just
a second here.
But what this is doing is it's going to be building a Docker image based on the code that we're bringing
down on line 14.
So let's go ahead and head over to our Jenkins instance and we're going to go ahead and we're going
to run this Jenkins file.
All right.
So I'm here at Jenkins.
And what I'm going to do first is I'm going to go to manage Jenkins and I'm going to go to manage plugins.
Now, if I go to install here, I'm going to do is I'm just going to search Docker.
You're going to see a few that I have here, the Docker API plug in the Docker Commons, plug in the
Docker pipeline, plug in, and then the Docker plugin.
You're going to want to ensure that you have all of those installed and you're going to want to ensure
that you have Docker installed on your build server, which in this case is just the Jenkins server.
So let's go ahead and go back to Jenkins.
We're going to go to new item.
We're going to give this a name.
Now I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to click Pipeline.
Click.
Okay, Scroll down to my pipeline script.
I'm going to paste in what I just showed everybody on Vee's code.
Notice here how it's the exact same.
Let me go ahead and I'm going to click Save.
I'm going to click Build now.
And now our pipeline is going to officially kick off and we have our few stages here.
We can see our development stage and our building, our image stage and as you can see, it is already
complete.
It's probably going to be a little bit longer for you because you probably don't have the go Docker
image installed locally.
And because I was testing this out already, I already have that.
So if you notice that's taken a little bit longer, that's perfectly normal.
But if I click on our build here and I click on our console output, we can see that our code was brought
down and then we can see that our Docker image was successfully built.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.