In the previous video So far, you've seen how to test your code, how to pull it down from GitHub,
how to build it.
But we haven't exactly seen what it looks like to fully run the code.
So what we're going to do right here is I'm actually going to take out line 22.
And what we're going to do is we're going to have three stages.
The first is going to be the test.
Second is going to be build.
Actually, this should be just build here.
And then the third stage is run.
So this test stage and the build stage, we've kind of already seen that where we built our code, really
where we want to focus is the run stage.
So on line 24 here.
Notice how I have this directory.
Now, by default, all pipelines are under this workspace directory.
And then what I'm doing is I'm actually calling upon the Go web app sample build and that build actually
gets there by line 21 here.
So without line 21, this build wouldn't exist.
But because we're ultimately able to build our code and it all goes to the same place, we're then able
to call upon our go binary here.
So what I'm going to do is go ahead and I'm going to copy this.
We're going to head over to the Web browser.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to go into my pipeline right here.
And this pipeline is already created.
So go ahead and just create this pipeline.
Just call it go full pipeline.
If you call it something else, just keep in mind that you will have to change the name here on line
26.
Now, that's the name of my pipeline.
So I was able to get this going.
Next, I'm going to go to configure here and this is just going to be a standard build pipeline.
And then what I'm going to do is I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to run our pipeline now.
So go ahead and I'll build this.
And we'll click on our 18 build here.
As you can see, I've been playing around with this a little bit.
Now I'm going to go to my console output.
Now let's take a look at what's actually happening here.
First, I'm running my tests and as you can see, a lot of these directories don't have tests, but
the controller directory does.
And these tests ran.
They were all good and passed successfully, which is great.
Next, we're going to scroll down here.
We see our build process occurring.
Scroll down a little bit more and we can see here that our pipeline did in fact finish successfully.
So I'm going to go here and I'm just going to take my IP address of my Jenkins host.
Pop that in.
And as we can see, our application is up and running over Port 8000.
Now, one thing that I do just want to point out, I'm not sure why this occurs, but it says go web
app sample not found.
I actually even saw this on, for example, if I go to one of my previous builds that finished successfully.
If I just go to the console output here and I scroll down, notice how it does say the same thing,
but the application is in fact running successfully.
It's time for some hands on practice.