Let's start with how application delivery works in a traditional infrastructure model and how it evolved
with the emergence of technologies such as cloud computing and infrastructure as code.
Let's go back in time and look at how infrastructure was provisioned in the traditional I.T. model.
Let us consider an organization that wants to roll out a new application.
The business comes up with the requirements for the application.
The business analyst then gathers the needs from the business, analyzes it, and converts it into a
set of high level technical requirements.
This is then passed on to a solution architect.
The solution.
Architect then designs the architecture to be followed for the deployment of this application.
This would typically include the infrastructure considerations, such as the type, spec and amount
of servers that are needed, such as those for front end web servers, back end servers, databases,
load balancers, etc..
Following the traditional infrastructure model, these would have to be deployed in the organization's
on premise environment, which would mean making use of the assets in the data center.
If additional hardware is needed, they would have to be ordered via the procurement team.
This team will put in a new hardware request with the vendors.
It can then take anywhere between a few days to weeks or even months for the hardware to be purchased
and delivered to the data center.
Once received at the data center, the field engineers would be in charge of rack and stack of the equipment.
The system administrators perform initial configurations and the network administrators make the systems
available on the network.
The storage admins assigned storage to these servers and the backup admins configure backups.
And finally, once the systems have been set up, as per the standards, they can then be handed over
to the application teams to deploy their applications.
This deployment model, which is still quite commonly used today, has quite a few disadvantages.
The turnover time can range between weeks to months, and that's just to get the systems in a ready
state to begin the application deployment.
This includes the time it takes for the system to be initially procured and then handed over between
teams.
Also, scaling up or scaling down the infrastructure on demand cannot be achieved quickly.
The overall cost to deploy and maintain this model is generally quite high.
While some aspects of the infrastructure provisioning process can be automated, several steps, such
as the rack and stack cabling and other deployment procedures are manual and slow.
With so many teams working on so many different tasks, chances of human error are high and this results
in inconsistent environments.
And at the major disadvantage of using this model is the underutilization of the compute resources.
The infrastructure sizing activity is generally carried out well in advance and the servers are sized
considering the peak utilization.
The inability to scale up or down easily means that most of these resources would not be used during
off peak hours.
In the past decade or so, organisations have been moving to virtualisation and cloud platforms to take
advantages of services provided by major cloud providers such as Amazon, AWS, Microsoft Azure, Google
Cloud Platform, etc..
By moving to cloud the time to spin up the infrastructure and the time to market for applications are
significantly reduced.
This is because with cloud you do not have to invest in or manage the actual hardware assets that you
normally would in case of a traditional infrastructure model.
The data center, the hardware assets and the services are managed by the cloud provider.
A virtual machine can be spun up in a cloud environment in a matter of minutes, and the time to market
is reduced from several months, as in the case of a traditional infrastructure, two weeks in a cloud
environment.
And infrastructure costs are reduced when compared with the additional data center management and human
resources cost.
Cloud infrastructure comes with support for APIs, and that opens up a whole new world of opportunity
for automation.
And finally, the built in auto scaling and elastic functionality of cloud infrastructure reduces resource
wastage.
With virtualisation and cloud, you could now provision infrastructure with a few clicks.
While this approach is certainly faster and more efficient when compared to the traditional deployment
methods, using the management console for resource provisioning is not always the ideal solution.
It is okay to have this approach when we are dealing with limited number of resources, but in a large
organisation with elastic and highly scalable cloud environment with immutable infrastructure, this
approach is not feasible.
Once provisioned, the systems still have to go through different teams with a lot of process overhead.
That increases the delivery time and the chances of human error are still at large, resulting in inconsistent
environments.
So different organizations started solving these challenges within themselves by developing their own
scripts and tools.
While some use simple shell scripts, others use programming languages such as Python, Ruby, Perl
or PowerShell.
Everyone was solving the same problems, trying to automate infrastructure, provisioning to deploy
environments faster and in a consistent fashion by leveraging the API functionalities of the various
cloud environments.
These evolved into a set of tools that came to be known as infrastructure as code.
In the next lecture, we will see what infrastructure as code is in more detail.