In this lecture, we will get introduced to infrastructure as code, which is commonly known as IAC.
We will also take a look at commonly used IAC tools.
So earlier we discussed about provisioning by making use of the management console of various cloud
providers.
The better way to provision cloud infrastructure is to codify the entire provisioning process.
This way we can write an execute code to define provision, configure, update and eventually destroy
infrastructure resources.
This is called as infrastructure as a code or IAC.
With infrastructure as code, you can manage nearly any infrastructure component as code such as databases,
networks, storage, or even application configuration.
The code you see here is a shell script.
However, it is not easy to manage it.
It requires programming or development skills to build and maintain.
There's a lot of logic that you will need to code and it is not easily reusable.
And that's where tools like TerraForm and Ansible help.
That code that is easy to learn is human readable and maintain.
A large shell script can now be converted into a simple TerraForm configuration file like this.
With infrastructure as code, we can define infrastructure resources using simple, human readable,
high level language.
Here is another example where we will be making use of Ansible to provision three AWS EC two instances
making use of a specific army.
Although Ansible and perform are easy tools, they have some key differences in what they are trying
to achieve and as a result they have some very different use cases.
You will see these differences next.
There are several different tools.
Part of the infrastructure as code family, Ansible, TerraForm, puppet, cloud formation, Packer,
salt stack, Vagrant, Docker, etc..
Although you can possibly make use of any of these tools to design similar solutions, they have all
been created to address a very specific goal.
With that in mind, I can be broadly classified into three types.
Configuration management Ansible puppet salt stack fall into this category.
Tools used for server templating, Docker Packer and Vagrant fall into this category.
And finally, we have infrastructure provisioning tools such as TerraForm and Cloud formation.
Let's look at these in a bit more detail.
The first type of IAC tool that we are going to take a look at is configuration management tools.
These include tools like Ansible, Chef, Puppet and Salt Stack.
And these are commonly used to install and manage software on existing infrastructure resources such
as servers, databases, networking devices, etc..
Unlike the ad hoc shell scripts that we saw earlier, configuration management tools maintain a consistent
and standard structure of code, and this makes it easier to manage and update it as needed.
They're also designed to run on multiple remote resources at once.
An Ansible playbook or a rule can be checked into a version control repository.
This allows us to reuse and distribute it as needed.
However, perhaps the most important feature of a configuration management tool is that they are important.
This means that you can run the code multiple times and every time you run it, it will only make changes
that are necessary to bring the environment into a defined state.
It would leave anything already in place as it is without us having to write any additional code.
Next, let's look at server templating tools.
These are tools like Docker, Vagrant and Packer from Hashicorp that can be used to create a custom
image of a virtual machine or a container.
These images already contain all the required software and dependencies installed on them.
And for the most part, this eliminates the need of installing software after a VM or a container is
deployed.
The most common examples for server templated images are VM images such as those that are offered on
OS boxes.
Dot org.
Custom images in Amazon, AWS and Docker images on Docker Hub and other container registries.
Server Templating tools also promote immutable infrastructure, unlike configuration management tools.
This means that once the VM or a container is deployed, it is designed to remain unchanged.
If there are changes to be made to the image instead of updating the running instance, like in the
case of configuration management tools such as Ansible, we update the image and then redeploy a new
instance using the updated image.
We have a section on immutable infrastructure later in this course where we look at it in much more
detail.
The last type of IAC tool which is specifically of interest for this course is provisioning tools.
These tools are used to provision infrastructure components using a simple declarative code.
These infrastructure components can range from servers such as virtual machines, databases, VPC,
subnets, security groups, storage, and just about any service based on the provider we choose.
While cloud formation is specifically used to deploy services in AWS, TerraForm is vendor agnostic
and supports provider plugins for almost all major cloud providers.
In the upcoming lecture, we will see how TerraForm helps in provisioning infrastructure.