Let's now talk about TerraForm and go over some of its features at a high level.
As we discussed, the reform is a popular ESI tool, which is specifically useful as an infrastructure
provisioning tool.
TerraForm is a free and open source tool which is developed by Hashicorp.
It installs as a single binary, which can be set up very quickly, allowing us to build, manage and
destroy infrastructure in a matter of minutes.
One of the biggest advantages of TerraForm is its ability to deploy infrastructure across multiple platforms,
including private and public cloud, such as on premise vSphere cluster or Cloud solutions such as AWS,
GCP or Azure to name a few.
These are just a few of the many resources that are from can manage.
So how does TerraForm manage infrastructure on so many different kinds of platforms?
This is achieved through providers.
A provider helps TerraForm manage third party platforms through their API.
Providers enabled TerraForm managed cloud platforms like AWS, GCP or Azure.
As we have just seen, as well as network infrastructure like big IP, Cloudflare DNS, Palo Alto Networks
and info blocks, as well as monitoring and data management tools like Datadog or Xero, Wavefront and
Sumo Logic databases like Influx, DB, MongoDB, my SQL, PostgreSQL and version control systems like
GitHub, Bitbucket or GitLab.
TerraForm supports hundreds of such providers and as a result can work with almost every infrastructure
platform.
TerraForm uses SQL, which stands for Hashicorp Configuration Language, which is a simple declarative
language to define the infrastructure resources to be provisioned as blocks of code.
All infrastructure resources can be defined within configuration files that has a dot DF file extension.
The configuration syntax is easy to read and write and pick up for a beginner.
The sample code is used to provision a new EQ to instance on the cloud.
This code is declarative and can be maintained in a version control system, allowing it to be distributed
to other teams.
We cover the syntax in more detail later in this course.
We also have lots of hands on labs where you will be practicing working with these files and gain a
lot of experience by the end of this course.
So we said that the code is declarative.
But what does declarative mean?
The code we define is the state that we want our infrastructure to be in.
That's the desired state.
And this on the right is the current state where there's nothing.
TerraForm will take care of what is required to go from the current state to the desired state without
us having to worry about how to get there.
So how does TerraForm do that?
Perform works in three phases in IT plan and apply during the init phase.
TerraForm initializes the project and identifies the providers to be used for the target environment.
During the plan phase TerraForm drafts a plan to get to the target state and then in the upload phase.
TerraForm makes the necessary changes required on the target environment to bring it to the desired
state.
If for some reason the environment was to shift from the desired state, then a subsequent TerraForm
apply will bring it back to the desired state by only fixing the missing component.
Every object data for manages is called a resource.
A resource can be a compute instance, a database server in the cloud or on a physical server on premise
that therefore manages.
Therefore manages the lifecycle of resources from its provisioning to configuration to decommissioning.
TerraForm records the state of the infrastructure as it is seen in the real world.
And based on this, it can determine what actions to take when updating resources for a particular platform.
TerraForm can ensure that the entire infrastructure is always in the defined state at all times.
The state is a blueprint of the infrastructure deployed by TerraForm.
TerraForm can read attributes of existing infrastructure components by configuring data sources.
This can lead to be used for configuring other resources within TerraForm.
TerraForm can also import other resources outside of TerraForm that were either created manually or
by the means of other ESI tools and bring it under its control so that it can manage those resources
going forward.
Perform cloud entry form enterprise provide additional features that allow simplified collaboration
between teams, managing infrastructure, improved security and a centralized UI to manage TerraForm
deployments.
All these features make TerraForm an excellent enterprise grade infrastructure provisioning tool.
Well, that was a quick introduction to TerraForm at a high level.
So let's dive in and explore all of these in much more detail in the upcoming lectures.