In this section, we will look into the basics of applications.
As we have been discussing, DevOps engineer must be comfortable with operations as well as software
development concepts.
When I say development, I'm not referring to hard core coding skills or programming.
Instead, I am referring to understanding the basics of application development in different types of
languages.
And if you were given an application to deploy, how do you deploy it?
So this section is mainly for those who are from a non development background, and it will provide
you with some basics of the different kinds of programming languages and how software is developed using
those and how they are built and how they can be deployed.
And how to perform some basic troubleshooting tasks.
And of course, each of these lectures are followed by labs where you'll be given an application source
code and you'll build and deploy the application.
We will also talk a little bit about how an application is compiled and what a source code or machine
code is.
I promise without getting into too much detail, but I think it will help you relate the concepts later
when you work on builds.
So the goal of this section is not to discuss all of the programming languages and the hundreds of libraries
and build tools they support.
Instead, it is to simply get a high level overview of the various the most commonly used applications
so that when you attend a DevOps or cloud course on, say, Docker and the instructor gives you an application
to modernize and containerized, you know what they are talking about, you know, the different steps
involved in that and you should be able to relate those with what you learn in this section.
So keeping that in mind, let's proceed.
There are so many different programming languages out there today, and we're going to pick a few of
the most popular and commonly used languages for this.
I checked Stack overflows.
Insights from their 2019 survey and looked at the top programming, scripting or markup languages.
From this, we filter out the databases, scripting and markup languages, so we are left with this.
JavaScript, Python, Java seem to be the top three.
So we're going to go ahead with that.
For JavaScript, we will use the Node.js framework for server side.
The different programming languages can be broadly classified into compiled or interpreted.
Now, I'm not going to get into describing each of these in detail or which one is better than the other.
Our goal here is to understand the high level difference between these languages and what you need to
know from a DevOps perspective.
That is, if a developer gives you an application code, what do you need to know in order to build,
test or deploy this application?
So I'm going to try and simplify this as much as I can.
Compiled languages such as Java C or C++, or first developed, then compiled and then executed, whereas
interpreted languages are developed and executed.
Compiled languages are first written, then compiled into machine language and then executed.
A compiled program only works on the platform it was designed for in a compiled programming language
such as Java.
The application source code is first developed and it is compiled and then run.
So here we have a simple code in file My class Java, which is then compiled using the Java Sea Command
and specifying the name of the code.
This creates a new file which is by the name my Class class, which is the compiled version of the source
code.
And then we run the application by running the compiled file using the Java Command.
Of course, this is the most simplest form.
We will discuss a lot more about Java later in this course.
In an interpreted programming language, you develop the source code, then you run it using an interpreter.
In this case, we have a simple python application.
We develop it first and then run it using the python interpreter.
But remember, that doesn't mean that it is in compiled at all.
When the program is run, it is implicitly compiled into a byte code and then run.
Hmm.
So I said, Bytecode.
So what's that and why do you need that?
What you see here is the source code of an application, a human readable source code that developers
write.
We want a machine that is our laptop to run this and perform the tasks we ask it to perform.
However, a machine can't understand this code in its current format, so we need to convert this code
into a machine code that is readable by machine that is in zeros and ones.
And that's where a compiler comes in.
A compiler translates code written in one language to another language.
In this case, it translates code from a human readable format in Python into a machine readable ones
and zeros.
That's the most simplified explanation, but it's not really that simple.
So there are a few more steps involved before you can get a source code to be converted to a machine
code and then run on a machine.
And it's done differently in different programming languages.
Say, for instance, if this application was developed on a specific machine with a specific processor
set and we compiled the source code into machine code like this, it would generate a machine code that
is only compatible with similar systems.
It wouldn't work on other systems with different CPU configuration.
So in the past you had to compile the same application on different kinds of systems and generate different
bills to get them to run on all systems.
And that's why the modern compilers do not compile the code directly into machine code.
Instead, it is first converted to an intermediate form called as byte code.
It's usually a file named with the extension p c in Python.
This byte code is then used by the python interpreter to convert to machine code and then execute the
program.
The Python interpreter runs the byte code in an environment called as a virtual machine.
These are not VMs that we refer to in the infrastructure space.
The Python virtual machine is just a virtual computing environment inside which the byte code is executed,
and that's really where our source code gets converted to machine code.
So now with Python VM, we don't really have to compile our application on different machines to generate
different machine codes.
As long as you have the python VM available on a system, our application can run.
And remember all of that happens in the background when you run the application using the python command.
So that's a quick introduction about the different types of programming languages we will be discussing
in this section.
We will talk more about each of these programming languages along with Hands on Labs later in the upcoming
lectures.
But before that, let's talk about packages a bit.
Now, when a developer develops code that can be reused, they share it to the community as packages
that can be reused.
So they are also referred to as modules or libraries, depending on the programming language being used.
These could be libraries to help work with file systems, perform math operations, interact with operating
systems or packages for development, developing different kinds of applications like web servers,
implementing security, networking, etc. Applications use these packages in their code as dependencies,
and so these dependencies must be available for the applications to run.
These dependencies are handled by different tools for different programming languages such as NPM,
for Node.js, PIPP for Python, etc..
While getting into the world of DevOps, understanding the basics of package management can help you
better understand build processes and aid in troubleshooting issues that may arise due to dependency
errors.
We will look at these as well for each programming language in the respective lecture.
Talking about build.
When an application is coded, it goes through a procedure of development, build, test and delivery.
DevOps courses talk extensively about automating these tasks with CI CD pipelines, and before learning
how to automate these tasks, it is important to know what to automate and have a basic understanding
of a software development lifecycle.
Now, I don't intend to bore you with theories on the different software development models.
Instead, we're going to go straight to labs and get a first hand experience of deploying an e commerce
application.
So first we're going to go through the different types of applications like Python, Java, Node.js.
We'll also look at some basic basics of web servers like Apache Web server and an engine X.
And then we'll also look at databases.
And then finally, we're going to look at working through an application and see the entire process
of the software development lifecycle that involves all of these different steps.
And we will see that in action and you will do that yourself in our labs.
So that's it from this lecture.
In the next lecture, we're going to talk about Java.
So I'll see you there.