In this section, we will look into the basics of Java.
Java, as you know, has been one of the most popular programming languages widely used for building
desktop, mobile and web applications.
It is free and open source and has a huge community following and support.
The latest version of Java as of this recording is version 13, and these are some of the previous versions
and the year they came out.
In your work environment, you might find a lot of applications dependent on different versions of Java,
and it's not unlikely to see a lot of organizations stuck at version eight.
Version nine introduced changes that made many popular tools and libraries incompatible at the time
of the release, which prevented many companies from upgrading their infrastructure.
So these, along with some of the changes in licensing terms, resulted in many applications being stuck
at version eight of Java.
You may download and install Java on your platform from the Oracle website on Linux machines like Central
West, which we will be using in our lab.
Download the Java build and using a utility like we get and extract it to a directory.
The bin directory within the extracted folder has all the java binary files.
To check if java is installed on a machine or to check the version of Java.
Run the Java command with the version option.
As you can see, the current version is 13 .0.2.
Now, it's important to note that older versions of Java before version eight also referred to the version
numbers as 1.8 instead of just eight.
So that was the original version naming scheme in the past.
So this changed with version nine.
So don't get confused with the two types of version names up until version eight.
It was known as 1.5, 1.6, 1.7 and 1.8.
But from version nine onwards it changed to nine, ten, 11, 12, 13, etc..
Now.
We thought we were talking about Java, but what's all the JDK that we see here?
So the release page says JDK availability.
The downloaded files are named JDK.
The version says Open JDK.
So what's what's a JDK?
JDK stands for Java Development Kit.
It is a set of tools that will help you develop, build and run Java applications on a system.
So you don't really install just Java.
You install a kit or a set of tools that helps to all three to develop a Java application.
You can really just use any text editor to write the code, but once you do to debug your application,
you have the Java debugger tool to document your application source code.
You have the Java doc tool.
Once the source code is developed to build and compile your application, you have the Java Sea tool
and the JAR Tool helps archive the code and related libraries into a single jar file.
Now we will talk more about how this build process works and see it in action in the upcoming lectures.
Once built to run the Java application, you need the Java runtime environment.
A Java runtime environment is needed to run a Java application on any given system.
In fact, that's the only component you need to simply run a build Java application on any system.
And of course, you also need the Java command line utility or the loader that is used to run the application.
So all of these and many other tools together form the Java development kit.
So these tools are commands available in the bin directory.
When you install Java and what we have listed here are just a few of the many tools included within
the JDK.
It's important to note that in the past, before version nine of Java, JDK and Java were shipped as
separate components.
So back then you could install these components individually.
And so if you were not really developing a Java application and just wanted to run an existing, fully
built application, you could simply just install the Java runtime environment alone and run the application.
You would see separate directories of installation for each of these.
From version nine onwards, both JDK and GRC are packaged together into a single Java development kit
package.
So when you install JDK, you will install all tools as well as the Java runtime environment.
Well, we will now head over to the labs and our practice working with.
Java.
So you'll basically be having multiple systems and you'll install Java.
You'll explore the different versions of Java.
You'll run basic Java programs.
And in the next lecture, we'll continue with builds in Java.