We will now look at building a Java application.
In this lecture, we'll talk about building a Java application.
So let's start with a build process in its simplest form.
So here's a sample Java application.
The application source code is first developed, then it is compiled and then run.
So here we have a simple code in the file.
My class Java, which is then compiled using the Java Sea Command by specifying the name of the code
file.
This creates a new file, which is then which is the compiled version.
We then run the application by running the compiled file using the Java loader.
But note that you do not specify the class extension when running the application using the Java Command.
What you're specifying here is essentially the class name, which happens to be my class if you look
here at the top.
So our objective is to convert the human readable code into machine code, as in Python.
The source code is first compiled from a human readable form into a byte code, except that here we
compile it manually using the Java Sea Command.
The bytecode is then run inside of Java virtual machines known as VMS.
Again, these are not the same VMs that we refer to in the infrastructure space.
These are Java virtual computing environments that exist within the system.
So this allows us to develop Java applications once and run them anywhere.
Anywhere where there is a supported gvm available.
So this truly makes Java Cross platform.
You can develop your code once and compile it and then run it anywhere on any operating system.
So that was compiling just one file.
But a typical application may have many such files.
They may be dependent on each other or may have dependencies on external libraries To distribute the
application to end users, we need to package it up.
And that's where an archive like JAR can help.
JAR stands for Java Archive and it helps compress and combine multiple Java class files and dependent
libraries and assets into a single distributable package.
If, in case of a web application, there may be other files such as static files and images that may
be part of the application.
In that case, all files are packaged into a VAR file, which stands for Web Archive.
So to create an archive, use the JAR Command and specify the name of the output file, in this case
my app jar, and then passing the list of files that need to be part of the archive.
Running this command generates the my AB jar output file.
When this file is created, it automatically generates a manifest file within the package at path meta
inf slash manifest mf.
This file contains information about the files packaged in the jar file and any other metadata regarding
the application.
One such information is the entry point of our application.
So of the many Java classes that that you see here, which one is the starting point or entry point
when someone tries to run this packaged version of the application.
So that needs to be specified as a main class property within this manifest file.
Once built and distributed, the application can be run on any system with the Java runtime environment
installed using the Java Command.
But if if you're running a jar file, then you use the Java option like this before specifying the file
name.
Now another thing is documentation.
So our code also needs to be documented so that others can easily read and understand the various functionalities.
And for that we use the Java doc utility running the Java Doc command and specifying the source code
as input can help us generate documentation that would look like this.
So it's an HTML version of the documentation of the code that other developers can easily browse through
and read.
So we have seen developing source code, compiling the code into byte codes and then packaging it into
jar files and then generating documentation on that.
So these are kind of the steps that form a build process.
Of course, it usually includes many other steps, such as tests and vulnerability scans and code signing,
etc. But for our purpose, we will keep it simple.
So we have accomplished these tasks using the tools part of the Java development kit directly, like
the Java Sea Command, the JAR Command and the Java Dock Command.
So these build processes can get really huge and complex when large applications and hundreds of developers
are working on the same application at the same time.
So there are different developers pushing in code updates to code at the same time and then builds are
kicking off.
We'll need to compile all those different source codes together into classes and then need to package
them together and as well as generate documentation, etc..
So this, this can get really complex when there are when there are so many developers and when the
application is really complex.
So that's where build tools can help you automate much of these processes.
Some of the popular build tools for Java or MAVEN, GRADLE and, and these tools use configuration files
where you can specify the steps that you want your the build tool to automate, such as the steps in
your build process.
And these tools automatically execute these steps in that particular order that you have defined.
So let's see an example with Ant.
Right.
So we will see an example of a building, an application, and then automating that with Ant.
So on the left here you see are the steps that we executed manually so far.
So these are the same commands that we discussed.
Now these can be converted into an ant build configuration file, which is in an XML format, and it
looks like this.
So each section of this XML file has a target action specified to perform a task.
The first section for compiling the second section is for generating documentation.
The third section is for creating a deployable jar file.
So once the build configuration file is created, we run the build using the command line utility.
This will result in running all the three specified actions, one after the other, and generating the
outputs such as the documentation files and jar files as required.
So if you look at each of these in the compiled section, we're specifying what the source directory
is.
So this is where all of our source code is, right?
The human readable format of the source code and after compilation, the class files are put into this
destination directory.
So this is the path where class files are in the next step.
This is for generating documentation.
Here again, we specify the the source code, and here you can have different filters where you can
filter specific files out.
And then here you have a destination directory where the generated source code will be stored.
So all the HTML files, the the documentation in the HTML format will go into this.
Similarly, at the end, the packaging section here, the name of the section is JAR.
So these names could really be anything.
This is what you will be calling here.
And this is the base directory where the builds are build files are, which is basically the class file.
So a jar requires the different class files the path to that.
So that's this what's here.
And the destination file is my class jar.
So that's going to be the final packaged output, right?
And then here you can see the main section is the main is where the program starts and you're saying
the dependencies are compiled and docs.
So each or each one is a dependency.
So if you simply run and it just runs all those commands, all those, all these steps one after the
other.
So in case you only want to run specific sections, not all of them, for example, in this case I just
want to run, compile and jar and skip the documentation section.
Then I can specify the name of the target actions here in the command like this.
Okay, so that's a high level overview of build tools, and we cannot get into more details about each
of these tools because that's going to take a long time.
But they all kind of work the same way.
For example, if you browse around GitHub and look for where is that Java applications, you'll see
different configuration files.
So all Java applications come with one of these configuration files.
In case of Maven, you have the Palm XML file where you have.
The build instructions configured, and these repositories also have the instructions to run that build.
For example here this is MAVEN running with a clean and install.
Similarly, here's an example of GRADLE, another project that uses Gradle build, and here you have
the configuration Gradle Gradle configuration.
And here's the command that's used to build the application and then run the application.
So these build tools make it very easy for others to easily build and run applications so you don't
really have to follow hundreds of steps.
It kind of automates all of those.
So that's it for now in this section.
That's all what we're going to discuss about Java and build processes.
So now you know the basics of how to go about building and running a Java program, you know, what
Java runtime environment is and what a Java development kit is.
You know what it means when someone says compile a program and you know what it means when you're asked
to package a Java application into your files and when someone says, you know, we use and for builds
or Gradle or Maven, you know exactly what they're talking about.
When you go through a DevOps course and you're shown automating a build process with pipelines or container
using an application with Docker, you will now know what those commands mean, what they're the commands
that they're automating right in the pipeline, and you'll know what you're trying to do.
So that's the goal of this lecture and this section.
It was great having you here and I will see you in the next lecture after the labs.
So head over to the labs and practice working with builds in Java.