In this section, we will look into the basics of a Node.js application.
Before talking about Node.js, let me quickly introduce JavaScript.
So in the past websites looked like this playing with mostly just text links and probably some images.
It was built with basic HTML code and some CSS to style it.
JavaScript is the technology that drives modern web development from a plain text website.
JavaScript allowed us to build websites that are intelligent and interactive, such as building calculators,
fun animations, games, graphs, running predictions on the web, running mathematic, mathematics
calculations, etc. So JavaScript made it possible to develop web pages that can almost do anything
that you can really think of today that you can do on a web page.
JavaScript paved the way for different client side frameworks like jQuery, Angular, JS, React, JS,
Vue.js, Enbridge's Backbone, JS, etc..
But remember, all of these are client side technologies.
That is, they're used to build web pages that would eventually run on clients or users systems like
our laptops.
They didn't actually have anything to do with the application server itself.
In the past server side code or the back end code, as you call it, was mostly only on Java or Python
Ruby.
So you had one of these on the server side and then you'd have a JavaScript based framework that would
run on the client side in the browsers.
Node.js took JavaScript out of the web browsers and onto the server side.
Node.js is a server side JavaScript environment that can be used to develop applications such as Web
servers using JavaScript.
An important feature that distinguishes Node.js from others is its ability to handle a large number
of concurrent connections by implementing a non blocking i o model.
Now Node.js is open source and free and it's compatible with different platforms like Windows, Linux,
Unix, Mac OS, etc..
Here are the different versions of Node.js.
As of this recording, the latest version is 13.
To install Node.js, follow instructions in the Node.js documentation site.
The node source repository contains binary distributions for all different Linux flavors.
So we will look at an example for CentOS here on CentOS.
First, add the repository for Node.js and then use the YAML, install Node.js command to to install
it.
Once installed successfully.
Node is the command line utility run the node v command to list the node version.
So if you're given an application written in Node.js as you see it here on the right, then to run it,
simply run the node command followed by the file name.
As I was saying, working with the code inside of these application files are out of scope for this
course.
So we're not really going to look into coding.
Our focus is understanding how to deploy a Node.js application when given a set of code and not really
read through and understand the code itself.
So that's it for this lecture.
Head over to the labs and practice working with the basics of installing and running a simple node application.
And I will see you in the next lecture.
We will where we will talk more about Node.js and packages.