Okay, So we have now set up Node.js and we're ready to rock.
So it is also important to learn a little bit about libraries and dependencies and package management
in Node.js, because this is one area that you might struggle with when trying to deploy an application.
You might run into dependency errors, unable to find libraries and mismatching versions.
So we'll see how those are fixed.
Now, as with any programming language, Node.js supports a large number of packages or libraries that
are developed by the either the core team or contributed by the community.
These could be packages for working with files, hosting web servers, interacting with databases,
implementing security, etc. And all of these packages are available at a public repository at PM JS
dot com and PM, which stands for Node Package Manager allows developers to develop new reusable packages
or modules and share them on the public repository.
Other developers can then download and use these on their projects.
There are thousands of packages available in the repository today.
So KPMG's Dotcom is the website that hosts the public repository.
When you install Node.js, a command line utility called NPM is also installed automatically that helps
you interact with NPM repository, run the NPM v command to list the version of the NPM CLI utility.
Note that this could be different from the Node.js version.
Use the NPM search command along with the name of the package to search for a package that will list
all packages available by that name.
A brief description.
The author and date it was published.
Once you identify what package needs to be installed, install it using the NPM install command.
When you install a package and PM installs it under the directory node, underscore modules under your
present working directory, a directory by the name of the package is created and all files are created
under it, such as the license file, the read me file, and the code is located under the lib directory.
There's also a file named package JSON, and that is the file that contains the metadata for that package,
such as its name version, its author is get repository, etc. This is a useful file that you can inspect
in case you are troubleshooting issues with dependency errors.
So you can install packages for two purposes.
One for the application you are building or two globally across the system.
What we just did was install a package for the application that we are working on.
When you run the NPM install command without any options, it assumes that you want to install the package
in the current directory.
So for example, our application is coded in a file named app.
US within that file you can import this package using the required function like this and specifying
the package name.
Well, that's just about how much we're we're going to read.
Worry about the code for now.
When we import a package into our application, like this node first looks at the local node underscore
modules directory under our application for that package.
In this case, it finds the file under the node modules directory.
So it uses that.
If not, it looks for the package under the global directory.
So to see the list of paths that node looks at, look at the module paths configuration of node.
By running this command, it will list all the paths node would look at while importing a package.
You can also install a package globally to be available across a system for this run the same and PM
install command but with the dash g option.
So there are two types of modules built in modules and external modules Built in modules are installed
automatically when Node.js runtime is installed for the first time and is available for use.
They're located at the location user lib node modules on Linux systems.
Some examples are listed here.
The first module is used to handle file systems.
The HTTP module is used to host an HTTP server and the OS module is used to work with operating systems.
There are many more of such modules.
Some examples of external modules are expressed, which is a popular web framework used to develop web
applications.
React is used to create front end user interfaces.
The debug module is used to debug applications and these can be searched and installed using the NPM
search and install commands as we saw in the previous lectures.
So an application or a package has a set of dependencies and scripts associated with it.
These are recorded in the package JSON file.
So when developers build an application, they create this file in the root of the project.
This file, as we discussed, has the name and version of the application along with a list of dependencies.
The dependencies are packages or modules that this application requires.
The packages also has their versions defined.
Installing different on or unsupported dependencies can cause applications to not work, so it is important
that these versions are defined properly.
Also, remember that your application may have a package JSON file with the list of dependencies and
each of these packages may have their own package JSON file with their own dependencies.
So don't get confused between the two.
Okay, so that's it for this lecture.
And we now head over to the labs and practice working with LPM.
So we search packages, explore existing packages, install additional packages and run applications
that use these packages, work with dependency management, etc..