In this section, we will look into the basics of Python.
Python is a free and open source cross-platform compatible programming language as we discussed before.
Once the application is developed, Python requires the python interpreter to run the application.
To download python interpreter, go to the downloads page on the Python website and download the Python
installer for your operating system.
Now, it's important to note about the two different versions of Python.
Version two was released in the year 2000 and its development ended in the year 2010, and Python version
three was initially released in the year 2008 and continues to be developed today.
Python three introduced considerable changes with respect to improvements and fixes from Python two
that programs written in Python two required a lot of changes to be made to run in Python three.
Python three did not guarantee backward compatibility with its predecessor, so applications had to
be carefully migrated or ported to Python three.
So remember that applications developed in Python two must be run on a python two interpreter and applications
written in Python three must be run in a python three interpreter.
Python three also introduced a whole set of new features which pave the way to support modern technologies
such as machine learning, data science and artificial intelligence.
Some operating systems come pre-installed with Python, so run the Python two or Python three commands
to verify if it's installed properly.
If not instal python using the yum installed python command.
Note that python two is available with the package named python two and python 3.6.
Version is available as python three six.
You can have both versions of python installed on the same system at the same time.
Once installed to invoke the python two interpreter, simply run the python two command and to invoke
the python three interpreter.
Simply run the python three command.
You will then be inside the interpreter where you can type in python commands and work with Python.
And if you want to exit out of that mode type exit.
To come out of it.
Note that some Python installations may also have installed as just Python without the version.
And Python without any version in the command line usually defaults to the whatever version was first
installed.
Sometimes it could be Python two, or it could be Python three.
To get the full version of installed Python run the python command for the respective version followed
by the Dash v option.
The V is in capital letter.
So here you can see that the Python two version is 2.7.16.
And Python three version is 3.6.8.
To run a python program, use the python command followed by the program name.
In this case, we have a simple Hello world program running the Python command, followed by the program
name runs the program and prints the message.
Well, head over to the labs and work with installing Python and run a sample application in Python.
And in the next lecture we will talk about dependencies and builds in in Python.