In this lecture, we will look into the basics of package management in Python.
Pip is the package manager for Python.
When you install Python, it also installs PIP automatically.
And as we discussed earlier, we can have two separate versions of Python installed on the same host.
In this case we have Python version two and version three.
And so you will have two separate versions of PIP as well.
You'll have one for version two and another for version three.
So you have two for Python two and PIP three for Python three.
And if you run the PIP command along with the Dash v option, just like the python command at the end
of that of the output, you can also see the version that it works for.
So this one is for 2.7 and this runs for 3.4, Python 3.6.
But the version of PIP itself is different, remember?
So this is PIP version 9.0.3 and this as well.
So in some cases you may have the command just simply as PIP.
So if you don't know if it's pointing to Pip two or Pip three, you could run the PIP command with the
version flag and it will tell you what version of Python that is pointing to.
So this is important.
Sometimes this can get mixed up.
So you might be working on a Python three application and you might just run use the PIP command as
a is to install libraries and it'll install it in the python two dependencies folders.
So to install a package using PIP, run the PIP install command and specify the package name.
In this case, we're trying to install a package by the name Flask.
Flask is a popular web framework for Python and it helps you develop web applications.
We'll see that in one of the upcoming lectures.
So when Python is installed, it creates a directory structure like this.
A directory is created for each version of Python under the user lib path.
This is so when packages are installed using a specific version of PIP, they are placed under the right
python version.
So when you install a python package, it installs it under the user lib python path.
Under the side packages directory, a separate directory is available for each version of python packages.
Could also be 32 bit or 64 bit, so a separate path is available for 64 bit packages.
So in this case FLASK is a 64 bit package.
So and we installed it for Python version two because PIP points to Python version two and so it gets
installed under user lib 60 for Python two and side packages.
So this is for 32 bit packages and this is for 64 bit packages.
And inside each of them you have separate path for 2.7, 3.6.
So this is especially important to note because you'll most likely run into issues where you install
packages and your application still cannot find the packages.
So you can actually go in and search and in this path and find out where it is, where it was installed.
And that will help you in troubleshooting.
So let me explain a bit more about that.
So to see the location where a particular package is installed, run the show command and provide the
package name.
In this case, when you run the pipe show Flask command, it tells you the location where that particular
package is installed.
So as I said, user lib, 64, Python 2.7 and side packages.
So once installed, a package is imported into the code using the import statement.
When a package is imported within an application, Python looks under a set of directories for the package.
So to get a list of paths that Python looks for, when it looks for a package, you could print the
easiest path property using this piece of code that's given here.
This is the default location where the python interpreter would look for packages.
So in case you installed packages and and it can't find them, these are some of the commands that you
can use to identify the cause of the issue.
So in this case, these are the paths that it's going to look at for the packages.
When you do a import flask, it's actually going to look this go this path and then it's eventually
going to find it under this path, which is loop 64, Python 2.7 site packages.
And if it's not able to find it anywhere, then you probably installed it for the wrong version of Python
or in a different path.
And that path is not available here and you can use this command to troubleshoot those kind of issues.
Okay.
And this is how you import.
A Python package into the source code.
So using the import command.
Okay, So large applications have many, many different packages to be installed.
So in that case, instead of running the install command multiple times like this, you can either run
a single command with all the packages, package names in it, or a better approach would be to move
all the package details inside a file named requirements txt and then run the PIP install command,
but this time passing the requirements txt file using the dash r option.
So what happens is when you run the single command, now Pip is going to go through this file and install
each of these dependencies.
So.
Um, this way your all your dependencies are stored in a requirements or text file, and then it can
be checked in into your source code repository as well, so that when another developer downloads the
application, you can simply get started by running the a single PIP install for requirements command.
And if any new packages are to be added to the application, you simply go in and add it to the requirements
file and then check that into your source code repository.
Another best practice is to specify the version of these packages as well.
Like this, if you don't specify that, Python will always install the latest stable version of a package.
Now, for some reason, if the new version of the package introduced a change that is incompatible with
the rest of your application, there are chances that it would break your application.
So in almost all Python projects you will find a similar requirement file with version numbers inside
that.
And so when you see when you are given the source code of an application and you see the requirements
file, you now know what that what that file is used for and what to do with that file.
So when a newer version of a package is available and the current version needs to be updated, run
the install command with the upgrade option like this and to uninstall a package, run the uninstall
command and specify the package name.
There are a few other package managers as well with Python and such as Easy Install was the original
way of installing Python packages.
So a set of tools called setup tools are used to package python code into zipped format called eggs.
The easy install package manager can then be used to search, find and install these packages.
So think of eggs as jars in Java if you are familiar with it.
As we have discussed in one of the previous lectures about about Java where we use jars to jar commands
to package application into a single single file, It's similar to what eggs are in Python, so once
you get the eggs, either use the easy install utility or just by downloading the binary and placing
them in a path where python looks for dependencies as we saw a few slides before and your application
will be able to import these packages so you don't really have to unpack an egg.
You can just simply download the egg file and place it in a location where python can find it and it'll
just use that without having to unpackaged it.
And then came a wheel.
So wheels are like eggs, as in they are also zip files too, but they must be unpacked before installing.
So wheels have an extension.
WHL and packages packaged as wheels can be installed using python like this as you would with the other
python packages.
So that's it for now.
Head over to the labs and practice working with python packages.
In this lab you'll identify you'll work with package management tools where you'll identify the list
of packages to be installed, identify the location where the packages are installed, work with different
versions of PIP and upgrade and uninstall packages and work with requirements file, etc. So head over
to the labs and I'll see you in the next lecture.