In this section, we will learn how to install TerraForm.
TerraForm can be downloaded as a single binary or an executable file from the TerraForm download section
in w w w.
Dot terraform i.
O.
Installing their form is as simple as downloading this file and copying it to the system path.
Once installed.
We can check the version by running the command TerraForm version.
The latest version of TerraForm as of this recording is 0.13 and will be making use of this version
throughout the course.
TerraForm is supported on Windows, Mac and several other Linux based distributions.
Please note that all the examples and labs used in this course will make use of TerraForm running on
a Linux machine and specifically the version 0.13.
And that's it.
We can now start deploying resources using TerraForm.
As stated earlier, TerraForm uses configuration files which are written in SQL to deploy infrastructure
resources.
These files have a dot F extension and can be created using any text editor such as notepad or notepad
plus plus for windows or command line text editors such as Vim or Mac in Linux.
Or it could be any ID of your choice.
So what is the resource?
A resource is an object that therefore manages.
It could be a file on a local host, or it could be a virtual machine on the cloud, such as an easy
to.
Instance.
Or it could be services like SSE three buckets x Dynamo db tables.
I am users or I am groups, roles, policies, etc..
Or it could be resources on major cloud providers such as the Compute and app engine from GCP databases
on Azure, Azure Active Directory, etc..
There are literally hundreds of resources that can be provisioned across most of the cloud and on premise
infrastructure using TerraForm.
We will look into some of these examples later in this course.
But for the first few sections, we will stick to two very easy to understand resources, the local
file type of resource, and a special kind of resource called a random pit.
It is important to use a simple resource type to really understand the basics of TerraForm, such as
the lifecycle of resources, the SQL format, etc. Once we gain a good understanding of the basics,
we can easily apply that knowledge to other real life use cases and we will see that in later sections
of this course.