In this lecture, we will learn how to update and destroy infrastructure using TerraForm.
In the previous lecture, we saw how to create a local file.
Now let us see how we can update and destroy this resource using TerraForm.
First, let us try to update this resource.
Let us add in a file permission argument to update the permission of the file to 0700 instead of the
default value of 0777.
This will remove any permission for everyone else except the owner of the file.
Now, if we run TerraForm Plan, we will see an output like this.
From the output, we can see that the resource will be replaced.
The minus plus symbol in the beginning of the resource name in the plan implies that it will be deleted
and then recreated.
The line with the command that reads Forces replacement is responsible for the deletion and recreation.
And in this example, this is caused by the file permission argument that we added to the configuration
file.
Even though the change we made was trivial, TerraForm will delete the old file and then create a new
file with the updated permissions.
This type of infrastructure is called an immutable infrastructure.
We saw this briefly when we discussed the different types of ICC tools.
If you want to go ahead with the change, use beta form, apply command and then type.
Yes.
When prompted.
Upon confirmation the existing file is deleted and recreated with the new permissions.
To delete the infrastructure completely, run the TerraForm destroy command.
This command shows the execution plan as well.
And you can see the resource and all of its arguments have a minus symbol next to them.
This indicates that the resource will be destroyed.
To go ahead with the destroy.
Confirm?
Yes, in the prompt.
This will delete all the resources in the current configuration directory.
In this example, it deletes the file slash root slash pets.
Dot.
TXT.
That's it for this lecture.
Let's head over to the Hands-On Labs and practice updating and deleting infrastructure resources using
TerraForm.