Hello and welcome to the Ultimate DevOps Bootcamp course.
If you have been procrastinating about starting your DevOps journey, this is the perfect time and the
perfect course.
My name is Chad Monomyth, and me, along with my fellow instructors, will be assisting you through
this course.
In this course you'll not just learn theory, but you'll learn by doing with the help of our hands on
labs.
Every topic is followed by a hands on lab created specifically for that topic to help you gain hands
on experience.
If you're an absolute beginner, we'll start with the basic prerequisites on systems administration
like Linux and networking.
Ultimately, I.T. and DevOps is there to serve applications to end users.
And if you started your career on the infrastructure side of things, and if you have been a person
who hated coding and development, then you might find it especially difficult to follow some of the
concepts in DevOps, like what's front end and back end in a software, What are APIs, what's a build
process, what is packaging, what are dependencies, what are environment variables, etc. So although
you don't have to learn coding, it's good to have some idea about these from the perspective of a few
of the most popular programming languages.
So that's what we see next.
We see the basics of Java, Node.js, Python.
Again, there is no coding or programming involved.
We will only see how to take an application written in these languages and what are the necessary steps
required to build and host them in a server.
Developers collaborate on Git and Git is kind of at the center of DevOps pipeline or infrastructure
as code.
So Git I would say is the most important piece to learn.
So we have a short module on that and we then move on to containers and Docker and container orchestration
with Kubernetes.
Now many DevOps tools like Ansible, Docker and Kubernetes use YAML files to define configurations.
So understanding the basics of YAML is a must and you will learn YAML with a set of hands on exercises.
Now we learn about microservices architecture.
After this, we then move on to learning automation tools like Ansible and TerraForm, and finally we
learn about Python.
Now it's important to learn at least one programming language and you learn all of this by doing so
together you can stack up hundreds of hours of hands on experience by the time you're at the end of
this course.
If you run into any issues.
We have a thriving community to support you and we are so sure you'll benefit from our courses that
we offer a 30 day money back guarantee.
So there is nothing for you to lose.
I'm very excited to get started and I will see you in the first lesson.