Let's talk about what Sy said is why it's important, why we need it in today's world and the different
components behind it.
So first things first continuous integration and continuous deployment.
Delivery is a way to take code, package it up and deploy it to a system.
That system could be serverless, like a lambda function or an Azure function could be a virtual machine
or an easy to instance.
It could be some container running somewhere with Docker, etc. So let's break down what PSI is, what
CD is, and what CD is.
So first things first, continuous integration, which is your CI process.
And really the gist of it is you take the code and you package it up.
So I want you to think of continuous integration kind of like a gift that you're wrapping.
So the gift comes in pieces.
Maybe you order it on Amazon and then once you get that gift, you take it out of the box and then you
put that gift together.
Maybe it's like a toy chest or a toy box or something like that.
So you have a bunch of screws, maybe you have some nails, you got to go get that screwdriver, make
sure all the screws are in properly.
And then once you do that and once everything is in where it's supposed to be, then the gift gets wrapped
in wrapping paper.
That's really your CI process.
You're taking the code, you're packaging it up, and then you are giving it to the CD process to continuous
deployment or continuous delivery process.
So there are a few key pieces of CI.
The first is you package up that code.
So let's say you're in GitHub and you have a GitHub repository and maybe that GitHub repository has
a bunch of different folders or directories with all different pieces of code in it inside of your CI
process.
It does a sort of clone of that GitHub repository and then it packages it up, it puts it in that box,
it wraps it up like that gift.
The next thing is typically in your CI process is where you test your code.
So like unit test, you would run automatically integration tests, etc. Pretty much you want to make
sure that that code is ready to go before you even try to deploy it.
You want to make sure that it passes all your tests.
You want to make sure that it has all of the dependencies that are needed.
Imagine trying to deploy an application and then once it's deployed, you realize, Oh, it's missing
this go library or it's missing this python package.
And then the last thing is you would typically run any type of security checks against the code.
So, for example, let's say you're using some type of security lender or sonar cube or something like
that.
This is really the process, your CI process, where you would run those security checks against the
code.
Okay, So now let's talk about continuous delivery and continuous deployment.
Now, don't worry.
We will be talking about the differences between continuous delivery and continuous deployment, I believe,
coming up in the next slide.
So the CD process is where you deploy the code to some system.
That system could be, again, serverless.
It could be a container.
It could be a virtual machine.
It could even be bare metal.
It doesn't have to actually be in the cloud.
It could be on prem running in, I don't know, VMware ESXi, for example.
So I want you to think about that gift that you wrapped in the C section.
Once that gift is wrapped, it can be given to a person.
So you take that gift, that wrapped gift, you put it that gift in your car, you drive it to the person's
house and you deliver it to their house, You deliver it, you maybe put it on, I don't know, the
front step or something like that.
But the point is, you take the gift, that packaged gift and you drive it to the person's house, you
deliver it.
So that's that CD process.
Once the code is packaged and tested and all that good stuff in the CI process, you then deliver it
to whatever system you're running on.
Now, really quick, I do just want to chat about the differences between continuous deployment and
continuous delivery.
Now, the reason why I bring this up is because a lot of people don't talk about this.
You know, you always hear about the CD process or the CD process, but not the differences between
CD and CD.
So continuous delivery is there's essentially some button somewhere to deploy the code for some manual
intervention.
So, for example, let's say the code goes through the CI process and it's ready to be deployed.
Well, then you would go into Jenkins and you would click the button to deploy the code.
So there is manual intervention.
Obviously, it's not as manual as, you know, taking the packaged code and RDP or SSH into a server,
copying the code where it's supposed to be manually running the code.
It's of course not like that.
Everything is still automated.
The only thing that's not automated is that button click.
Somebody has to physically log in to Jenkins and click that button, or quite frankly, any other CSP
platform.
It's all the same when it comes to continuous delivery.
Now continuous deployment means the code gets automatically deployed after the CI process.
So let's say that you're committing and pushing some code to GitHub.
Once it gets pushed to GitHub, the CI process would automatically kick off and then once the code builds,
the CD process would automatically run and it would be deployed to your, again, your container or
your VM or serverless or wherever.
So the key differences here are continuous delivery.
There's some magical button that you have to press to deploy the code.
Continuous deployment, it's all about just everything is automatic.
There's zero human intervention.
So, you know, if code gets pushed at 2:00 in the afternoon to GitHub, guess what?
It's going to also be deployed to your system.
So the key pieces of KD is in number one.
It ensures that you are authenticated to the system or wherever you're deploying, let's say, to point
to a system.
Let's say you deploying to, I don't know, AWS or Azure, you would ensure that you are authenticated
during the CD process.
The next bit is ensure that the code that's being deployed is working as expected once deployed.
So a lot of people, what they do as part of the CD process is inside of there you have tests to actually
run a test against the system to make sure that the application is running.
If it's not running the way that it's supposed to, the CD process would fail.
Well, that's it for this lecture.
We'll see you in the next.