There are obviously a ton of different tools out there, free paid enterprise.
All of that stuff.
There's a ridiculous amount nowadays, So why?
Jenkins Well, we're going to go over these bits, but I want you to think open source a ton of plugins
completely free.
And if you want to pay a little bit of money, there are some enterprise options as well.
So first things first, Jenkins itself, the full CI CD suite, all of the plugins, the ability to
deploy it, the ability to host it yourself, it is all 110% free.
You can host it on a VM, on a container.
You could even host it locally for development purposes if you want.
I wouldn't recommend for production purposes hosting it on your Mac or on your Windows device, but
you could if you wanted to.
And again, you don't have to pay anything to actually use the software.
This is open source.
This is 100% free.
Next.
There are a ton of plug ins, specifically 1000 plus plug ins, which to be honest.
Is definitely a lot more than a lot of other platforms, and there's a good reason for that.
Jenkins has been around for a really long time.
People have created a ton of plugins for it, primarily because remember it is open source and because
it's open source, you can create all of the different plugins for it whenever you want to.
And with all of the plugins you pretty much going to have a plugin for every major DevOps tool, public
cloud provider programming language like Go and Python if you need support for it, it's all there.
And if it's not, guess what?
It's open source.
You could create yourself.
Now if you want enterprise like you want support, you want a number to call.
You want the ability to not have to host it yourself.
You want it more like a SAS style platform.
Enterprise options for Jenkins are available.
Well, that's it for this lecture we'll see in the next.