So now that we know a little bit about what it is, why Jenkins is a great free option, let's actually
talk about Jenkins.
So I am here at the Jenkins web page right now.
You could go to w w w dot Jenkins i o and see the same thing that I'm seeing.
So first things first, we have the mascot here.
I always thought this was quite funny, you know, it's like a butler type of thing, but it makes sense,
right?
The Jenkins mascot is a butler and by definition, secede is doing the work for you.
That's.
That's the whole idea here.
We're taking the manual tasks out, that manual effort, and we're giving it to secede.
So when we're at the Web page here and by the way, I just I'm going to click on a few of these things
here, and we're going to go into depth with plug ins and all that good stuff.
So this is just a high level.
If you don't already know it, don't worry about it.
We will be going through all of that inside of this course.
So first things first, we have the blog here, and this is a blog that goes into everything that's
happening inside of Jenkins today, vulnerabilities.
We have some how to guides like use containers as build agents, all of that fun stuff.
Next, we have a documentation and Jenkins documentation is actually really, really solid when you
click on installing Jenkins, for example, and we got a bunch of stuff here, let's say maybe we click
on Docker and we have all of the documentation needed to install Jenkins via Docker, the prerequisites
that are needed, installing Jenkins using Mac OS and Linux.
We keep going here.
We got all the commands that are needed.
So the documentation for Jenkins, it's definitely some of the best documentation that I've worked with
so far.
Next we have plugins, so plugins again, we're going to go through this, but plugins are a way for
you to connect with Jenkins to other systems.
So for example, if we just search Azure here, we can see that there are several different plugins,
but for example, maybe you want to use the Azure Cloud or the A-Z CLI to run any type of automated
tasks in Azure.
Well, there's a plugin for that.
You can use the Azure CLI with Jenkins, just like there are a ton of different other plugins, things
like for Azure App Services, Key Vault, Azure Container Services or HCI, a whole bunch of good stuff.
Next we have community and of course this is extremely important.
We have things like meetups contributing to writing the code, any help that's needed documentation
testing, connecting to the world about Jenkins.
There is obviously a vast community of Jenkins users, engineers, managers, all of that good stuff,
and this is where you could find those people.
Next.
If we click on Subprojects, we can see a few different other projects that Jenkins is working on as
well.
Things like Jenkins configuration as Code Jenkins area meetups, right?
So that would be under community and all that.
And then of course we have the about security press, we have the roadmap here which tells us exactly
what's happening with Jenkins.
So in short, if you want to get started with Jenkins, which we of course are in this course, but
if you want to get started on your own, play around anything, This is the place to do it, to chat
with the community, to find any plugins that are needed, any documentation.
This is all where you need to start and you don't have to go anywhere else.
You can stay right at Jenkins dot I.
Oh well, that's it for this lecture we'll see in the next.